<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A collection of acts of Parliament, charters, trials at law, and judges opinion concerning those grants to the Colledge of Physicians London, taken from the originals, law-books, and annals, commanded by Sir Edward Alston Kt., president, and the elects and censors / made by Christopher Merret ...</title>
            <author>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 227 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 70 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1836</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18709</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12112311</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12112311</idno>
            <idno type="VID">54229</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50695)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 54229)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 871:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A collection of acts of Parliament, charters, trials at law, and judges opinion concerning those grants to the Colledge of Physicians London, taken from the originals, law-books, and annals, commanded by Sir Edward Alston Kt., president, and the elects and censors / made by Christopher Merret ...</title>
                  <author>Merret, Christopher, 1614-1695.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 135 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royal College of Physicians of London.</term>
               <term>Medical laws and legislation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:54229:1"/>
            <p>A COLLECTION OF Acts of Parliament, Charters, Trials at Law, and Judges Opinions Concerning Thoſe GRANTS to the Colledge of Phyſicians <hi>London,</hi> taken from the <hi>Originals, Law-Books,</hi> and <hi>Annals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Commanded By Sir <hi>EDWARD ALSTON</hi> K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Preſident, and the Elects and Cenſors.</p>
            <p>Made by <hi>CHRISTOPHER MERRETT,</hi> Fellow and Cenſor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:54229:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:54229:2"/>
            <head>CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ACts, 3. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>Search for the Original, 122, 123</item>
               <item>ACts, 14, 15. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 3.</item>
               <item>ACts, 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 14, 18.</item>
               <item>ACts, 34, 35. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 27.</item>
               <item>ACts, 1. <hi>Mariae</hi> 30.</item>
               <item>Chirurgeons and their Liberties, 18.</item>
               <item>Charters, 10. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 3.</item>
               <item>Confirmed, 9, 11, 19, 30, 34, 39, 40, 41, 61.</item>
               <item>Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> for Anatomies, 34.</item>
               <item>King <hi>James,</hi> 37.</item>
               <item>to be confirmed next Parl. 62.</item>
               <item>An Abridgment of it, 134.</item>
               <item>Allowed in the Exchequer. 65.</item>
               <item>His Letter in proſecution of it, 130.</item>
               <item>The like from his Councel, 133.</item>
               <item>Tryals, Colledge <hi>verſus</hi> Gardiner, 67, 110, 112.</item>
               <item>Tryals, Colledge <hi>verſus</hi> Dr. Bonham, 75.</item>
               <item>Bugge, 65,</item>
               <item>Tryals, Colledge <hi>verſus</hi> Barton, 101.</item>
               <item>Tryals, Colledge <hi>verſus</hi> Jenkins and Read, 113.</item>
               <item>Tryals, Colledge <hi>verſus</hi> Barker, 122.</item>
               <item>Tryals, Colledge <hi>verſus</hi> Trigge, 124.</item>
               <item>Tryals, Colledge <hi>verſus</hi> Blanke, 124, 133.</item>
               <item>Tryals, Colledge <hi>verſus</hi> Butler, 133.</item>
               <item>Bonham <hi>verſus</hi> Colledge, 79.</item>
               <item>Butler <hi>verſus</hi> Colledge, 106.</item>
               <item>Concerning the Kings Phyſicians, 129.</item>
               <item>Lord chief Juſtice Pophams Reſolves, 113.</item>
               <item>Lord Chancellour, Chief Juſtice, and Judges, reſolves, 116.</item>
               <item>Several tryals nonſuits and directions, 122, 123, 124, 133.</item>
               <item>1. Form of a Declaration, 67.</item>
               <item>2. an Information in the Exchequer, 67.</item>
               <item>3. a Warrant to commit to priſon, 101.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="index_of_privileges">
            <pb facs="tcp:54229:3"/>
            <head>PRIVILEGES.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Coll. Incorporated, <hi>pag.</hi> 4, 5.</item>
               <item>To chooſe a Preſident, 5</item>
               <item>To have a Common Seal, 6.</item>
               <item>To purchaſe Lands, 6, 60</item>
               <item>To plead and be impleaded, 6, 124.</item>
               <item>To make by-Laws, 6, 56</item>
               <item>To have a Hall and meetings, 55.</item>
               <item>To impriſon non-payers of fines, 52.</item>
               <item>To have all fines, 53, 57</item>
               <item>To pay 6 l. per annum for thoſe fines, 63.</item>
               <item>Not to be in Inqueſts, juries, &amp;c. 8.</item>
               <item>Freed from Watch, Ward, and Offices, 15.</item>
               <item>Freed from Armes, compare 19, &amp; 22. 61, 126.</item>
               <item>May practiſe Chirurgery, 18.</item>
               <item>Elects to be choſen, 10.</item>
               <item>What Phyſicians they may licence, 11</item>
               <item>Register his office and oath, 57, 58</item>
               <item>Officers to chooſe and ſwear, 58, 59</item>
               <item>Cenſors are to be yearly choſen, &amp; their office concerning Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians and Medicines, 7</item>
               <item>May fine and impriſon for <hi>mala praxis,</hi> 7, 31, 32, 47</item>
               <item>And for that only, 97, 98</item>
               <item>Keepers to receive whom they commit to priſon, 31</item>
               <item>Muſt be ſworn, 16.</item>
               <item>their forfeiture for non-ſwearing and ſearching, 16</item>
               <item>May ſearch Apothecaries, &amp;c. ſhops, 16, 32, 44, 50, 52</item>
               <item>Apothecaries refuſing ſearch, how fined, 17, 33.</item>
               <item>May ſummon, examine, fine, and convent Phyſicians and witneſſes, 45, 51.</item>
               <item>May fine and impriſon witneſſes not appearing, &amp;c. 46</item>
               <item>May ſwear witneſſes, 49.</item>
               <item>May take a bond of 100 l. for no farther practiſe, 59</item>
               <item>May puniſh non admiſſos, and how, 47.</item>
               <item>Diſcovery of offenders, and how, 48</item>
               <item>May convent Apothecaries, &amp;c. 51</item>
               <item>Admitted by the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, 3, 11, 75</item>
               <item>Colledge, 7.</item>
               <item>Biſhops, 2, 3.</item>
               <item>Elects, 11</item>
               <item>Penalty of non admiſſi, 2, 7, 42</item>
               <item>By the Common Law, 66</item>
               <item>In what caſes any perſon may Practiſe, 27.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:54229:3"/>
            <head>ANNO TERTIO HENRICI Octavi.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>CAP. XI.</hi> By whom every Phyſician and Chirurgeon ſhall be allowed.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the King our Soveraign Lord, and to all the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled. For as much as the ſcience and cunning of Phyſick and Chirurgery (to the perfect knowledge where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, be requiſite both great learning and ripe experience) is daily within this Realm exerciſed by a great multitude of ignorant perſons: of whom the greater part have no manner of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight in the ſame, nor in any other kind of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: ſome alſo can no letters on the book, ſo<note place="margin">Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces enſuing by ignorant perſons pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick or Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery.</note> far forth that common Artificers, as Smiths, Weavers, and women boldly, and cuſtomably take upon them great cures, and things of great
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:54229:4"/>
difficulty: in the which they partly uſe ſorcery and witchcraft, partly apply ſuch medicines unto the diſeaſe, as be very noyous, and nothing meet therefore, to the high diſpleaſure of God, great infamy to the Faculty, and the grievous hurt, damage, and deſtruction of many of the Kings liege people: moſt eſpecially of them that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcern the uncunning from the cunning. Be it therefore (to the ſurety and comfort of all manner people) by authority of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Enacted, That no perſon within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<note place="margin">By whom they which practiſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick or Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery in <hi>London,</hi> &amp;c. ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. <hi>St.</hi> 14. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 5. 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 8.</note> of <hi>London,</hi> nor within ſeven miles of the ſame, take upon him to exerciſe, and occupy as a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician or Chirurgeon, except he be firſt examined, approved, and admitted by the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> or by the Dean of <hi>Pauls,</hi> for the time being, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to him or them, four Doctors of Phyſick, and for Chirurgery, other expert perſons in that Faculty, and for the firſt examination ſuch as they ſhall think convenient, and afterward alway four of them that have been ſo approved, upon the pain of forfeiture, for every moneth that they do occupy as Phyſicians or Chirurgeons not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted not examined after the tenour of this Act, of v. li. to be imployed, the one half thereof to the uſe of our Soveraign Lord the King, and the other half thereof to any perſon that will ſue for it by action of debt, in which no wager of Law, nor protection ſhall be allowed.</p>
            <p>And over this, that no perſon out of the ſaid<note place="margin">A Phyſician or Chirurgeon allowed by the Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe.</note> City and precinct of vii. miles of the ſame, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he have been (as is aforeſaid) approved in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:54229:4"/>
the ſame, take upon him to exerciſe and occupy as a Phyſician or Chirurgeon, in any Dioceſe within this Realm, but if he be firſt examined and approved by the Biſhop of the ſame Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, or he being out of the Dioceſe, by his Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car general: either of them calling to them ſuch expert perſons in the ſaid faculties, as their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion ſhall think convenient, and giving their Letters teſtimonials under their Seals to him that they ſhall ſo approve, upon like pain to them that occupy contrary to this Act (as is above ſaid) to be levied and imployed after the form before expreſſed.</p>
            <p>Provided alway that this Act nor any thing<note place="margin">The Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> and <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi>
               </note> therein contained, beprejudicial to the Univerſities of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> or either of them, or to any priviledges granted to them. <hi>Raſt. pla. fol.</hi> 426.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <head>Anno xiiii &amp; xv. <hi>Henrici</hi> octavi.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>CAP. V.</hi> The priviledges and authority of Phyſicians <hi>in London</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN their moſt humble wiſe ſhew unto your Highneſs, your true and faithful ſubjects, and liege men, <hi>John Chambre, Thomas Linacre, Fernan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus de Victoria,</hi> your Phyſicians, and <hi>Nicholas Halſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well, John Fraunces,</hi> and <hi>Robert Yaxley,</hi> and all other
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:54229:5"/>
men of the ſame faculty within the City of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and ſeven miles about, that where your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (by your moſt gracious Letters Pattents, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring date at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the 23. day of <hi>September,</hi>
               <note place="margin">A body cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate of the faculty of Phyſick with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>London</hi> and vii. miles compaſs. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no 10. H.</hi> 8.</note> the tenth year of your moſt noble raign) for the Common-wealth of this your Realm; in due exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing and practiſing of the faculty of Phyſick, and the good miniſtration of medicines to be had, have incorporate and made of us, and of our Company aforeſaid, one body and perpetual Comminalty or Fellowſhip of the faculty of Phyſick, and to have perpetual ſucceſſion and common ſeal, and to chuſe yearly a Preſident of the ſame Fellowſhip and Comminalty, to overſee, rule and govern the ſaid Fellowſhip and Comminalty, and all men of the ſame faculty, with divers other liberties and priviledges, by your Highneſs to us granted, for the Common-wealth of this your Realm, as in your ſaid moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Letters Pattents more at large is ſpecified and contained, the tenour whereof followeth in theſe words.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="letters_patent">
                        <p>
                           <hi>HEnricus</hi> Dei gratia, Rex Angliae &amp; Franciae, &amp; Dominus Hiberniae, Omnibus ad quos prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes literae pervenerint, Salutem. Cum Regii of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficii noſtri munus arbitremur ditionis noſtrae hominum faelicitati omni ratione conſulere: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Id. autem vel in primis fore, ſi improborum conatibus tempeſtive occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus, apprime neceſſarium duximus, improborum quoque hominum, qui medicinam magis avaritiae ſuae
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:54229:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
cauſa quam ullius bonae conſcientiae fiducia profitebuntur, unde rudi &amp; credulae plebi plurima incommoda orian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, audaciam compeſcere. Itáque partim bene inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum civitatum in Italia, &amp; al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is multis nation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bus exemplum imitati, partim gravium virorum Doctorum Joannis Chambre, Thomae Linacre, Fernandi de Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoria medicorum noſtrorum, Nicholai Halſewel, Joannis Franciſci, &amp; Rob. Yaxley, medicorum, ac precipuè reverendiſsimi in Chriſto patris, ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>domini, dom. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae Tituli ſanctae Ceciliae, trans Tiberim ſacroſanctae Romanae Eccleſiae Presbyteri Cardinalis, Eboracenſis Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopi, &amp; Regni Noſtri Angliae Cancellarii chariſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi,<note place="margin">A perpetual Colledge of Phyſicians <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                              <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and gran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ed in London and the Suburbs.</note> ſimi, precibus inclinati, Collegium perpetuum docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; gravium virorum, qui medicinam in urbe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra Londino &amp; ſuburbibus intráque ſeptem millia paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuum, ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ea urbe quaquaverſus publice exerceant, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitui volumus a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>que imperamus. Quibus tum ſui ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noris tum publicae utilitatis nomine, curae ut spera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus erit, malitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ſorum, quorum meminimus, inſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam temeritatémque, tam exemplo gravitatéque ſua deterrere quam per leges noſtras nuper editas, ac per conſtitutiones per idem collegium condendas punire. Quae quo facilius rite peragi poſsint memoratis Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus Johanni Chambre, Thomae Linacre, Fernando de victoria medicis noſtris, Nicholao Halſewell, Joanni, Franciſco, &amp; Roberto Yaxley, medicis conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſsimus, quod ipſi omnéſque homines ejuſdem facultatis de &amp; in civitate praedicta, ſint in re &amp; nomine unum cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus &amp; communitas perpetua, ſive Collegium perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum. Et quod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> eadem communitas ſive collegium ſingulis annis in perpetuum eligere poſsint &amp; facere de communitate illa aliquem providum virum &amp; in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:54229:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
facultate medicinae expertum in praeſidentem ejuſdem<note place="margin">A preſident of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and his office and duty. The Colledge ſhall have perpetual ſucceſſion and a common ſeal. They ſhall be of ability to purchaſe land.</note> Collegii ſive communitatis, ad ſupervidend. recogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendum, &amp; gubernand. pro illo anno Collegium, ſive communitatem praed. &amp; omnes homines ejuſdem facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis &amp; negotia eorundem. Et quod idem praeſidens &amp; collegium ſive communitas habeant ſucceſsionem perpetuam, &amp; commune ſigillum negotiisdict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitatis &amp; praeſidentis in perpetuum ſerviturum. Et quod ipſi &amp; ſucceſſores ſui in perpetuum ſint perſonae habiles &amp; capaces ad perquirendum, &amp; poſsidendum in feodo &amp; perpetuitate terras &amp; tenementa, redditus &amp; alias poſſeſsiones quaſcunque.</p>
                        <p>Conceſsimus etiam eis &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis pro nobis &amp; haeredibus noſtris, quod ipſi &amp; ſucceſſores ſui poſsint perquirere ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>i &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis, tam in dicta urbe quam extra, terras &amp; tenementa quaecunque, annuum valorem duodecim librarum non excedendum. Statuto de alienatione admanum mortuam non obſtante. Et quod ipſi per nomina praeſidentis Collegii, ſeu communita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis facultatis medicinae Lond. pl' itari &amp; impl' itari poſsint coram quibuſcúnque Judicibas in curiis &amp; actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus quibuſcúnque. Et quod praedict. praeſidens &amp;<note place="margin">They muſt ſue and be ſued.</note> Collegium ſive communitas, &amp; eorum ſucceſſores con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationes licitas &amp; honeſtas de ſeipſis ac Statuta &amp; Ordinationes pro ſalubri gubernatione ſuperviſu &amp; correctione Collegii, ſeu communitatis praedictae, &amp; omnium hominum eandem facultatem in dicta civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate<note place="margin">They muſt make lawful aſſemblies, and ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</note> ſeu per ſeptem miliaria in circuitu ejuſdem civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis exercen. ſecundum neceſsitatis exigentiam (quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; quando opus faerit) facere valeant licite &amp; impune, ſine impedimento noſtri, haeredum vel ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſorum noſtror. juſticiariorum, eſcaëtorum, vicecomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:54229:6"/>
&amp; aliorum ballivorum, vel miniſtrorum noſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum haeredum vel ſucceſſorum noſtrorum quorumcunque. Conceſsimus etiam eiſdem praeſidenti &amp; Collegio, ſeu communitati &amp; ſucceſſoribus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuis, quod nemo in dicta<note place="margin">No man ſhall practiſe Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick in Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don or vii. miles thereof, unleſs he be allowed.</note> civitate, aut per ſeptem milliaria in circuitu ejuſdem, exerceat dictam facultatem, niſi ad hoc per dictum praeſidentem &amp; communitatem, ſeu ſucceſſores eorum, qui pro tempore fuerint, admiſſus ſit per ejuſdem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentis &amp; Collegii literas ſigillo ſuo communi ſigil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latas, ſub poena centum ſolidorum pro quolibet menſe, quo non admiſſus eandum facultatem exercuit, dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e nobis &amp; haeredibus noſtris, &amp; dimidium dicto praeſidenti &amp; Collegio applicandum.</p>
                        <p>Praeterea volumus &amp; concedimus pro nobis &amp; ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſoribus noſtris (quantum in nobis eſt) quod per praeſidentem &amp; Collegium praedictae communitatis pro tempore exiſten. &amp; eorum ſucceſſores in perpetuum quatuor ſingulis annis per ipſos eligantur, qui habeant ſuperviſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m &amp; ſcrutinium, correctionem &amp; guberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, omnium &amp; ſingulorum dictae civitatis medico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<note place="margin">Four Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans of London ſhall be year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choſen to have the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſight of the others.</note> utentium facultate medicinae in eadem civitate, ac aliorum medicorum forinſecorum quorumcunque facultatem illam medicinae aliquo modo frequentantium &amp; utentium infra eandem civitatem &amp; ſuburbia ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem, ſive intra ſeptem milliaria in circuitu ejuſdem civitatis, ac punitionem eorundem pro delictis ſuis in non bene exequendo faciendo &amp; utendo illa. Necnon ſuperviſum &amp; ſcrutinium omni modo medicinarum &amp; earum reception. per dictos medicos, ſeu aliquem eorum hujuſmodi ligeis noſtris pro eorum infirmitatibus cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randis, &amp; ſanandis, dandis, imponendis, &amp; utendis quoties &amp; quando opus fuerit pro commodo &amp; utilitate
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:54229:7"/>
eorundem ligeorum noſtrorum. It a quod punitio hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi medicorum utentium dicta facultate medicinae, ſic in praemiſsis delinquentium per fines, amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, &amp; impriſonamenta corporum ſuorum &amp; per alias vias rationalibiles, &amp; congruas exequatur.</p>
                        <p>Volumus etiam &amp; concedimus pro nobis haeredibus &amp; ſucceſſoribus noſtris (quantum in nobis eſt) quod nec praeſidens, nec aliquis de Collegio praedicto medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum, nec ſucceſſores ſui, nec eorum aliquis exercens facultatem illam, quoquo modo in futur. infra civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem<note place="margin">Phyſicians ſhall not be ſummoned in Juries in London. St. 32. H. 8. 40.</note> noſtram praedictam, &amp; ſuburbia ejuſdem ſeu alibi ſummoneantur, aut ponantur neque eorum ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis ſummoneatur, aut ponatur in aliquibus aſsiſis, juratis, inqueſtis, inquiſitionibus, attinctis, &amp; aliis recognitionibus infra dictam civitatem, &amp; ſuburbia ejuſdem impoſterum coram Majore ac vicecom. ſeu coronatoribus dictae civitatis noſtrae pro tempore exiſten<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> capiendum, aut per aliquem officiarium, ſeu mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum ſuum, vel officiarios ſive miniſtros ſuos ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nend. licet iidem jurati, inquiſitiones, ſeu recognitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſummon. fuerint ſuper brevi, vel brevibus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, vel haeredum noſtrorum de recto, ſed quod dicti magiſtri, ſive gubernatores, ac communitas faculta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis antedictae, &amp; ſucceſſores ſui &amp; eorum quilibet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam facultatem exercentes, verſus nos, haeredes &amp; ſucceſſores noſtros, ac verſus majorem &amp; vicecomites civitatis noſtrae praedictae (pro tempore exiſtente) &amp; quoſcúnque officiarios &amp; miniſtros ſuos ſint inde quieti, &amp; penitus exonerati in perpetuum per prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentes.</p>
                        <p>Proviſo quod literae noſtrae, ſeu aliquid in eis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. non cedent in prejudicium civitatis noſtrae L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:54229:7"/>
ſeu libert. ejuſdem. Et hoc abſque fine ſeu fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>do pro praemiſsis, ſeu ſigillat. praeſentium nobis faciend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venda, vel aliqualiter reddenda, aliquo Statuto, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinatione, vel actu in contrarium, ante haec tempora facto, edito, ordinato ſeu proviſo in aliquo non obſtante. In cujus rei teſtimonium has literas noſtras fieri fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus patentes. Teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> meipſo apud Weſtmonaſterium, xxiii. die Sept. An. reg. noſtri x. Per ipſum regem &amp; de data praedicta authoritate Parl.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Tunſtall.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>ANd for ſo much that the making of the ſaid Corporation is meritorious, and very good for the Common-wealth of this your Realm, it is therefore expedient and neceſſary to provide, that no perſon of the ſaid politique body and Comminalty aforeſaid, be ſuffered to exerciſe<note place="margin">Character of Phyſicians.</note> and practiſe Phyſick, but only thoſe perſons that be profound, ſad, and diſcreet, groundly learned, and deeply ſtudied in Phyſick.</p>
            <p>In conſideration whereof, and for the further authoriſing of the ſame Letters Patents, and alſo<note place="margin">The Kings Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and every Article therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed.</note> enlarging of further Articles for the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth to be had and made: Pleaſeth it your Highneſs, with the aſſent of your Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, to enact, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, and ſtabliſh, that the ſaid Corporation of the ſaid Comminalty and Fellowſhip of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Phyſick aforeſaid, and all and every Grant, Article and other thing contained and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:54229:8"/>
ſpecified in the ſaid Letters Patents, be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, granted, ratified and confirmed in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Parliament, and clearly authoriſed and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the ſame good, lawful, and available to your ſaid body Corporate, and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors for ever, in as ample and large manner as may be taken, thought, and conſtrued by the ſame. And that it pleaſe your Highneſs, with the aſſent of your ſaid Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and the Commons in this your preſent Parliament aſſembled, ſurther to enact, ordain, and eſtabliſh, That the ſix perſons beforeſaid, in your ſaid moſt gracious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Letters Patents na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as principals, and firſt named of the ſaid Comminalty and Fellowſhip, chuſing to them two moe of the ſaid Comminalty from hence forward, be called and cleaped Elects. And that the ſame Elects yearly chuſe one of them<note place="margin">There ſhall be eight E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects of the Phyſicians of <hi>London.</hi>
               </note> to be Preſident of the ſaid Comminalty, and as oft as any of the rooms and places of the ſame Elects ſhall fortune to be void, by death or otherwiſe, then the Supervivors of the ſame elects (within thirty or forty dayes next after the death of them or any of them) ſhall chuſe, name, and admit one or moe, as need ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, of the moſt cunning and expert men, of and in the ſaid faculty in <hi>London,</hi> to ſupply the ſaid room and number of eight perſons. So that he or they that ſhall be ſo choſen, be firſt by the ſaid Supervivors ſtraightly examined, after a form deviſed by the ſaid Elects, and alſo by the ſame Supervivors approved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:54229:8"/>And where that in Dioceſes of <hi>England</hi> out<note place="margin">Phyſicians in other places muſt be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Preſident and three of the Elects. 3. <hi>H.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.</note> of <hi>London</hi> it is not light to find alway men able ſufficiently to examine (after the Statute) ſuch as ſhall be admitted to exerciſe Phyſick in them, that it may be enacted in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That no perſon from henceforth be ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to exerciſe or practiſe in Phyſick through <hi>England,</hi> untill ſuch time that he be examined at <hi>London</hi> by the ſaid Preſident, and three of the ſaid Elects: and to have from the ſaid Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent or Elects Letters teſtimonials of their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving and examination, except he be a Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duat of <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> which hath accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed all things for his form, without any grace. <hi>St. 32. H. 40. 1. M. 9. Coke li. 8. fo.</hi> 14.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="excerpt">
                        <head>At the head of the Parl. Roll.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>PArliamentum inchoatum &amp; tentum in Civitate Londonniar<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quinto decimo die Aprilis Anno</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Prorogation of the Parl.</note> 
                           <hi>Regni metuendiſsimi ac potentiſsimi Regis, Henrici octavi fidei defenſoris quarto decimo &amp; deinde proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatum uſque Weſtm. &amp; ibidem tentum die veneris ultimo die Julii Anno ejuſdem Regis quinto de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimo.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="excerpt">
                        <head>At the foot of the ſame Roll.</head>
                        <p>Die Mercurii viceſimo nono die menſis Julii <hi>C<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> xvi<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>
                           </hi> die Parliamenti peſte in dies magis &amp; magis in urbe Londino ac praeſertim circa palatium Dni Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis de Bridewell invaleſcente Reverendiſsimus Dus
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:54229:9"/>
Legatus Cancellarius exhibuit, oſtendit certis Dnis spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> &amp; temporalib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> quandam Commiſsionem Dni<note place="margin">Adjournment of the Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>.</note> Regis magno ſigillo ſuo ſigillatam cujus tenor ſequitur in hec verba <hi>Henricus</hi> octavus dei gra. Angl. &amp; Franc. Rex. ſidei defenſor &amp; Dns hibn, reverendiſsimo in Xp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ri intimo<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ac dilciſsimo Conſiliario ſuo Dno Thome miſeratione divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> tituli ſce Cecilie ſacorſte Romane Ecclie presbytero Cardinali Ebor Archiep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Angl. primati aplice ſedis etiam de latere legato Cancellar. ſuo ſalt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, Sciatis qd propter infeccoem a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ris peſtiferi ubi<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> per Civitatem nram London<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> invaleſcentem de adviſamento &amp; aſſenſu conſilii nri aſsignavimus vos ac vobis tenore preſencium committimus poteſtatem &amp; auctoritatem spialem ad preſens Parliamentum nrm uſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Weſtm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ad diem Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris prox. futur. prorogand. &amp; continuand. ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> tenend. dantes ulterius univſis &amp; ſingulis tam Archepis Epis Abbib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> Priorib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> Ducib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> Comitib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> vicecomitib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> Baronib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> Militib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> Civib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> Burgenſib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> qm omnibus aliis quor. intereſt ad dictum Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum nrm praedict. conventur. tenore preſenciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſirmiter in mandatis qd vob. in premiſsis faciend. &amp; exequend. pareant obediant &amp; intendant prout decet. In cujus rei Teſtimon. has Iras nras fieri fecimus Patentes, Teſte meipo apud Weſtm. xxix. die Julii Anno Regni nri Quinto decimo. Qua quidem Commiſsione publice per Clicum Parliamenti lca dcus Reverendſsimus Dns Legatus Cancellarius virtute ejuſdem Commiſsionis prorogavit continuavit &amp; adjornavit preſens Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentum uſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Weſtm. ad diem veneris tunc. prox. futur. ibidem<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> tenend. hora conſueta Mandavit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuper dcus Reverendiſsimus Dns Legatus Cancellarius Attorn. &amp; Solicitatori Dui Regis qd aſſumpta
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:54229:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſecum dca Commiſsione die ſequenti accederent in domum Coem intimaturi eis de domo coi dcam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogacoem continuacoem &amp; adjornacoem lcuri<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> coram eis dcam. Commiſsionem ad intencoem quod ipſi Coes diem prefixum apud Weſtm. obſervent prout decet.</p>
                        <p>Die Jovis tertio decimo die menſis Auguſti Cxxx.<note place="margin">Confirmation of this Act, &amp;c.</note> die Parliamenti ad horam ferme ſextam poſt meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diem Dno Rege in ſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o matis. ſedente in Camera vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariter dca Camera Parliamentor. infra pala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ium ſuum Weſtm. aſſidentib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> dnis tam ſpiritualib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> hatib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> ſive robis Parliamentarib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> decoratus preſente etiam de do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo coi ſive inferiori toto populo &amp; plebe Thomas Moore miles eor. Prolocutor. ſilentio prius indict. gravit. eloquent. &amp; magno cum honoris &amp; humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ac modeſt. honeſtament. regiam affatus eſt Matem. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>and. ſummis &amp; merit. quidem extolle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s laudib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> dotes graves nature &amp; fortune eidem ſue Mati. a Deo maximo conceſſas copioſiſsime proſequeba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur magnam in prudencia excellenciam promptam for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinis agilitatem mirum temperancie moderamen di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinum juſtitie ardorem Innatam clemencie erga ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditos benignitatem ſubditor. erga eandem ſuam ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>em amorem obedientiam ac debitam obſervantiam multa per exempla declarabat In cujus rei comproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conem quoddam ſcrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>um Indentatum conceſsionem cujuſdam maximi Subſidii in ſe continen. Regiae Mati. optulit Argumentum certe evidentiſsimum ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me devocois <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>onor. Regem ſubditor. Cui tam excellenti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>racoi fine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>m impoſito dictus Reverendiſsimas Dns Legatus Cancellarius Dno Rege prius conſult. ſingula egregie recitando reſpondebat, Quo fact. idem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verendiſsimus Dns Legatus Cancellarius Acta omnia<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           <pb n="14" facs="tcp:54229:10"/>
in preſenti Parliamento pro bono publico edita &amp; fca ex mandato Dni Regis recitari &amp; publicari juſsit Quibus ex ordine per inicia recitatis &amp; lcis &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis per Clcum Parliamenti reſponcoe ſecdm ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacoes Regiae voluntatis declarativas a dorſo ſcriptas fca dictus Reverendiſsimus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Dns legatus Cancellarius exhortando &amp; admonendo noie Regis omnes Dnos &amp; Coes ſupradictos ut diligent. ordinata &amp; Statuta pro bono publico in hoc Parliamento obſervarent &amp; ab aliis obſervari procurarent poſt grat. ex parte Dni Regis accoem dict. Dnis &amp; Coib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or. diligenti &amp; laborioſa perſeverancia circa expedicoem premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. Parliamentum predictum noie Regio duxit fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end. &amp; diſſolvend. &amp; illud realit. finivit perit &amp; diſſolvit concedens omnib<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>bus</ex>
                           </expan> liberam ad propria rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendi facultatem Anno Regni ſup. dicti metuendiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimi ac potentiſsimi Dni nri Regis Quinto decimo.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <head>Anno xxxii. <hi>Henrici</hi> octavi.</head>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XL.</hi> Priviledges granted to Phyſicians in <hi>London.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN moſt humble wiſe ſhewen unto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty your true and faithful ſubjects, and liege men, the Preſident of the corporation of the comminalty and fellowſhip of the ſcience and faculty of Phyſick in your City of <hi>London,</hi>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:54229:10"/>
and the Commons of the fellowes of the ſame, that whereas divers of them many times having in cure, as well ſome of the Lords of your moſt honourable Councel, and divers times many of the Nobility of this Realm, as many other your faithful and <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>leige people, cannot give their due attendance to them and other their patients with ſuch diligence, as their duty were and is to do, by reaſon they be many times compelled as well within the City of <hi>London,</hi> and Suburbs of the ſame, as in other Towns and Villages, to keep watch and ward, and be choſen to the office of Conſtable, and other offices within the ſaid City, and Suburbs of the ſame, as in other places with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this your Realm, to their great fatigation and unquieting, and to the peril of their Patients, by reaſon they cannot be conveniently attended. It may therefore pleaſe your moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, with the aſſent of your Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament aſſembled, and by authority of the ſame to enact, ordain, and eſtabliſh, that the<note place="margin">The Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in <hi>London</hi> ſhall be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged to bear certain offices there.</note> Preſident of the ſaid Comminalty and fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for the time being, and the commons and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of the ſame, and every fellow thereof that now be, or that any time hereafter ſhall be their ſucceſſors, and the ſucceſſors of every of them, at all time and times after the making of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Act, ſhall be diſcharged to keep any watch and ward, in your ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> or the Suburbs of the ſame, or any part thereof: And that they or any of them ſhall be choſen Conſtable,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:54229:11"/>
or any other officer in the ſaid City or Suburbs. And that if any time hereafter the ſaid Preſident for the time being, or any of the ſaid commons, or fellows for the time being, by any waies or means be appointed or elected to any watch or ward, office of Conſtable, or any other office within the ſaid City or Suburbs, the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, or election to be utterly void and of none effect, any order, cuſtome or law to the contrary before this time uſed in the ſaid City notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>And that it may pleaſe your moſt royal Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, by the authority aforeſaid, that it may be further enacted, ordained and eſtabliſhed, for the Common-wealth and ſurety of your loving ſubjects of this your Realm, in, and for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of medicines to ſuch your ſaid ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects as ſhall have need of the ſame, That from<note place="margin">Four Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhall be choſen year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſearch Apothecary wares in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
                  </note> henceforth the ſaid Preſident for the time being, commons, and fellowes, and their ſucceſſors, may yearly at ſuch time as they ſhall think moſt meet and convenient for the ſame, elect and chooſe four perſons of the ſaid commons, and fellows of the beſt learned, wiſeſt, and moſt diſcreet, ſuch as they ſhall think convenient, and have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the ſaid faculty of Phyſick: and that the ſaid four perſons ſo elected and choſen after a corporal Oath to them miniſtred by the ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, or his Deputy, ſhall and may by vertue of this preſent Act, have full authority and power, as o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ten as they ſhall think meet and convenient, to enter into the houſe or houſes of all, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:54229:11"/>
every Apothecary, now or any time hereafter uſing the myſtery or craft of Apothecary within the ſaid City, only to ſearch, view, and ſee ſuch Pothecary Wares, Drugs, and ſtuffes as the ſaid Apothecaries, or any of them have, or at any time hereafter ſhall have in their houſe or houſes: And all ſuch Wares, Drugs, and ſtuffes as the ſaid four perſons ſhall then find defective, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and not meet, nor convenient to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in any medicines for the health of mans body, the ſame four perſons calling to them the Wardens of the ſaid myſtery of Apothecaries within the ſaid City for that time being, or one of them, ſhall cauſe to be brent, or otherwiſe deſtroy the ſame, as they ſhall think meet by their diſcretion. And if the ſaid Apothecaries, or any of them, at any time hereafter do obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately, or willingly refuſe, or deny the ſaid four perſons yearly elected and choſen, as is before ſaid, to enter into their ſaid houſe or houſes for the cauſes, intent and purpoſe before rehearſed, That then they and every of them ſo offending contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry<note place="margin">The forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of an Apothecary that refuſeth to have his houſe ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. <hi>St. 1. M.</hi> 9.</note> to this Act, for every time that he or they do o offend, do forfeit C. s. the one half to your Majeſty, and the other half to him that will ſue for the ſame by action of debt, bill, plaint, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in any of the Kings Courts wherein no wager of law, eſſoine, or protection ſhall be allowed. And if the ſaid four perſons or any<note place="margin">The forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſuch as being elect, refuſe to be ſworn or to make ſearch.</note> of them ſo elected and choſen as before is ſaid, do refuſe to be ſworn, or after his ſaid oath to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them adminiſtred, do obſtinately refuſe
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:54229:12"/>
to make the ſaid ſearch, and view once in the year at ſuch time as they ſhall think moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient by their diſcretions, having no lawful im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment by ſickneſs or otherwiſe to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: that then for every ſuch wilful and obſtinate default, every of the ſaid four perſons making default, to forfeit forty ſhillings.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as the Science of Phyſick doth comprehend, include and contain the knowledge<note place="margin">Any of the Phyſicians of <hi>London</hi> may practiſe Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery.</note> of Chirurgery, as a ſpecial member and part of the ſame, therefore be it enacted, that any of the ſaid Company or fellowſhip of Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, being able, choſen, and admitted by the ſaid Preſident and fellowſhip of Phyſicians, may from time to time as well within the City of <hi>London,</hi> as elſewhere within this Realm, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and exerciſe the ſaid Science of Phyſick in all and every his members and parts, any Act, Statute or proviſion made to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CAP. XLII.</hi> The authority and liberties of Barbers and Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons in <hi>London,</hi> being made of one Company.</head>
               <p>THe King our Soveraign Lord by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Lords Spiritual and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and the Commons in this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, and by the authority of the ſame,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:54229:12"/>
by all their common aſſents, duly pondering among other things neceſſary for the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of this Realm, that it is very expedient and needful to provide for men expert in the Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Phyſick and Chirurgery for the health of mans body, when infirmities and ſickneſs ſhall happen, for the due exerciſe and maintenance whereof, good and neceſſary acts be already made and provided. Yet nevertheleſs, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as within the City of <hi>London,</hi> where men of great experience as well in ſpeculation, as in practiſe of the Science and faculty of Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, be abiding and inhabiting, and have more commonly the daily exerciſe and experience of the ſame Science of Chirurgery then is had or uſed within any parts of this Realm: And by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion thereof many expert perſons be brought up under them, as their ſervants, apprentices and others, who by the exerciſe and diligent infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their ſaid maſters, as well now, as hereafter ſhall exerciſe the ſaid Science within divers other parts of this Realm, to the great relief comfort, and ſuccour of much people, and to the ſure ſafeguard of their bodily health, their limbs and lives. And for as much as within the ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> there be now two ſeveral and diſtinct Companies of Chirurgeons, occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pying and exerciſing the ſaid Science and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Chirurgery, the one Company being<note place="margin">By whom and at what time the Barbers of <hi>London</hi> were incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</note> commonly called the Barbers of <hi>London,</hi> and the other Company called the Chirurgeons of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> which Company of Barbers be incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:54229:13"/>
to ſue, and be ſued by the name of Maſters or Governors of the Myſtery and Communalty of the Barbers of <hi>London,</hi> by vertue and authority of the Letters Patents under the great Seal of the late King of famous memory King <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth, dated at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the four and twentieth day of <hi>February</hi> in the firſt year of his reign, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as well by our moſt dread Soveraign Lord, as by the right noble and vertuous Prince King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, Father unto the Kings moſt excellent Highneſs now being, were and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, as by ſundry Letters Patents thereof made, amongſt other things in the ſame contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned more at large may appear. And the other Company called the Chirurgeons, be not incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate,<note place="margin">The benefit like to enſue by joyning the Barbers and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons in one Company.</note> nor have any manner of Corporation: which two ſeveral and diſtinct Companies of Chirurgeons were neceſſary to be united and made one body incorporate, to the intent that by their union and often aſſembly together, the good and due order, exerciſe, and knowledge in the ſaid Science or Faculty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of Chirurgery, ſhould be as well in ſpeculation, as in practiſe, both to themſelves and all other their ſaid ſervants and apprentices, now and hereafter to be brought up under them, and by their learning, and diligent, and ripe informations, more perfect, ſpeedy, and effectual remedy ſhould be then it hath been, or ſhould be, if the ſaid two Companies of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and Chirurgeons ſhould continue ſevered aſunder, and not joyned together, as they before this time have been, and uſed themſelves, not
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:54229:13"/>
medling together. Wherefore in conſideration of the Premiſes, be it enacted by the King our Soveriagn Lord, and by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and by the Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the authority of the ſame, That the ſaid two ſeveral and diſtinct Companies of Chirurgeons, that is to ſay, both the Barbers and the Chirurgeons, and every perſon of them being a freeman of either of the ſaid Companies after the cuſtome of the ſaid City<note place="margin">The Barbers and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> made one Company and incorporated.</note> of <hi>London,</hi> and their ſucceſſors from henceforth immediately be united, and made one entire and whole body corporate, and one Comminalty per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual, which at all times hereafter ſhall be called by the name of Maſters, or Governours of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery &amp; Comminalty of Barbers and Chirurgeons of <hi>London</hi> for evermore, and by none other name: And by the ſame name to implead, and be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaded before all manner of Juſtices, in all Courts, in all manner of Actions and Suits. And alſo to purchaſe, enjoy, and take to them and to their ſucceſſors all manner of lands, tenements, rents, and other poſſeſſions whatſoever they be, and alſo ſhall have a common Seal, to ſerve for the buſineſs of the ſaid Company and Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ever. And by the ſame name peaceably, quietly, and indifferently have, poſſeſs and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy to them and to their ſucceſſors for ever, all ſuch lands and tenements, and other heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoever, which the ſaid Company, or Comminalty of Barbers have and enjoy, to the uſe of the ſaid Myſtery and Comminalty of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:54229:14"/>
of <hi>London.</hi> And alſo ſhall peaceably, and quietly have, and enjoy all and ſingular benefits, grants, liberties, priviledges, franchiſes, and free cuſtomes, and alſo all manner of other things, at any time given or granted unto the ſaid Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Barbers or Chirurgeons, by whatſoever name or names they or any of them were called, and which they, or any of them now have, or any of their predeceſſors have had, by acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Letters Pattents of the Kings Highneſs, or other his moſt noble progenitors, or otherwiſe by any lawful means had at any time afore this preſent Act, in as large and ample manner and form, as they, or any of them have, had, might, or ſhould enjoy the ſame, this union, or conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſaid companies together notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. And as largely to have and enjoy the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, as if the ſame were, and had been ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and particularly expreſſed, and declared with the beſt and moſt cleareſt words, and terms in the law, to all intents and purpoſes. And that<note place="margin">The Barbers and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> ſhall be exempt from bearing of armes, or to be in watches or inqueſts. 5. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 6.</note> all perſons of the ſaid Company now incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate by this preſent Act, and their ſucceſſors, that ſhall be lawfully admitted, and approved to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy Chirurgery after the form of the Statute in that caſe ordained and provided, ſhall be exempt from bearing of armour, or to be put in any watches or inqueſts: And that they, and their ſucceſſors ſhall have the ſearch, overſight, puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and correction as well of Freemen, as of foreins, for ſuch offences as they, or any of them ſhall commit, or do againſt the good order of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:54229:14"/>
Barbery, or Chirurgery, as afore this time a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the ſaid myſtery and Company of Barbers of <hi>London,</hi> hath been uſed and accuſtomed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the good and politick rules and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances by them made, and approved by the Lords Chancellor, Treaſurer, and two chief Juſtices of either Bench or any three of them after the form of the Statute in that caſe ordained and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.<note place="margin">19. <hi>H.</hi> 7. 7.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And further be it enacted by the authority<note place="margin">The Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons may take yearly four con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomies.</note> aforeſaid, that the ſaid Maſters or Governors of the Myſtery and Comminalty of Barbers and Chirurgeons of <hi>London,</hi> and their ſucceſſors year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for ever after their ſaid diſcretions at their free liberty and pleaſure, ſhall and may have and take without contradiction four perſons condemned, adjudged, and put to death for felony, by the due order of the Kings Lawes of this Realm, for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomies, without any further ſuit or labour to be made to the Kings Highneſs, his Heirs or Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors for the ſame. And to make inciſion of the ſame dead bodies, or otherwiſe to order the ſame, after their ſaid diſcretions at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, for their further and better knowledge, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, inſight, learning, and experience in the ſaid Science or Faculty of Chirurgery. Saving unto all perſons, their heirs and ſucceſſors, all ſuch right, title, intereſt, and demand, which they, or any of them might lawfully claim to have, in, or to any of the lands and tenements with the appurtenances belonging unto the ſaid Companie of Barbers and Chirurgeons, or any of them, at any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:54229:15"/>
time afore the making of this Act, in as ample manner and form as they or any of them had or ought to have had heretofore: Any thing in this preſent Act compriſed, to the contrary hereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as ſuch perſons being of the Myſtery or Faculty of Chirurgery, oftentimes meddle, and take into their cure, and houſes, ſuch ſick and diſeaſed perſons, as been infected with the peſtilence, great Pocks, and ſuch other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious infirmities, do uſe, or exerciſe Barbery, as waſhing, or ſhaving, and other feats thereunto belonging, which is very perillous for infecting the Kings liege people, reſorting to their ſhops, and houſes there being waſhed or ſhaven. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is now enacted, or dained, and provided by the authority aforeſaid, that no manner per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon within the City of <hi>London,</hi> Suburbs of the ſame, and one mile compaſs of the ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> after the Feaſt of the Nativity of our Lord God next coming, uſing any Barbery or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving,<note place="margin">No Barber in <hi>London</hi> ſhall uſe Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery.</note> or that hereafter ſhall uſe any Barbery or ſhaving within the ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> Suburbs, or one mile circuit of the ſame City of <hi>London,</hi> he nor they, nor none other for them, to his, or their uſe ſhall occupy any Chirurgery, letting of bloud, or any other thing belonging to Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, (drawing of teeth only except.) And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore in like manner whoſoever that uſeth the myſtery or craft of Chirurgery, within the<note place="margin">No Chirurge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>London</hi> ſhall uſe the art of ſhaving.</note> circuit aforeſaid, as long as he ſhall fortune to uſe the ſaid myſtery or craft of Chirurgery, ſhall
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:54229:15"/>
in no wiſe occupy nor exerciſe the feat or craft of Barbery or ſhaving, neither by himſelf, nor by none other for him to his or their uſe: And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, that all manner of perſons uſing Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery for the time being, as well freemen, as fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reins, aliens, and ſtrangers within the ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> the Suburbs thereof, and one mile compaſs of the ſame City of <hi>London,</hi> before the Feaſt of Saint <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel next coming, ſhall have an open ſign on the ſtreet ſide where<note place="margin">Every Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon in <hi>London</hi> ſhall have a Sign at his door</note> they ſhall fortune to dwell, that all the Kings liege people there paſſing by may know at all times whether to reſort for their remedies in time of neceſſity.</p>
               <p>And further be it enacted by the authority aſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,<note place="margin">None ſhall be a Barber in <hi>London</hi> but a Freeman of that Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</note> That no manner of perſon after the ſaid Feaſt of Saint <hi>Michael</hi> the Archangel next com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, preſume to keep any ſhop of Barbery or ſhaving within the City of <hi>London,</hi> except he be a Freeman of the ſame Corporation and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
               <p>And furthermore, at ſuch times as have been heretofore accuſtomed, there ſhall be choſen by<note place="margin">Four War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens ſhall be choſen, and their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> the ſame Company, four Maſters or Governors of the ſame Corporation or Company, of the which four, two of them ſhall be expert in Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgery, and the other two in Barbery, which four Maſters, and every of them ſhall have full power and authority from time to time, during their ſaid office, to have the overſight, ſearch, puniſhment, and correction of all ſuch defaults and inconveniences, as ſhall be found among the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:54229:16"/>
ſaid Company uſing Barbery, or Chirurgery, as well of freemen, as foreins, aliens, and ſtrangers, within the City of <hi>London</hi> and the circuit afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, after their ſaid diſcretions. And if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon<note place="margin">The forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the offenders.</note> or perſons uſing any Barbery, or Chirurgery, at any time hereafter, offend in any of theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles aforeſaid: then for every moneth the ſaid perſons ſo offending ſhall loſe, forfeit and pay five pounds, the one moity thereof to the King our Soveraign Lord, and the other moity to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that will or ſhall ſue therefore by action of debt, bill, plaint, or information in any the Kings Courts, wherein no wager of law, eſſoine, or protection ſhall be admitted or allowed in the ſame.</p>
               <p>Provided that the ſaid Barbers and Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, and every of them ſhall bear and pay lot and ſcot, and ſuch other charges, as they and their predeceſſors have been accuſtomed to pay within the ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> this act nor any thing therein contained to the contrary hereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>Provided alway, and be it enacted by authority<note place="margin">Any perſon may keep a Barber or Chirurgeon as his ſervant.</note> aforeſaid, that it ſhall be lawful to any of the Kings Subjects, not being Barber or Chirurgeon, to retain, have, and keep in his houſe, as his ſervant, any perſon being a Barber or Chirurgeon, which ſhall and may uſe, and exerciſe thoſe arts and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of Barbery and Chirurgery, or either of them, in his maſters houſe, or elſewhere by his Maſters licenſe or commandement, any thing in this Act above written to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:54229:16"/>
            <head>Anno xxxiiii. &amp; xxxv. <hi>Henrici</hi> octavi.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>CAP. VIII.</hi> Any perſon being no common Chirurgeon, may miniſter outward medicines.</head>
            <p>WHere in the Parliament holden at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter,</hi> in the third year of the Kings moſt Gracious reign, amongſt other things for the avoiding of ſorceries, witchcrafts, and other inconveniencies, it was enacted, That no perſon within the City of <hi>London,</hi> nor within ſeven miles of the ſame, ſhould take upon them to exerciſe and occupy as Phyſician, or Chirurgeon, except he be firſt examined, approved, and admitted by the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> and other, under and upon certain pains and penalties in the ſame Act men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned. Sithence the making of which ſaid Act,<note place="margin">By what means the Chirurgeons of <hi>London</hi> have abuſed the Statute of 3. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 11. for their own gain.</note> the company and fellowſhip of Chirurgeons of <hi>London,</hi> minding only their own lucres, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the profit or eaſe of the diſeaſed or pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, have ſued, troubled and vexed divers honeſt perſons, as well men as women, whom God hath endued with the knowledge of the nature, kind and operation of certain herbs, roots and waters, and the uſing and miniſtring of them, to ſuch as been pained with cuſtomable diſeaſes: as womens breſts being ſore, a pin and the web in the eye, uncomes of hands, ſcaldings,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:54229:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
burnings, ſore mouthes, the ſtone, ſtrangury, ſauce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lim, and morfew, and ſuch other like diſeaſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and yet the ſaid perſons have not taken any thing for their pains or cunning, but have miniſtred the ſame to poor people only for neighbourhood and Gods ſake, and of pity and charity. And it is now well known, that the Chirurgeons ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted will do no cure to any perſon, but where they ſhall know to be rewarded with a greater ſum or reward then the cure extendeth unto, for in caſe they would miniſter their cunning unto ſore people unrewarded, there ſhould not ſo many rot and periſh to death for lack of help of Chirurgery as daily do: but the great part of Chirurgeons admitted, been much more to be blamed, then thoſe perſons that they trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>For although the moſt part of the perſons of the ſaid craft of Chirurgeons have ſmall cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, yet they will take great ſums of money, and do little therefore, and by reaſon thereof they do oftentimes impair and hurt their pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, rather than do them good.</p>
            <p>In conſideration whereof, and for the eaſe, comfort, ſuccour, help, relief and health of the Kings poor Subjects, inhabitants of this his Realm, now pained, or diſeaſed, or that hereafter ſhall be pained or diſeaſed.</p>
            <p>Be it ordained, eſtabliſhed and enacted by the authority of this preſent Parliament, that all time from henceforth it ſhall be lawful to every perſon being the Kings Subject, having
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:54229:17"/>
knowledge and experience of the nature of herbes, roots and waters, or of the operation<note place="margin">It ſhall be lawful for any perſon to cure outward ſores not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Statute of 3. H. 8. 11.</note> of the ſame by ſpeculation or practiſe within any part of the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> or within any other the Kings Dominions, to practiſe, uſe and miniſter in and to any outward ſore, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, wound, apoſtemations, outward ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or diſeaſe, any herb or herbs, oyntments, bathes, pultes, and emplaſters, according to their cunning, experience and knowledge in any of the diſeaſes, ſores, and maladies beforeſaid, and all other like to the ſame, or drinks for the ſtone, and ſtrangury, or agues, without ſuit, vexation, trouble, penalty or loſſe of their goods, the foreſaid Statute in the foreſaid third year of the Kings moſt Gracious reign, or any other Act, Ordinance or Statute to the contrary hereof, heretofore made, in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:54229:18"/>
            <head>Anno primo <hi>MARIAE,</hi> Seſsio ſecunda.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>CAP. IX.</hi> The Incorporation of Phyſicians in <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>WHereas in the Parliament holden at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> the fifteenth day of <hi>April,</hi> in the fourteenth year of the reign of our late Soveraign Lord King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, and from thence adjourned to <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the laſt day of <hi>July,</hi> in the fifteenth year of the reign of the ſame King, and there holden: It was enacted, that a certain Grant by Letters Pattents, of incorporation made and granted by our ſaid late King, to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of <hi>London,</hi> and all clauſes and Articles contained in the ſame Grant, ſhould be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, granted, ratified, and confirmed by the ſame Parliament.</p>
            <p>For the conſideration thereof, be it enacted by<note place="margin">A confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>St.</hi> of 14. <hi>H.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 5. touching the Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </note> authority of this preſent Parliament, that the ſaid Statute or act of Parliament, with every article and clauſe therein contained, ſhall from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ſtand and continue ſtill in full ſtrength, force, and effect. Any Act, Statute, Law, Cuſtome, or any other thing made, had, or uſed to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And for the better reformation of divers enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:54229:18"/>
happening to the Common-wealth, by the evil uſing and undue adminiſtration of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and for the enlarging of further Articles for the better execution of the things, contained in the ſaid Grant enacted.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore now enacted, That whenſoever<note place="margin">Whoſoever ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon by the Preſident of the Colledge of Phyſicians in <hi>London,</hi> ſhal be received and kept thereby.</note> the Preſident of the Colledge, or Communalty of the faculty of Phyſick of <hi>London,</hi> for the time being, or ſuch as the ſaid Preſident and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhall yearly, according to the tenor and meaning of the ſaid Act, authoriſed to ſearch, examine, correct, and puniſh all offenders, and tranſgreſſors, in the ſaid faculty, within the ſame City and precinct, in the ſaid Act expreſſed, ſhall ſend or <hi rend="sup">a</hi> commit any ſuch offendor or offendors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="sup">a</hi> 
                  <hi>Co. li. 8. fo.</hi> 114.</note> for his or their offences or diſobedience, contrary to any article or clauſe, contained in the ſaid Grant or Act, to any Ward, Goal, or Priſon, within the ſame City and Precinct (the Tower of <hi>London</hi> except.) That then from time to time, the Warden, Goaler or Keeper, Wardens, Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, or Keepers of the Wards, Goals and Priſons, within the City or Precinct aforeſaid (except be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore excepted) ſhall receive into his or their Priſons, all and every ſuch perſon and perſons ſo offending, as ſhall be ſo ſent or committed to him or them, as is aforeſaid, and there ſhall ſafely keep the perſon or perſons, ſo committed, in any of their priſons, at the proper coſts and charges of the ſaid perſon or perſons, ſo committed, without bail or mainpriſe, until ſuch time as ſuch offendor or offendors, or diſobedient, be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:54229:19"/>
of the ſaid impriſonment, by the ſaid Preſident, and ſuch perſons as by the ſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſhall be thereunto authoriſed, upon pain that all and every ſuch Warden, Goaler, or Keeper, doing the contrary, ſhall loſe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit<note place="margin">The offenders forfeiture, and who ſhall have it, and by what means.</note> the double of ſuch fine and amerciament, as ſuch offender and offenders, or diſobedients, ſhall be aſſeſſed to pay, by ſuch as the ſaid Preſident and Colledge ſhall authoriſe, as aforeſaid, ſo that the ſame fine and amerciament, be not at any one time above the ſum of xx. li. the moity thereof to be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to the uſe of our Soveraign Lady the Queen, her Heirs and Succeſſors, the other moity unto the ſaid Preſident and Colledge. All which forfeitures to be recovered by action of debt, bill, plaint, or information in any of the Queens, her Heirs, and Succeſſors Courts of Record, againſt any ſuch Warden, Goaler, or Keeper, ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding: in which ſuit no eſſoine, wager of Law, nor protection ſhall be allowed, ne admitted for the defendant.</p>
            <p>And further be it enacted by the authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid,<note place="margin">Searching in <hi>London</hi> for Apothecary wares. 32<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>H.</hi> 8. 40.</note> for the better execution of the ſearch and view of Poticary wares, Drugs and Compoſitions, according to the tenour of a Statute, made in the two and thirdieth year of the reign of the ſaid late King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, that it ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the Wardens of the Grocers, or one of them, to go with the ſaid Phyſicians in their view and ſearch, that if the ſaid Warden or War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, do refuſe or delay his or their coming thereunto, forthwith and immediately when the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:54229:19"/>
ſaid Preſident, or four of his Colledge Elect, as aforeſaid, do call upon him or them, that then the ſaid Phyſicians may and ſhall execute that ſearch and view, and the due puniſhment of the<note place="margin">The penalty for reſiſting ſearch of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary wares.</note> Apothecaries: for any their evil and faulty ſtuffe, according to the Statute laſt before mentioned, without the aſſiſtence of any of the ſaid Wardens: any clauſe in the aforenamed ſtatute to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary hereof notwithſtanding. And every ſuch perſon or perſons, as will or ſhall reſiſt ſuch ſearch, ſhall forfeit for every ſuch reſiſtence x. li. the ſame penalty to be recovered in form afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, without any of the delaies aforeſaid to be had in ſuit thereof.</p>
            <p>And further be it enacted, that all Juſtices,<note place="margin">Other Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates ſhall aſſiſt the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians in their ſearch.</note> Maiors, Sheriffs, Bailiffs, Conſtables, and other Miniſters, and Officers, within the City and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts above written, upon requeſt to them made, ſhall help, aid and aſſiſt the Preſident of the ſaid Colledge, and all perſons by them (from time to time) authoriſed for the due execution of the ſaid Acts or Statutes, upon pain for not giving of ſuch aid, help and aſſiſtence, to run in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Queens Majeſty, her Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="charter">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:54229:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Queen <hi>ELIZABETHS</hi> Charter for Anatomies.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>ELizabetha</hi> Dei gratia Anglie Francie &amp; Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernie regina fidei defenſor &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>
                  <hi>Omnibus</hi> ad quos preſentes litterae pervenerint ſalutem.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clariſsime memorie Pater noſter Henricus octavus nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Rex Anglie inter nonnullas alias in commodum &amp; utilitatem regni ſui Anglie preclare admodum ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas &amp; ſtabilitas ordinationes ſaluti ſubditorum ſuorum ſummopere invigilans per literas ſuas patentes Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium perpetuum quorundam gravium virorum medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum qui medicinam in urbe ſua Londino &amp; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbiis ejuſdem, intraque ſeptem miliaria ab ea urbe quaqua verſus publice exercerent, inſtituerit &amp; incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraverit eos in corpus corporatum &amp; politicum per no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Preſidentis Collegii ſeu communitatis facult at is medicine Londini &amp; conceſſerit eidem preſidenti Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legii ſive communitatis predicte &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis diverſas libertates &amp; privilegia. <hi>Quas</hi> lras patentes &amp; omnia in iis contenta idem Pater nr non ſolum per ſenatus conſultum ſeu Parliament<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m ſuum tentum Annis quarto decimo &amp; quinto decimo regni ſui con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmavit, ſed etiam per idem ſtatutum in multis ad auxit &amp; amplificavit. <hi>Quod Quidem</hi> pium inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum dci Patris nri quandoquidem in reipublice commoditatem ceſſit manifeſtam &amp; in majorem indies ceſſurum veriſimile ſit, ſinos quod rem medicam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitentibus maxime neceſſarium eſt, conceſſerimus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictis
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:54229:20"/>
preſidenti Collegii ſive communitatis predicte &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis inperpetuum quotannis quaedam hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana corpora ad anatomizandum ut informamur. <hi>Sciatis</hi> qd nos non modo preclaram inſtituco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>em dicti Patris noſtri merito recolentes, verumetiam regi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficii nri munus arbitrantes regiminis noſtri ſubdito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum incolumitati, ſaluti &amp; ſecuritati quantum in nobis eſt, providere de gra nra spiali ac ex nra ſcientia ac mero motu noſtris conceſsimus ac per preſentes pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis heredibus &amp; ſucceſſoribus noſtris concedimus prefato Preſidenti Collegii ſive communitatis medicine Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dini predict. &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis ſive eorum aſsigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis qd habeant &amp; accipiant annuatim Temporibus futuris inperpetuum una vice vel diverſis anni vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus ad diſcrecoem voluntat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m &amp; libertatem predict. preſidis pro tempore exiſtm. &amp; ſucceſſorum ſuorum unum duo tria vel quatuor corpora humana ad diſcin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend. &amp; anatomizand. quod jure publico hujus regni furti homicidii vel cujuſcunque felonie condemnatum &amp; mortuum fuerit, vel que jure publico hujus regni furti homicidii vel cujuſcunque felonie condemnat. &amp; mort. fuerint intra Comitatum Midd. vel infra Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatem London predictam, vel alibi ubicunque in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra ſedecim miliaria predict. Civitatis prox. in quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque Comitatu ſine impedimento noſtri heredum vel ſucceſſorum noſtrorum, aut vicecomitum Ballivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, ſervient. ad clavam, ſeu aliorum officiariorum aut ſubditorum noſtrorum quorumcunque, ſive eorum alicujus. <hi>Et Quod</hi> licebit eidem preſidenti Collegii &amp; communitati predict. &amp; ſucceſſoribus ſuis &amp; aliis, quibuſcun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> eorum aſsignatis medicine profeſſoribus ſeu expertis eadem corpora ſecare, dividere &amp; aliter pro voluntate &amp; judicio ſuo cum ea reverentia qua
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:54229:21"/>
humane carni debetur tractare ad incrementum cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis medicine experimentum ejuſdem &amp; ad ſalutem ligeorum noſtrorum ſine contradictione alicujus. Et hoc abſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ulla pecuniarum ſumma, vel ullis pecuni a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſummis pro eiſdem reddend. ſeu cuicun<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vend. <hi>Proviſo</hi> ſemper quod cum hujuſmodi anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia de tempore in tempus tranſacta &amp; perfecta fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit predicta corpora ſumptibus ipſorum preſidentis &amp; ſucceſſorum ſuorum debitis exequiis &amp; ſepulture com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur. <hi>Eo Quod</hi> expreſſa mentio de vero va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lore Annuo aut de aliquo alio valore vel certitudine premiſſorum ſive eorum alicujus aut de aliis donis ſive conceſsionibus per nos vel per aliquem Progenitorum noſtrorum prefatis preſidents Collegii ſive communitati facultatis medicine Londini ante haec tempora factis in preſentibus minime fact. exiſtit. Aut aliquo ſtatuto Actu ordinatione proclamacoe proviſione ſive reſtricoe inde in contrarium habit. fact. edit. ordinat. ſive pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis. Aut aliqua alia re cauſſa vel materia qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque in aliquo non obſtante. <hi>In cujus</hi> rei teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium has litteras noſtras fieri fecimus Patentes. <hi>Teſte</hi> meipa apud Weſtmonaſterium viceſimo quarto die Februarii Anno regni noſtri ſeptimo.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Per breve de privato ſigillo &amp;c.</hi>
               <signed>Naylour.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters_patent">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:54229:21"/>
            <head>Letters Pattents granted by King <hi>JAMES</hi> to the Colledge of Phyſicians in <hi>London.</hi> dat. 8. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctobr. 15<hi rend="sup">o</hi> regni ſui.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>JAmes by the grace of God, King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </signed>
               <salute>To all to whom theſe preſents ſhall come greeting:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Whereas our moſt noble and<note place="margin">Preamble.</note> renowned Predeceſſors, King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight late King of this our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> in his Princely wiſdome deeply conſidering and by the example of forein well governed States and Kingdomes, truly underſtanding how profitable, beneficial and acceptable it would be unto the whole body of this Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> to reſtrain and ſuppreſs the exceſſive number of ſuch as daily profeſſed themſelves learned, and profound practiſers in the Faculty of Phyſick, whereas in truth they were men illiterate and unexperienced, rather propounding unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves their private gain, with the detriment of this Kingdome, then to give relief in time of need, And likewiſe duly conſidering that by the rejecting of thoſe illiterate and unskilful practiſers, thoſe that were learned grave and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found practiſers in that Faculty, ſhould receive
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:54229:22"/>
more bountiful reward; and alſo the induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Students of that profeſſion would be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter encouraged in their ſtudies and endeavours. For theſe and many other weighty motives,<note place="margin">Recital of the Patent of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporation.</note> cauſes and conſiderations, our royal and Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Predeceſſor King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, by his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Pattents bearing date at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> the three and twentieth day of <hi>September</hi> in the Tenth year of his reign, of his eſpecial grace and Princely favour, did erect found and eſtabliſh a Colledge, Comminalty or Incorporation of Phyſitians in the City and Suburbs of <hi>London</hi> and for ſeven miles every way in diſtance from the ſame, to be, remain, and have exiſtence for ever: and by the ſame Letters Pattents, our aforeſaid noble Predeceſſor did further give and grant un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>John Chambre, Thomas Linacre, Ferdinando de Victoria, Nicholas Halſewell, John Francis,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Yaxley,</hi> then learned, diſcreet, and profound practiſers in the ſaid Faculty of Phyſick in the foreſaid City of <hi>London.</hi> That they and all of the ſaid Faculty of Phyſick of and in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> ſhould for ever, from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth be in name and deed one Body Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty and Colledge; And further by the ſaid Letters Pattents did give and grant unto the ſaid Colledge and Comminalty, full power, ability and authority for ever, annually to elect and make one of the ſaid Colledge or Comminalty to be Preſident of the ſaid Colledge, Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Comminalty; And that the ſaid Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſo elected and made, and the ſaid Colledge
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:54229:22"/>
and Comminalty, ſhould have perpetual ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and a common Seal for the behoof and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the ſaid Preſideut, Colledge and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalty, and their Succeſſors for ever. And alſo by the ſaid Letters Pattents did further give and grant unto the ſaid Preſident, Colledge and Com. minalty, and their Succeſſors, divers and ſundry other liberties, priviledges, immunities, power, ability and authority, not only to and for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, advantage and commodity of the foreſaid Preſident, Colledge and Comminalty and their Succeſſors, but alſo for the more certain and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier diſcovery, ſpeedy reſtraint, and certain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of the before mentioned unskilful and illiterate practiſers in the ſaid faculty of Phyſick as aforeſaid. As by the foreſaid Letters Patents remaining of record amongſt other things therein contained, more plainly and fully it doth and may appear. Which ſaid Letters Patents, and<note place="margin">Confirmed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 14. <hi>H.</hi> 8.</note> all and every Grant, Article, and other thing contained and ſpecified in the ſame, were by Act of Parliament made in the xiiii. year of the reign of our ſaid noble predeceſſor King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, approved, granted, ratified and confirmed, and clearly authoriſed and admitted by the ſame good lawful and available to the ſaid body cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate and their ſucceſſors for ever, and that the beſt conſtruction that might be invented ſhould be made thereof, and of every part and parcel thereof for the beſt benefit, behoof, power and authority of the foreſaid Preſident, Colledge and Corporation of Phyſicians as aforeſaid.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:54229:23"/>
And further, by other ſeveral Acts of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, divers and ſundry other Priviledges, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">By other Acts.</note> ability, power and authority are and were eſtabliſhed, ordained, given and granted unto the ſaid Preſident, Colledge and Corporation of Phyſicians and their ſucceſſors, as by the ſaid ſeveral Acts of Parliament thereof made more fully and at large it doth and may appear. Sithence the making of which ſaid Letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and ſeveral Acts of Parliament, we do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs daily find that divers enormities and abuſes, not as yet ſufficiently provided for and<note place="margin">New Abuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> reformed, do abound and increaſe to the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent damage of us and our loving Subjects of this our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> by and through the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfulneſs, fraud and deceit of Phyſicians, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, Druggiſts, and ſuch like, and are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly much more to abound, unleſs timely and feſtine remedy be by us provided and applied for the curing of ſo publique a diſeaſe. <hi>Know ye</hi> therefore, that we graciouſly affecting ſo pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous<note place="margin">
                  <hi>K. James</hi>'s Grants.</note> and charitable a work, and intending hereby a more full and perfect reformation of the ſaid abuſes, grievances and enormities, which theſe later times have abundantly brought forth in this our Realm, out of our Princely diſpoſition and care for the repreſſing thereof; and of our ſpecial grace, certain knowledge and meer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the humble Petition aſwell of our truſty and well beloved <hi>Henry Atkins</hi> Doctor in phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, now Preſident of the ſaid Colledge, and one of our Phyſicians, <hi>Theodorus de Maierne</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:54229:23"/>
in Phyſick, one other of our Phyſicians, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Mounford</hi> and <hi>Edward Liſter</hi> Doctors in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, Fellowes and Elects of the ſaid Colledge, as of other the Doctors of the ſaid Colledge, have given, granted, ratified, approved, allowed and confirmed, and by theſe preſents, do for us our Heirs and Succeſſors, give, grant, ratifie, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove, allow and confirm unto the aforeſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their<note place="margin">A Confirm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Patents and Acts of Parliament.</note> Succeſſors, the ſaid Letters patents of our ſaid noble predeceſſor King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, herein before mentioned, and every article, clauſe, gift and grant therein contained, and not herein altered, for the honour, peace and quiet of the ſaid Colledge; and that the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors ſhall and may for ever hereafter have, receive, take, retain, keep, uſe, exerciſe and enjoy all and ſingular ſuch rights, titles, liberties, priviledges, immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, freedoms, executions, ability, power, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and other things, as by the ſaid Letters patents, or by any Acts of Parliament, are or were given, granted or confirmed, or were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by mentioned or intended to be given, granted or confirmed, notwithſtanding the not uſing, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſing or abuſing of the ſame; and that <hi>the ſame Letters Patents, and every article and clauſe therein contained, ſhall be adjudged, taken, and conſtrued moſt benignly and favourably, to and for the beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, avail and advantage of the foreſaid Preſident, and Colledge, or Comminalty, or their Succeſſors, any Ordinance, Cuſtome, or uſage to the contrary in any
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:54229:24"/>
wife notwithſtanding. And</hi> whereas our ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Predeceſſor, by the aforeſaid Letters patents, (amongſt other things) therein contained, hath given and granted unto the foreſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; and thereby expreſly appointed and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, that no perſon whatſoever ſhould exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe<note place="margin">Againſt not ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ed.</note> the ſaid Faculty of Phyſick within the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> or within ſeven miles in cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit thereof; unleſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſaid perſon ſhould firſt be admitted to do the ſame, by the foreſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, and Colledge or Comminalty, or their Succeſſors, by Letters teſtimonial of the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty ſealed with their common Seal, upon pain of forſeiting ſive pounds for every moneth wherein the ſaid perſons ſhould exerciſe the ſaid faculty being not admitted thereunto, the one half thereof to be for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ited and given to our ſaid Predeceſſor, his heirs and ſucceſſors, and the other half there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to be forfeited and given to the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, as by the ſaid Letters patents may appear. <hi>Now know ye,</hi> That we in our Princely wiſdome,<note place="margin">Power to ſue for the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lues.</note> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y conſidering how need<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ul it is and will be, that all and ſingular perſon and perſons practiſing or exerciſing the ſaid faculty of phyſick contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the intent and true meaning of the foreſaid Letters patents, ſhall be duly and condignly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed: and for the better encouragement of the foreſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and their Succeſſors to ſue for the ſaid pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:54229:24"/>
of five pounds ſpecified and mentioned by the ſaid Letters patents, of our eſpecial grace, certain knowledge, and meer motion. <hi>Have</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and granted, and by theſe preſents, for us, our heirs, and ſucceſſors, do give and grant unto the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors full power and lawful autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the name of us our heirs and ſucceſſors, or otherwiſe in their own name, by the name of the Preſident and Colledge of the Faculty of Phyſick within the city of <hi>London</hi> in any our Courts of record, or in any other place or places within this our Realm, according to our Lawes to ſue for, recover and have execution of and for all and ſingular ſuch penalties, forfeitures, ſum and ſums of money as now are or hereafter from time to time, ſhall accrew or grow due unto us our heirs or ſucceſſors, or to them by force or vertue of the foreſaid Letters patents or any the ſaid Statutes, or any clauſe or thing in them, or in theſe preſents contained (other then the Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance hereafter expreſſed, or by reaſon or, means of any offence or miſdemeanor whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver committed, perpetrated, or done or hereafter to be committed, perpetrated or done contrary to the intent and meaning thereof; and after the ſame ſhall be duly recovered, levied or recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved as aforeſaid. We will and by theſe preſents<note place="margin">Penalties to the Colledg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> uſe only.</note> for us our heirs and ſucceſſors, do give and grant the ſame penalties, forfeitures, and ſums<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of money, and every part and parcel thereof to the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge, and Comminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and their Succeſſors to be retained, had, taken,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:54229:25"/>
converted and enjoyed to their ſole and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per uſe benefit and behoof, without rendring, making or yielding unto us, our heirs or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, any part or parcel thereof: or any rent, accompt or recompence for the ſame (other then the yearly rent hereafter by theſe preſents reſerved) the ſaid Letters patents, or any the ſaid Statutes before mentioned, or any clauſe, article or reſervation in them or any of them contained to the contrary hereof in any wiſe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. <hi>And</hi> we do further by theſe preſents of our eſpecial grace, certain knowledge and meer motion for us, our heirs and ſucceſſors, give and grant unto the foreſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, that the four perſons to be annually choſen by the ſaid<note place="margin">To the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors power to ſurvey <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes.</note> Preſident, and Colledge or Comminalty for the time being, and their Succeſſors according to the intent and meaning of the foreſaid Letters patents of our ſaid Predeceſſor King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, now commonly called the four Cenſors of the ſaid Colledge, or any three of them for the time being, ſhall have full power and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful authority at all time and times hereafter, when and as often as to the ſaid four Cenſors, or any three of them ſhall ſeem requiſite and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient <hi>to examine, ſurvey, gover<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, correct and puniſh all and ſingular Phyſicians and Practiſers in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of Phyſick, Apothecaries, Druggiſts, Diſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ers and Sellers of Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s or Oyls, Preparers of Chymical Medicines,</hi> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old or imployed for gain, and all and every other perſon and perſons practiſing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:54229:25"/>
in the ſame faculty, or uſing the art or myſtery of an Apothecary, or the trade or craft of a Druggiſt, Diſtiller, Preparer or ſeller of any Oyls, Waters, or Medicines as aforeſaid, or that ſhall ſell or put to ſale any Stuff, Drugs, Oyls, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, or Medicines, or other thing whatſoever, fit, apt, and uſed or pretended to be fit, apt, and uſed for Medicines either ſimple or compounded, at or in any place or places within the foreſaid Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> or within ſeven miles of the ſame, by fines, amerciaments, and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments, and by other lawful waies and means according as the nature and quality of his or their offence or offences in the premiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſhall deſerve or require. <hi>And</hi> we do further of our like eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial<note place="margin">Power of the Cenſors to ſummon exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine and fine.</note> grace, certain knowledge, and meer motion, for us, our heirs and ſucceſſors, give and grant unto the foreſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors; and do by theſe preſents declare our will and pleaſure to be, That the ſaid four Conſors of the foreſaid<note place="margin">Phyſitians not licenſed.</note> Colledge for the time being, or any three of them for ever hereafter, when and as often, as to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid Cenſors or any three of them ſhall ſeem mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and convenient, ſhall have full power and authority to ſend for, ſummon, convent, and cauſe to appear and come before<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> them the ſaid four C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſors for the time being or any three of them, all and every Phyſician and Phyſicians, practiſer and practiſers in the ſaid Faculty of Phyſick with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the foreſaid City and Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> or within ſeven miles thereof, at ſuch times and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:54229:26"/>
places, as by the ſaid Cenſors or any three of them ſhall be reaſonably limited, prefixed and appointed, and <hi>to examine them concerning their skill or practiſe of the ſaid faculty of Phyſick, and their manner of practiſe therein:</hi> And if any Phyſician<note place="margin">Penalty for not appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</note> or practiſer in the ſaid Faculty of Phyſick upon reaſonable ſummons, and garniſhment to be made and given in that behalf, ſhall make default, and not appear before the ſaid Cenſors or any three of them at ſuch time and place as by the ſaid Cenſors or any three of them ſhall be reaſonably limited, prefixed and appointed, <hi>or ſhall refuſe to anſwer, or to be examined as aforeſaid;</hi> that then<note place="margin">Or refuſing to anſwer.</note> and ſo often the ſaid four Cenſors for the time being, or any three of them, ſhall and may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully aſſeſs and impoſe a reaſonable penalty, fine, or amerciament upon every or any ſuch delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent or offender for every ſeveral default of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance made upon ſeveral ſummons, or for every ſeveral refuſal to anſwer or to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as aforeſaid, at ſeveral times upon ſeveral appearances made, ſo as the ſame penalty, fine or amerciament ſo to be impoſed for any one default of appearance or refuſal to anſwer, or to be examined as aforeſaid, do not at any one time exceed <hi>the ſum of forty ſhillings of currant Engliſh money:</hi> and if any perſon or perſons ſo ſummon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or warned as aforeſaid do make his or their perſonal appearance before the foreſaid Cenſors, at ſuch time and place, as is or ſhall be limited and appointed as aforeſaid; and it ſhall then and there appear unto the ſaid Cenſors, that ſuch
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:54229:26"/>
perſon or perſons hath or have miniſtred or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Medicines or Phyſick unto any perſon or<note place="margin">Penalty of Practiſers without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence by the Genſors.</note> perſons, or hath or have practiſed in the ſaid fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Phyſick at any one or more time or times within the foreſaid City or Suburbs of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> or within ſeven miles thereof, without ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion and licenſe firſt had and obtained of and from the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalty, or their Succeſſors by Letters Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial under their Common Seal, according to the meaning of the Letters patents before mentioned: then it ſhall and may be lawful to and for the ſaid four Cenſors or any three of them to aſſeſs and impoſe a reaſonable penalty, fine, or amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciament upon every ſuch perſon and perſons ſo practiſing, <hi>for every ſuch his and their offence and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault</hi> in that behalf; ſo as the ſame exceed <hi>not the ſum of three pounds of lawful Engliſh money,</hi> and to<note place="margin">Three pounds<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> impriſon him by the ſpace of <hi>ſeven daies or under,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 7. daies.</note> for ſuch his offence, and not to detain him in priſon any longer, unleſs he ſhall not have made ſatisfaction and payment of the ſame Fine ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon him for the ſame offence, in which caſe it ſhall be lawful to detain him in priſon untill the ſame fine be ſatisfied. And if it ſhall then and there appear unto the ſaid Cenſors, or any three of them as aforeſaid, that any ſuch perſon or perſons ſo making his or their appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, hath at any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>time adminiſtred or preſcribed any <hi>noyſome, unwholſome, or unfit medicine or phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick</hi>
               <note place="margin">For bad pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe.</note> 
               <hi>unto any perſon or perſons within the limits a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid,</hi> then the ſaid Cenſors, ſhall and may from
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:54229:27"/>
time to time puniſh the ſaid delinquent or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender by reaſonable amerciament, fine or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment according unto their diſcretions to be by them impoſed as aforeſaid, ſo as the ſame fine <hi>do not exceed the ſum of Ten pounds,</hi> and ſo as<note place="margin">Ten pounds.</note> the impriſonment for ſuch offence exceed not the <hi>ſpace of fourteen daies,</hi> unleſs it ſhall be for non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment of ſuch fine, for which it ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to detain ſuch offender in priſon untill the ſame fine be ſatisfied. And to the end that the ſaid offenders in the premiſes may be the better<note place="margin">Diſcovery of offenders.</note> known and diſcovered, and may be for their ſaid miſdemeanors and offences duly and condignly puniſhed according to the merits of their ſaid offences, We do therefore of our more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant grace, certain knowledge and meer motion, for us our heirs and ſucceſſors, give and grant unto the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalty and their Succeſſors full power and law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful authority, that it ſhall and may be lawful to and for the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalty and their Succeſſors by any precept or proceſs to be made under their Common Seal, to ſummon and warn any perſon or perſons what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, whom they ſhall know or think meet, being any Apothecary, Chirurgeon, Druggiſt, or imployed in or about miniſtring of any phyſick or medicines, or attendant or ſervant upon any that ſhall have received phyſick or medicines to declare, teſtifie or prove againſt any ſuch delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent or offender in the premiſes, his or their miſdemeanors or offences upon reaſonable ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:54229:27"/>
and warning to appear and come before the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and their Succeſſors, or the ſaid Cenſors or any three of them, to be examined touching his or their knowledge of the ſaid offenders and their miſdemeanors and offences in the premiſes; and upon his or their appearance made as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid to adminiſter and give to him or them ſo to be produced to teſtifie as aforeſaid <hi>an Oath or Oathes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">To give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Oath.</note> and him and them to ſwear upon the holy Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts, to teſtifie and declare the truth of his and their knowledge concerning the ſaid offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in the premiſes and their ſaid miſdemeanors and offences, or otherwiſe to examine him or them without oath as they ſhall think fit. And that if any ſuch perſon or perſons as ſhall be thought fit as aforeſaid to declare and teſtifie concerning the ſaid offences upon reaſonable ſummons and warning given as aforeſaid ſhall wilfully make default, and ſhall not accordingly appear before the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and their Succeſſors, or the ſaid Cenſors or any three of them, or if he or they ſhall appear, and yet nevertheleſs ſhall refuſe to take ſuch oath or oathes as ſhall be then offered or tendred unto him or them as aforeſaid, or otherwiſe ſhall refuſe to be examined without oath, or ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to make anſwer to ſuch queſtions as ſhall be then asked or demanded of him or them by the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty and their Succeſſors, or the ſaid Cenſors or any three of them concerning his or their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:54229:28"/>
knowledge touching the ſaid offences and miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors or any of them, or any other matter or thing concerning the ſame, or the diſcovery thereof; then every ſuch perſon and perſons ſhall for every ſuch default or refuſal as aforeſaid, forfeit and pay to the ſaid Preſident, and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors <hi>the ſum of Twenty ſhillings of lawful Engliſh money. And</hi> we do further of our eſpecial grace, certain knowledge and mere motion, for us our heirs and ſucceſſors, give and grant unto the ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, and Colledge or Comminalty, and their Succeſſors, That the ſaid four Cenſors for the<note place="margin">Cenſors ſearch.</note> time being or any three of them ſhall and may have full and abſolute power and lawfull autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity at all time and times, when and as often as to them as aforeſaid ſhall ſeem meet and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, at fit and reaſonable times to enter into the houſe, ſhop, cellar, vault, workhouſe or ware<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, or any other rooms of the houſe of any Apothecary, Druggiſt, Diſtiller, and Seller of Waters, Oyls, or other compoſitions for the ends aforeſaid, or of any other perſon or perſons that now doth or hereafter ſhall put or ſet to ſale any Medicine, Drugs, Waters, Oyls, or Stuff, fit, apt or uſed, or pretended to be fit, apt or uſed for Medicines within the foreſaid City or Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> or within ſeven miles thereof; and then and there to ſearch, view, try, examine, and ſee the ſaid Medicines, Wares, Drugs, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Oyls, Medicines and Stuffs, of ſuch Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries, Druggiſts, Diſtillers, Preparers, or Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:54229:28"/>
of Waters, Oyls, or Medicines, or other perſon or perſons as aforeſaid, and to examine them upon oath or without oath, as they ſhall think beſt concerning the receipts and compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions thereof; and all ſuch Medicines, Wares, Drugs, Waters, Oyls, and Stuffs, as the ſaid four Cenſors or any three of them as aforeſaid ſhall finde or conceive to be defective, corrupted or not meet not convenient, to be miniſtred or uſed in medicine for the health of mans body, the ſaid four Cenſors or three of them, ſhall or may take, burn, or otherwiſe deſtroy the ſame or cauſe to be taken, burned; or otherwiſe deſtroyed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their diſcretions.</p>
            <p>And we do further for us our Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors,<note place="margin">Power to Convent A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> give and grant unto the ſaid Preſident or Colledge, and Comminalty, and their Succeſſors, that the ſaid four Cenſors for the time being or three of them, ſhall and may have full and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power and authority at all times, when and as often, as to them ſhall be thought meet and reaſonable, to ſend for, ſummon, convent, and cauſe to appear before them the ſaid four Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors for the time being or any three of them, at ſuch times and places within the foreſaid City and Suburbs of <hi>London</hi> or within ſeven miles thereof, <hi>all or any ſuch Apothecaries, Druggiſts, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillers, Preparers, and Sellers</hi> of ſuch Waters, Oyls, or Medicines as aforeſaid, or any other perſon or perſons whatſoever, uſing the Art or Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of an Apothecary or Druggiſt, or the Trade or Craft of a Diſtiller, Preparer, or Seller
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:54229:29"/>
of Waters, Oyls, or Medicines, or that ſhall put or ſet to ſale any Stuff, Drugs, Waters, Oyls, Medicines, or other things whatſoever, apt, fit, or uſed for Medicine either ſimple or compound within the foreſaid City and Suburbs of <hi>London,</hi> or within ſeven miles from the ſame: And if any ſuch perſon or perſons ſo ſummoned or warned as aforeſaid, upon reaſonable ſummons and garniſhment to him or them made in that behalf, ſhall not accordingly make his or their perſonal appearance before the ſaid Cenſors for the time being, or any three of them at ſuch time and place, as by the ſaid Cenſors or any three of them is or ſhall be reaſonably limited and appointed, Then we do by theſe preſents de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare that it ſhall and may be lawful to and for the foreſaid four Cenſors for the time being, or any three of them, to impoſe and inflict ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable penalty, fine and amerciament upon every ſuch perſon or perſons, ſo making default of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance as the ſaid four Cenſors or any three of them ſhall think meet in that behalf. So as ſuch fine or amerciament for any one ſuch default, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed not the ſum of <hi>Twenty ſhillings</hi> of lawful Engliſh money.</p>
            <p>And if any perſon or perſons ſummoned as<note place="margin">Bad Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines.</note> aforeſaid, ſhall make his or their perſonal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, before the aforeſaid four Cenſors for the time being or any three of them, at ſuch time or place as is or ſhall be limited and appointed, and then and there it ſhall appear unto the ſaid fonr Cenſors or any three of them, that the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:54229:29"/>
ſaid perſon or perſons ſo appearing then or of late did put or ſet to ſale, keep or retain in his or their ſhop or ſhops, houſe or houſes, any wares, drugs, waters, oyls, medicines or ſtuffs, defective, corrupted, and not meet or convenient to be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred in medicine for the health of mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or that any ſuch perſon or perſons, ſo ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned and appearing as aforeſaid, then or of late did make, or compound, or deliver out any medicine either ſimple or compounded, differing from, and not agreeable in name, nature, and quantity, unto the preſcript or direction deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto the ſaid perſon or perſons before the making, compounding or delivery of the ſaid medicine, then the ſaid four Cenſors for the time being, or any three of them ſhall have full power and authority to impoſe a reaſonable penalty, fine and amerciament upon all and every perſon and perſons, ſo offending, ſo as the ſame penalty, fine or amerciament for any one default or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence exceed not at any one time the ſum of <hi>Three pounds</hi> of lawful Engliſh money. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to impriſon ſuch offender untill he have made ſatisfaction and payment of the ſame fine ſo impoſed upon him for the ſame offence.</p>
            <p>And we do further of our eſpecial grace,<note place="margin">Grant of fines to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</note> certain knowledge, and meer motion, for us, our heirs, and ſucceſſors, give and grant unto the foreſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalty and their Succeſſors, all and ſingular the fines and amerciaments, penalties and forfeitures and every of them hereafter to be forfeited,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:54229:30"/>
aſſeſſed or impoſed upon any Phyſician or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſer in phyſick as aforeſaid, or to be forfeited impoſed or aſſeſſed upon any Apothecary, Drug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt, or other perſon or perſons, for or by reaſon of any miſdemeanor, offence, contempt, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault whatſoever, before in theſe preſents declared, mentioned, or ſpecified, and that the ſaid Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and Colledge or Comminalty and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, ſhall and may by the name of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Colledge of the faculty of Phyſick within the City of <hi>London</hi> at all times hereafter, and from time to time in any Ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Courts of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord according to Our Lawes ſue for, recover, levie, and take execution of and for the ſaid fines, amerciaments, penalties, and forfeitures, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or any part thereof; and the ſame being reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and levied, to have, take, retain and enjoy to the only uſe, behoof and benefit of the ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident, and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, without the let, diſturbance, or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Us, Our heirs or ſucceſſors; or any of the officers or miniſters of us, our heirs or ſucceſſors; and without giving or rendring any accompt or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence thereof, to us, our heirs or ſucceſſors. And that if any offender upon whom any ſuch fine or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciament<note place="margin">Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch as pay not their Fines.</note> ſhal be <hi>impoſed, ſhall be preſent before the four Cenſors, or any three of them, at the time of ſuch fine or amerciament impoſed, and ſhall not then pay the ſame, That then it ſhall and may be lawful to and for the ſaid four Cenſors or any three of them by whom ſuch fine or amerciament ſhall be impoſed to commit ſuch offender to priſon, and detain him in priſon untill he ſhall have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied the ſaid fine or amerciament and no longer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:54229:30"/>And further we will, and by theſe preſents for us our heirs and ſucceſſors of our eſpecial grace<note place="margin">To have a Hall.</note> and favour do grant unto the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, that it ſhall and may be lawful to and for them, or the greater part of them, to have, appoint, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and enjoy <hi>a certain Hall or Councel houſe</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our City of <hi>London</hi> or the Liberties of the ſame; And that the ſaid Preſident for the time being and his Succeſſors ſhall and may when and as often as to him ſhall ſeem meet and neceſſary, call, aſſemble, and keep within the ſame Hall or Houſe <hi>a certain Court or Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, to the number of Six perſons or more.</hi> whereof the ſaid Preſident for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be alwaies one; And that in the ſame Court or Convocation, the ſame Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors to the number of <hi>Six perſons or more, (whereof the Preſident for the time being to be one) ſhall and may treat, confer, conſult, and conſider of Arcicles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Meetings by whom and for what.</note> 
               <hi>Statutes, Acts, and Ordinances touching and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, and the good rule, ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the ſame, and the reformation and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs of the abuſes, miſchieſs and enormities herein be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, and hereby intended and meant to be provided for, and ſuppreſſed in the time to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further we will, and by theſe preſents for us our heirs and ſucceſſors, do grant to the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:54229:31"/>
Succeſſors, That the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Six perſons</hi> or more, whereof the ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident for the time being to be alwaies one upon publique ſummons thereof firſt made, being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together in their ſaid Hall or houſe, ſhall and may have full power and lawful au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from time to time, to ordain, conſtitute, make and ſet down in writing, ſuch wholſome and reaſonable Acts, Ordinances, Orders, Decrees,<note place="margin">To make By-lawes.</note> Articles and Conſtitutions, as to the ſaid Six per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or more of them ſo aſſembled, or the greater part of them ſo aſſembled, (whereof the ſaid Preſident to be one) ſhall ſeem good, profitable and neceſſary, according to their good directions, for the good rule, order, and government of the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, and of all other practiſers of Phyſick, and other the perſons before named, and all others offending in the ſaid faculty, or any other way touching or concerning the ſame, for the reformation and redreſs of the abuſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, miſdemeanors and enormities, and other the premiſes herein before mentioned or expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. And that the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſix perſons or more, (whereof the ſaid Preſident to be one) ſhall and may puniſh all and every delinquent or offender againſt the ſame Acts, Ordinances, Orders, Decrees, and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, or any of them, by impriſonment of his and their bodies, or by fine and amerciament to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:54229:31"/>
be by them as aforeſaid, adjudged, impoſed and inflicted from time to time as need ſhall require. And that the ſaid Preſident and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, ſhall and may lawfully levy, receive, have, and take the ſaid fines and amerciaments to their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per uſe, benefit, and behoof, without the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment<note place="margin">Fines to be paid to the Colledge.</note> or impediment of us, our heirs, or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, or of any the officers or miniſters of us, our heirs or ſucceſſors, and without any accompt to us, our heirs or ſucceſſors to be rendred or made for the ſame, other then the rent hereafter reſerved. All which ſaid Acts, Statutes, Ordinances, Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and Conſtitutions ſo as aforeſaid to be made, we will ſhall be obſerved and kept under the pains and penalties in the ſame to be limited and contained, ſo as the ſame Acts, Statutes and ordinances, impriſonments, fines, and amercia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be not contrary or repugnant to the Lawes and Statutes of this our Realm of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further we will, and by theſe preſents, for us, our heirs and ſucceſſors, do grant to the ſaid Preſident, and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors. That they, and their ſucceſſors, or the greater part of them aſſembled together in their ſaid Hall, ſhall and may nominate, elect and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point one honeſt and diſcreet perſon, which<note place="margin">A Regiſter his Office.</note> ſhal be and be called the Regiſter to the ſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, who ſhall from time to time be atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalty and their Succeſſors, at their Aſſemblies, Courts, Congregations, or meetings, and ſhall
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:54229:32"/>
ſet down in writing, regiſter, and enter into a Book, all ſuch rules, orders, ſtatutes, decrees, acts, ordinances, and other things as ſhall from time to time be had, made, done, provided and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, or the greater part of them, aſſembled together in their ſaid Hall; which ſaid Regiſter ſo to be named, ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and made as aforeſaid, ſhall be and continue in the ſaid office and place, for and during the will and pleaſure only of the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors or the greater part of them whereof the Preſident to be one. The ſaid Regiſter firſt taking his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Oath upon the holy Evangeliſts, before the<note place="margin">His Oath.</note> ſaid Preſident and four Cenſors for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or any three of them, whereof the Preſident to be one, for the doing and performing of his true and faithful ſervice to them in the ſaid office and place from time to time.</p>
            <p>And we do likewiſe will, and for us, our heirs and ſucceſſors do by theſe preſents grant unto the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, that they and their Succeſſors or the greater part of them, aſſembled in their ſaid Hall, ſhall and may from time to time, when and as often as to them ſhall ſeem meet, ordain,<note place="margin">Power to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Officers.</note> make, conſtitute and appoint ſuch and ſo many other fit and meet officer or officers, miniſter or miniſters, as to the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and theis Succeſſors, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of them ſhall be thought fit and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:54229:32"/>
for their ſervice and benefit, unto all and every which ſaid officers or miniſters, it ſhall be lawful to the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, or to the Cenſors or any three of them aſſembled together<note place="margin">To give Oathes.</note> in their ſaid Hall, to adminiſter and give oathes upon the ſaid holy Evangeliſts, for the due per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance and execution of his and their office and place. And the ſame Regiſter, and all and every other officer and miniſter by them to be elected, made, conſtituted or appointed as aforeſaid, from time to time upon reaſonable and juſt cauſe, to remove, expell and put out, of his and<note place="margin">To expell.</note> their ſaid offices and places, and to elect and put others into his and their rooms and places, when and as often as to the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, or the greater part of them, ſhall ſeem meet and convenient.</p>
            <p>And furher we do for us, our heirs and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, give and grant unto the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their ſucceſſors, That it ſhall and may be lawful to and for the ſaid Preſident and four Cenſors for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or any three of them (whereof the Preſident to be one) to cauſe ſuch perſons, which ſhall be convented, for any the offences aforeſaid, and<note place="margin">To take bonds of 100 <hi>l.</hi> to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe no more to his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties uſe.</note> ſhall be found offenders therin, to become bound to us, our heirs or ſucceſſors, and to our uſe in one or more ſeveral recognizances in ſuch ſum as they ſhall think fit, not exceeding the ſum of One hundred pounds, with conditions for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining them to offend any more in that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:54229:33"/>
behalf, as to the Preſident and four Cenſors or any three of them ſhall ſeem meet. And if ſuch perſon ſhall refuſe to become ſo bound by ſuch recognizance with ſuch condition, That then it ſhall and may be lawful to and for the ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and four Cenſors, or any three of them, (wereof the Preſident to be one) to commit ſuch<note place="margin">Or to impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſers.</note> perſon to priſon, and him to detain in priſon until he ſhall become bound in ſuch recognizance, with ſuch conditions as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And we do further of our eſpecial favour, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain knowledge, and mere motion, for us, our heirs, and ſucceſſors, give and grant unto the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, ſpecial Licence, free and lawfull liberty, power, and authority, to acquire,<note place="margin">To purchaſe Lands.</note> purchaſe, receive and take unto the ſaid Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Colledge or Comminalty and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, Mannors, Lands, Tenements, Tithes, Rents, Reverſions, and Hereditaments, of or from any perſon or perſons whatſoever, not exceeding in the whole the clear yearly value of One hundred Marks of lawful Engliſh money above all charges and repriſes. So as the ſame Mannors, Lands, Tenements, Tithes, Rents, Reverſions and Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments, by vertue hereof to be acquired and purchaſed, be not holden of us, our heirs or ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, immediately in chief, or by Knights ſervice, or of any other perſon or perſons by Knights ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, the Statute of alienation in Mortmayne or any other ſtatute, law, ordinance, or proviſion to the contrary thereof in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:54229:33"/>And we do further give and grant for us, our heirs and ſucceſſors unto the foreſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, that all and every Phyſician and Phyſicians, that now is or are, or that hereafter ſhall be ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, admitted, and made a Member of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Colledge or Comminalty, ſhall from time to time be wholly and abſolutely freed, exempted and diſcharged, of and from providing and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of any Armour, or other munition, within our<note place="margin">Coll. freed from provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arms.</note> ſaid City of <hi>London,</hi> and the Liberties thereof, or within ſeven miles compaſs as aforeſaid. Any Statute, Act, Ordinance, Conſtitution or Uſage, to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And we do further for us, our heirs and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors,<note place="margin">A general Grant.</note> give and grant to the foreſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and by theſe preſents declare and manifeſt our pleaſure for ever to be, That the ſaid Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Colledge, or Comminalty and their Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, ſhall and may have, take, receive, uſe, exerciſe, and enjoy, all and ſingular the gifts, grants, liberties, priviledges, immunities, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, benefits, advantages, profits, commodities, power, ability and authority herein before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, or otherwiſe by any other former Letters Patents given, granted or confirmed unto the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Colledge or Comminalty, or any of them, without the lett, hinderance, interruption, or diſturbance of us, our heirs, or ſucceſſors, or of any the officers or Miniſters of us, our heirs or ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, or of any other perſon or perſons whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:54229:34"/>And further of our like eſpecial grace, certain<note place="margin">This Patent to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed next Parliament.</note> knowledge, and meer motion, we will and for us, our heirs and ſucceſſors, do promiſe and grant to and with the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors by theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents. That at the next Parliament or Seſſion of Parliament, of us, our heirs or ſucceſſors, to be holden within this our Realm of <hi>England,</hi> We, our heirs or ſucceſſors, will give and grant our Royal and free aſſent and conſent to any Act, Bill, or Petition, by the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty, or their ſucceſſors, or any of them in the ſame Parliament, or Seſſion of Parliament, to be exhibited or preferred, and by the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Comminalty of the ſaid Parliament, to be approved, and aſſented unto, for the better enabling, authorizing, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſting of the ſaid Preſident, or Colledge and Comminalty, and their Succeſſors, to and with the ſeveral grants, powers, priviledges, authorities, exemptions, immunities, and other matters and things, in theſe preſents to them given, granted, and confirmed, or intended to be to them given, granted or confirmed according to our gracious intent and meaning herein before ſpecified and expreſſed.</p>
            <p>And further we will and by theſe preſents for us, our heirs and ſucceſſors, do grant unto the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and<note place="margin">A farther Confirmation of this Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> their Succeſſors, That theſe our Letters Patents, and all and ſingular the gifts, grants, authorities, powers, priviledges, and immunities, and other
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:54229:34"/>
things therein contained, ſhall be good, firm, available, and effectual in the law, to the intents and purpoſes aforeſaid, and ſhall be in all and every our Courts of Record, and elſwhere had, taken, conſtrued and adjudged moſt ſtrongly againſt us, our heirs and ſuceſſors, and moſt benignly, favourably, and beneficially to and for the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, any Statute, Act, Ordinance, Cuſtome, Uſage, Gift, Grant, or any other matter, or thing heretofore had, made, uſed, ordained, or provided, to the contrary in any wiſe notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs we will and our intent and mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, That the ſaid Preſident and Colledge or Comminalty and their Succeſſors, ſhall anſwer and pay to us, our heirs and ſucceſſors for and in reſpect of the fines, amerciaments, penalties, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures, and ſums of money herein before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, and by theſe preſents to them granted, as aforeſaid, the yearly Rent of Six pounds of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful<note place="margin">Six pound Rent to the King.</note> money of <hi>England</hi> at the Receipt of our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> at the Feaſt of the Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciation of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and St. <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael</hi> the Archangel, by even and equal portions, any thing herein contained to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. Although expreſs mention of the true yearly value or certainty of the premiſes, or any of them, or of any other gifts or grants by us or any of our progenitors or predeceſſors to the foreſaid Preſident and Colledge or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minalty heretofore made, in theſe preſents is
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:54229:35"/>
not made, or any Statute, Act, Ordinance, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, Proclamation or Reſtraint to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary thereof, heretofore had, made, ordained or provided, or any other matter, cauſe or thing whatſoever, to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>In witneſs whereof we have cauſed theſe our Letters to be made Patents. Witneſs our ſelf at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 
                  <date>the eighth day of October in the fifteenth year of our Reign of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of <hi>Scotland</hi> the one and fiftieth.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Yonge.
<hi>Per bre. de privato Sigillo.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Irr. in memorand. Scacc. de Anno octavo Regis nune Caroli viz. inter Record. de termino ſci. Michis Ro. Ex parte Reverend. dci. dom. Regis.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:54229:35"/>
            <head>In magno Rotulo de Anno 23. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis Caroli London.</head>
            <p>PReſidens Colleg. &amp; Coitas Medicor. Lond. deb. 27 l. 10 <hi>s.</hi> medietas 55 <hi>l.</hi> verſus Johannem Bugge de parochia Ecclie Xpi London<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> recuperat per Judicium Cur. quia exercuit facultatem Medicin. per ſpatium xi. menſ. integr. non exiſten. admiſſus ad exercendum &amp; occupand. dict. facultat. medicin, per Preſident. Collegium ſeu Communitat. facultat. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicin. London lris ſigillo ſuo comui ſigillat. contra formam ſtatuti iu hmoi caſu edit. &amp; proviſ. ſuper ipos onerat. virtute Ordinis hujus Scacc. dat. tertio Julii Anno <hi>15<hi rend="sup">to</hi>
               </hi> Regis Caroli.</p>
            <p>But the ſaid ſum of 27 <hi>l.</hi> 10 <hi>s.</hi> is allowed to the Preſident and Colledge of the Faculty of Phyſick within the City of <hi>London</hi> by Letters Patents under the Great Seal of <hi>England,</hi> bearing date the 8. day of <hi>October,</hi> in the 15. year of the late King <hi>James,</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and of <hi>Scotland</hi> the 51. and by Judgment of the Barons of this Court of publique Exchequer entred among the Records of Eaſter Term in the 7. year of the reign of the late King <hi>Charles</hi> in the cuſtody of the firſt Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer there, Roll the 24.</p>
            <p>And they are quit.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Examined by <hi>Hen. Croke</hi> Clerk of the Pipe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:54229:36"/>
            <head>The Common Law againſt them that practice, being not admitted.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>SI un que neſt Phyſition ou Surgeon emprent ſur luy un cure que murruſt in ſa main que ceſt fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie. Stanford</hi> Pleas of the Crown, <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Fitz Herbert. tit. Cor. pag.</hi> 311. <hi>Briton fol.</hi> 14. Which <hi>Dalton</hi> thus Engliſheth, And if one which is no Phyſician or Surgeon (or which is not allowed to uſe or practiſe ſuch Faculty) will take a cure upon him, and his Patient dieth under his hand, this hath been holden to be felonie. <hi>Lambard Eiren. tit. Felonie,</hi> ſaith thus, That <hi>Thorpe</hi> 43. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. 33. ſaith he knew one to be indited accordingly. But if this ſhould be drawn to felony, then I ſee not but that the ſame muſt be accounted murther in reſpect either of the bold preſumption or of the will to do harm, which doth amount to malice. And <hi>Dalt.</hi> in his Countrey Juſtice chap. 93. que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth thus of this Caſe, It cannot be diſcerned whether the Patients death cometh by any wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full default in the party, taking ſuch Cure upon him or by the Patients infirmities. Again, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in them no will to do harm, but rather to do good; and then the <hi>Stat.</hi> 34. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. leaveth ſo great a liberty of ſuch practiſe to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful perſons, that it will be hard now to make it felony.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:54229:36"/>
            <head>A Copy of an Exemplification of a Recovery againſt <hi>Edmund Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner</hi> 11. <hi>Feb.</hi> 6. <hi>Jac.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <hi>JAcobus</hi> dei Gra. Angl. Scot. Fran. &amp; Hib<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:aber"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>er</ex>
                  </expan>nie Rex fidei defenſor. &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>O<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ibus ad quos preſentes l<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re n<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re pervenerint ſaltem</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>inſpeximus quoddam Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordum coram nobis hitum in hec verba ſs. Plita co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram dno Rege apud Weſtm. Termino ſci Michis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Regni dom. Jacobi nunc Regis Anglie tertio Rotlo 438. ſſ. London ſſ. memorand. quod als ſcilt Termino ſce Trinitatis ultimo preterit. Coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. ven. Thomas Langton in Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Doctor Preſidens Collegii ſive Coitatis facultatis Medicine London qui tam pro dno Rege qm pro ſeipo &amp; Collegio predcto ſequitur per L. G. Atturnat. ſuum Et protulit hic in Curia dct. dom. Regis tunc ibm quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam billam ſuam verſus Edmundum Gardiner in Cuſtod. Marr. &amp;c. de plito debi &amp; ſunt pleg. de proc. ſcilt. Johes Doo &amp; Ricus Roo Que quidem billa ſequitur in hec verba ſſ. Londn ſſ. Thomas Langton in Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Doctor Preſidens Collegii, ſive Coitatis facultatis Medicine London. qui tam pro dno Rege quam pro ſeipo &amp; Collegio predco ſequitur queritur de Edmundo Gardiner in Cuſtod. Marr. mareſc. dni Regis coram ipo Rege exiſten. de plico quod reddat eidem dno Regi ac prefat. Preſiden. &amp; Collegio predco Sexaginta li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bras legalis mouete Anglie quas eis debet &amp; injuſte
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:54229:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
detinet pro eo viz. quod cum dns Henricus octavm nuper Rex Anglie per lras ſuas Paten. magno ſigillo ſuo Anglie ſigillat. Curie<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> hic prolat. geren. dat. apud Weſtm. in Com. Midd. viceſimo tertio die Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris anno Regni ſui decimo pro publico bono hujus regni in debito <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xercitio facultatis Medicine &amp; bona adminiſtracone Medicinar. hend. incorporaſſet &amp; feciſſet de Johe Chamber, Thoma Linacre Ferdinando de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoria ad tunc Medicis ejuſdem nuper Regis &amp; Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholao Halſwell Johe Franciſci &amp; Robto Yaxley &amp; oib<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>bus</ex>
               </expan> aliis viris ejuſdem facultatis tunc de &amp; infru Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitat. London. unum corpus &amp; perpetuam Coitatem ſive ſocietatem facultat. Medicine. Et ad hend. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuam ſucceſsionem &amp; Coie Sigillum &amp; ad Eligend. annuatim unum Preſident. ejuſdem ſocietatis ſive Coitatis adſupervidend. regend. &amp; gubnand. eandem ſocietatem ſive Coitatem &amp; omnes hoies ejuſdem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatis cum diverſis aliis privileg. &amp; aliis rebus per predom nuper regem eis conceſſs pro republica hujus regni, prout in predcis lris paten. plenius continetur Quar. tenor ſequitur in hec verba ſſ. Henricus Dei grac. Rex, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Cumque etiam in Statuto in Parliament. dci. nuper<note place="margin">Recital of the Charter.</note> Regis Henrici octavi tent. apud London. decimo quinto die Aprilis anno Regni ſui quarto decimo &amp; abinde adjornat. uſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abquam"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>quam</ex>
               </expan> Weſtm<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in Com. Midd. ultimo die Julii anno regni dci. nuper regis quinto decimo &amp; tunc &amp; ibm tent. inactitat. fuit quod predca Corporaco predce Civitatis &amp; ſocietat. facultat. medicine predce &amp; oia &amp; ſingula conceſſa articul. &amp; al. res content. &amp; ſpec. in predcis lris paten. forent approbat. conceſſ. ratiſicat. &amp; confirmat. &amp; clare authorizat. &amp; admiſſ. bona
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:54229:37"/>
litima &amp; valida Anglice available prefat. Corpori incorporat. &amp; eorum ſucceſſoribus imperpetuum in tam amplo &amp; largo modo qm poſſet capi putari &amp; conſtrui pro cadem, prout in eodem ſtatuto inter alia plenius continetur.</p>
            <p>Predictus tamen Edmundus Gardiner qui ad dcm.<note place="margin">Charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Gradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</note> facultat. exercend per Preſidentem &amp; Coitatem facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis Medicine London. predct. per lras Preſident. &amp; Collegii predci. ſigillo ſuo Coi ſigillat. non admiſſus eſt, nec unquam ante bec admiſſus fuit ſtatutum predcm minime ponderans nec penam in predcis Lris paten. content. verens dcam facultatem Medicine per ſpacium duodecim menſium jam ult. elapſs. &amp; prox preceden. ante diem impetraconis hujus bille ſcilt ultimum diem Maii anno regni dni Jacobi nunc Regis Anglie tertio in Civitate London. predca vidlt in parochia bte Marie de Arcubus in Warda de Cheap London. exercuit &amp; adhuc exercet contra formam Irar. paten. predcar. &amp; Statut. predct. per quod acco accrevit eidem Preſidenti qui tam &amp;c. ad exigend. &amp; hend. de prefat. Edmundo Gardiner pro predco dno Rege nunc &amp; eidem Preſidenti &amp; Collegio predco predcas ſexaginta libas vidlt pro quolibet menſe predcoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duodecim menſium Centum ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos predcus tamen Edms licet ſepius requiſit. &amp; predcas ſexaginta libras prefato dno Regi &amp; eidem Preſidenti &amp; Collegio predco ſeu eorum alteri nondum ſolvit ſed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aei huc uſque ſoluere omio contradixit &amp; adhuc contradic. ad damnum ipius Preſidentis qui tam &amp;c. quadragint. librar. &amp; inde tam pro eodem dno rege quam pro eodem Preſident. &amp; Collegio predco pred. ſectam &amp;c. Et modo ad hunc diem ſcilt diem Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curii prox. poſt octabis ſci. Michis iſlo eodem Termino
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:54229:38"/>
uſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> quem diem predcus. Edmundus Gardiner huit licenc. billam predca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> interloquendi &amp; tunc ad reſpondend. &amp;c.<note place="margin">Gardiners An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</note> coram dmo rege apud Weſtm. ven. tam predict. preſiden. qui tam &amp;c. per Atturnat. ſuum predcum quam predcus Edus Gard. per W. S. Atturnat. ſuum. Et idem Edus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. vim &amp; injur. quando &amp;c. &amp; dic. quod predict. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiden. &amp; Collegium qui tam &amp;c. acconem ſuam predcam inde verſus eum here ſeu manutenere non debet, Quia dic. quod per quendam Actum in Parliament. dci. dni Henrici nunc Regis Anglie octavi apud Weſtm. predcam in dct. Con. Midd. Anno Regni ſui Triceſimo quarto &amp; triceſimo quinto tent. edit. recitando in eodem Actu. Cum in Parliamento tent. &amp;c. quor. pretextu idem<note place="margin">Recites the Act of 34. 35. Hen. 8. ca.</note> Edms exiſtens ſubdit. dci. dni Regis nunc natus infra hoc Regnum Anglie, vidlt apud London. vidlt in paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia bte Marie de Arcubus in Warda. de Cheape London Achens cogniconem &amp; experientiam nature herbar. radicum &amp; aquar. ac opaconis eordem per tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus predcum in narracone predca ſuperius ſpec. apud London. predcam in parochia &amp; Warda predcis practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabat uſus fuit &amp; miniſtrabat in &amp; ad diverſas ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriores penas les uncomes vulner a impoſtumacones ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriores intumacones &amp; morbos diverſs herbam &amp; herbas unguent. lavacra lez pulteſſes &amp; emplaſtra ac potiones de Calculo &amp; Stranguria &amp; febribus ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum cognitionem experientiam &amp; notitiam ſuas in morbis penis &amp; lez maladies predict. ſcdm formam &amp; eſſcm predci Actus edit. in Annis 34. &amp; 35. ſupdcis. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſque hoc quod idem Edms dcam facultatem medicine infra Civitatem London. predcam aliter ſeu alio modo exercuit ſeu exercet, prout predcus Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens &amp; Collegium qui tam &amp;c. per narracoem ſuam
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:54229:38"/>
predcam ſuperius verſus eum queritur. Et hoc parat. eſt verificare unde pet. judm. ſi predcus Preſidens &amp; Collegium qui tam &amp;c. acconem ſuam predcam inde verſus eum here ſeu manu tenere debeat &amp;c. Et<note place="margin">Colledge Replies.</note> predcus Thomas Langton qui tam &amp;c. dic. quod ipe pro aliqua per predcum Eamundum Gardiner ſuperius plitando allegat. ab accone ſua predca verſus ipm Edmund. hend. precludi non debet, quia dicit quod per quendum actum in Parliamento dne Marie nuper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine Anglie tent. per prorogaconem apud Weſtm. in Com. Midd. 24. die Octobris Anno Regni ipius nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per regine primo &amp; ibm continuat. uſque ſextum diem menſis Decembris ex tunc prox. ſequen. recitan. quod cum in dco Parliamento tent. apud London. dco decimo quinto die Aprilis Anno decimo quarto Regni dci. Regis Henrici oct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vi &amp; inde adjornat. uſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ad Weſtm. predct. ultimo die Julii in anno decimo quinto Regni ejuſdem Regis, &amp; ad tunc tent. inactitat. exiſtit quod dca Conceſsio Corporationis per Lras Paten. fact. &amp; conceſſs per eundem nuper Regem Medicis London. &amp; oes Clauſul. &amp; articuli content. in eadem Conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione eſſent approbat. conceſſs. ratificat. &amp; confirmat. per idem Parliamentum pro conſideracone inde ſtabilit. exiſtit in dco Parliamento dce nuper Regine Marie, quod Statutum illud ſive Actus Parliamenti cum quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet Articulo &amp; Clauſula in eodem content. ex tunc deinceps ſtaret &amp; continuaret ſemper in plenis robore vigore &amp; effectu Aliquo Actu Statuto lege conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine vel aliqua alia re fact. habita vel uſa in contrar. in aliquo non obſtan. Prout per idem Statutum Anno Regni dce nuper Regine Marie primo ſupradco edit. plenius liquet. Et hoc parat. eſt verificare unde ex
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:54229:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
quo predcus Edms practitiam &amp; exercitium predcte facultatis Medicine ſuperius recogn. idem Thomas Langton qui tam &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it judicium &amp; debit. predcum tam dco dno Regi quam eidem Thome et Collegio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> predco unacum dampnis ſuis accone detenconis debi. illius ſibi adjudicari &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Et predcus Edms Gardiner dic. quod plitum predcm<note place="margin">Gardiner Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes.</note> per predct Thomam Langton modo et forma predctis ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perius replicando plitat. materia<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> in eodem cont. minus ſufficien. in lege exiſtunt ad acconem predci Thome Langton predicam verſus ipm Edmuna Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner hend. manutenend. Ad quod idem Edms Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner neceſſe non habet nec per legem terre tenetur ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quo modo reſpondere unde pro defend ſufficien. repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caconis in hac parte idem Edms Gardiner ut prius pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit indicium. Et quod predctus Thomas Langton ab accone ſua predca verſus ipm Edmundum Gardiner hend. precludat &amp;c. Et predcus Thomas Langton qui tam &amp;c. dic. quod plitum predcum per ipm Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam modo et forma predcis ſuperius replicando plitat. materiaque in eodem content. bona et ſufficien. in lege exiſtunt ad acconem ipius Thome Langton predcam verſus predcum Edmundum Gardiner hend. manute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nend. Quod quidem plitum materiamque in eodem content. idem Thomas Langton paratus eſt verificare et probare prout Cur &amp;c. Et quia predcus Edmundus Gardiner ad plitum illud non reſpond. nec ill. huc uſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> aliqualiter dedic, idem Thomas Langton ut prius petit Judicium et debm predctm tam dco dno Regi quam eidem Thome et Collegio predco unacum dampnis ſuis predictis accone detenconis debit. illius ſibi adjudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cari &amp;c. Et quia Cur dni Regis hic de Judicio ſuo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:54229:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
de &amp; ſuper premiſsis reddend. nondum adviſatur, dies inde da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. eſt partibus predcis coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. uſque diem Jovis prox. poſt octabis ſci. Hillari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> de Judicio ſuo de &amp; ſuper premiſsis audiend. &amp;c. eo quod Cur. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i Regis hic inde nondum &amp;c. Ad quem diem coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. ven. partes predce per Attornat. ſuos predcos. Et quia Cur. dni Regis hic de Judicio ſuo de &amp; ſuper premiſsis predcis reddend. nondum adviſatur dies ulterius inde dat. eſt partibus predcis coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. uſque diem Mercurii prox. poſt xviii. Paſchae de judicio inde audiend. &amp;c. eo quod Cur. dni Regis hic inde nondum &amp;c. Ad quem diem coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. ven. partes predce per Atturnat. ſuos predcos. Et quia Cur. dni Regis hic de Judicio ſuo de &amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per premiſsis predcis reddend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nondum adviſatur dies ulterius inde dat. eſt partibus predcis coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. uſque diem Veneris prox. poſt Craſtin. ſce Trinitatis ex tunc. prox. ſequen. de Judicio inde au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diend. eo quod Cur. dni Regis hic inde nondum &amp;c. Ad quem diem coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. ven. partes predce per Atturn. ſuos predcos, ſuper quo viſs. &amp; per Curiam dni Regis hic plenius intellcis oib<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abbus"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>bus</ex>
               </expan> &amp; ſingulis premiſsis, maturaque deliberacone inde hita pro eo quod videt. Cur. dni Regis hic quod Plitum predcm per predcm Thomam Langton qui tam &amp;c. ſuperius replicando plitat. materiaque in eodem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. bona &amp; ſufficien. in lege exiſtit ad acconem ipius Thome Langton qui tam &amp;c. verſus predcm Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundum hend. manutenend. Ideo conſs. eſt quod predcus Thomas Langton qui tam &amp;c. recuperet verſus Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundum debitum predcm unde dns Rex heat unam
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:54229:40"/>
medietatem, &amp; predcus Thomas Langton qui tam &amp;c. &amp; Collegium pd<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> heat alteram medietatem juxta for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum lrar. paten. predcar. &amp; Statut. pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>. Quod<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> idem Thomas Langton qui tam &amp;c. recuperet verſus<note place="margin">Coſts.</note> eum ſex libras treſdecim ſolidos &amp; quatuor denarios pro damnis ſuis que ſuſtinuit tam accone detenconis debi predci quam pro miſs &amp; cuſtagiis ſuis per ipſum circa ſectam ſuam in hac parte appoſit. eidem Thome Langton qui tam &amp;c. per Cur. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i Regis hic ex aſſenſu ſuo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicat. Et predcus Edmundus in miſerecord. &amp;c. Poſtea ſcilt die Sabbi prox. octab. ſci Martini Anno regni dni Jacobi nunc Regis Anglie ſexto coram eodem dno Rege apud Weſtm. ven. predcus Praeſidens per Attur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. ſuum predcum &amp; Cogn. ſe eſſe ſatisfact. per predcm Edmundum Gardiner de tota parte ſua debi predci &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> damnis predcis que ad ipn Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentem pertinet ideo ipe idem Edms de tota parte illa &amp; de damnis illis ſit quiet. &amp;c. Quod quidem Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordum coram nobis ſic hitum duximus exemplifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cand. In cujus rei Teſtimonium has lras nras ſieri fecimus patentes</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Teſte Thoma Fleminge apud Weſtm. <date>undecimo die Februarii Anno Regni nri Anglie Francie &amp; Hibnie ſexto &amp; Scocie quadrageſimo ſcdo.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Byng. &amp; Byng.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:54229:40"/>
            <head>A Copy of an Exemplification of a Recovery againſt Doctor <hi>Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham 13. Feb. 6. Jacobi.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>JAcobus Dei grac. Angl. Scot. Franc. &amp; Hibnie Rex fidei defen. &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>Omnibus ad quos preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ut ſupra ſſs Plita coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. Termino ſci Michis Anno Regni dni Jacobi nunc Regis Anglie quinto Rotulo 299. ſſs London ſſs Memorand. quod als ſcilt. Termino ſce Trinitatis ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo preterito Coram dno Rege apudweſtm. ven. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidens Collegii ſive Coitat. facultatis medicine Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don qui tam pro dno Rege quam pro eodem Praeſidente &amp; Collegio predco ſequitur per Laurencium Gibſon Atturnat. ſuum. Et protulit hic in Cur. dci dni Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis tunc ibm quandam Billam ſuam verſus Thomam Bonham in Cuſtod. Marr. &amp;c. de plito debi &amp; ſunt pleg. de proſs. ſcilt. Johes Doo &amp; Ricus Roo. Que qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Billa ſequitur in hec verba ſſs. London. ſſs. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidens Collegii feu Coitat. facultat. Medicine London. qui tam &amp;c. <hi>(as in</hi> Gardiners <hi>Caſe.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Et modo ad hunc diem ſcilt. diem Veneris prox. poſt<note place="margin">Bonhams An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</note> octab. ſci. Michis iſto eodem Termino uſque quem diem predcus Thomas Bonham huit Licenc. ad billam predcam interloquendi &amp; tunc ad reſpondend. &amp;c. Coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. ven. tam predcus Praeſidens Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legii ſeu Coitatis dce facultatis Medicine London. qui tam &amp;c. per Atturnat. ſuum p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> predcum qm predcus
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:54229:41"/>
Thomas Bonham per William Edwards Atturn. ſuum. Et idem Thomas defend. vim &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. quando &amp;c. Et dic. quod predcus Praeſidens Collegii ſeu Coitat. dce facultat. Medicine London. qui tam &amp;c. pro dco dno Rege quam pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>odem Praeſidente &amp; Collegio predco ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur acconem ſuam predcam inde verſus cum habere ſeu manutenere non debet, quia dic. quod bene &amp; ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt, quod predcus dus Henricus octavus nuper Rex Anglie per predcas lras ſuas patent. magno ſigillo ſuo Anglie ſigillat<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> geren. dat. apud Weſtm. in predco Com. Midd. predco Vice ſimo tertio die Septembris Anno Regni ſui decimo ſup. dco pro publico bono hujus Regni in debo exertio facultat. Medicine &amp; bona admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracone Medicinar. hend. &amp; pro cauſis &amp; conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus in eiſdem lris patentibus expreſsis incorporaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet &amp; feciſſet de predcis Johne Chamber, Thomas Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacre &amp; Ferdinando de victoria ad tunc Medicis ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem nuper Regis &amp; Nichao Halſewel Johe Franciſci &amp; Robto Yaxley &amp; oibus aliis viris ejuſdem facultatis tunc de &amp; infra dcam Civitatem London<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unum Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus &amp; perpetuam Coitatem ſive ſocietatem facultat. Medicine &amp; ad hend. perpetuam ſucceſsionem &amp; Coe ſigillum, &amp; ad eligend. annuatim unum preſiden. ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſocietatis ſive Coitatis ad ſupervidend. regend. &amp; gub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and. eandem ſocietatem ſive Coiatem &amp; omnes homines ejuſdem facultat. Cum diverſis aliis privile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giis &amp; al. rebus per dnm nuper regem eis conceſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> reipublica hujus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Regni prout in predcis lris paten. ut prefertur plenius continetur. Ad quod predcus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uper Rex conceſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. etiam per eaſdem lras patent. eiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em tunc Preſidenti &amp; Collegio ſeu Coitat. &amp; ſucceſſor. ſuis quod nemo in dca Civitate aut<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> per ſept. milliar.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:54229:41"/>
in Circuit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ejuſdem exerceret dcam facultatem niſi ad hoc per predcum Praeſidentem &amp; Coitat. ſeu ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures eorum qui pro tempore fuerint admiſſs foret per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>juſdem Praeſidentis &amp; Collegii lras ſigillo ſuo Coi ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillat. ſub pena Centum ſolidor pro quolibet menſe quo non admiſſus eandem facultatem exerceret, dimid. inde dco dno nuper Regi &amp; heredibus ſuis et dimid. dco Praeſidenti &amp; Collegio applicand. &amp;c. <hi>and recites the Statute of 14.</hi> Hen. <hi>8. cap. 5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Et predcus Thomas Bonham ulterius dic. qd ipe idem Thomas diu ante predum viceſimum quintum diem Junii Anno Regni dci dni Regis nunc Anglie quinto ſupradicto, ſcilt. ſcdo die Julii Anno Dni mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limo quingenteſimo nonage ſimo quinto in Alma Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demia Cantabrigie ſuſcepit gradum &amp; dignitat. Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in Medicinis &amp; ad tunc &amp; ibm ſcilt. eodem ſcdo die Julii an. dni millimo quingenteſimo nonageſimo quinto ſupradicto apud Cantabrigiam predcam in Com. Cantabr. rite et li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ime Ordinat. &amp; fact. fuit Graduat. Anglice a Graduat pred vidlt Doctor in Medicinis ſedum leges ſtatuta conſtitucones &amp; Ordinacones dce Academie Cantabrigie. Quodque idem Thomas tunc et ibm adimplevit omnia Anglice, <hi>did accompliſh all things</hi> pro forma ſua ſine aliqua gratia Quorum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> pretex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u idem Thomas hujmodi Graduat. Cantabrigie vidlt Doctor. in Medicinis in forma predca exiſten. qui adimpleviſſet omnia Anglice, <hi>had accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all things,</hi> pro <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orma ſua ſine aliqua gratia dcam facultatem Medicine per predcm ſpatium duodecim menſium vlt. elapſ. et prox. preceden. ante diem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petraconis bille predce ſcilt. predcm viceſimum quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum diem Junii ann. Regni d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i Regis nunc
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:54229:42"/>
Anglie quinto ſupradicto in dca Civitati London. vidlt. in predca parochiab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Marie de Arcubus in Warda d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cheape London. exercuit modo et forma prout predcus Preſidens qui tam &amp;c. ſuperius verſus eum narravit prout ei bene licuit. Et hoc paratus eſt verificare, unde petit Judicium ſi predcus Praeſidens qui tam &amp;c. acconem ſuam predcam inde verſus eum habere ſeu ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutenere debeat &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Ad quem diem coram dno Rege apud Weſtm. ven. tum predcus Preſidens qui tam &amp;c. qm predcus Thomas Bonham per Atturnat. ſuos Predcos. Super quo viſſs et per Cur. dni Regis hic plenius intellcis oibus et ſingulis premiſsis maturaque deliberacone inde hita pro eo qd videtur Cur. dni Regis hic qd plitum predcm per pre fat. Thomam Bonham modo et forma predcis ſuperius plitat. materiaque in eodem content. minus ſufficien. in lege exiſtunt ad ipm Praeſidentem qui tam &amp;c. ab ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cone ſua predca verſus ipm Thomam hend. precludend. ideo conceſs. eſt predcus Preſiden. qui tam &amp;c. recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peret verſus ipm Thomam Bonham debm predcm unde dns Rex heat unam medietatem &amp;c. et recuperet duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decim libras pro damnis ſuis que ſuſtinuit &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>In cujus rei teſtimonium &amp;c. dat. <date>13. die Febr. Anno Regni Anglie Fr. et Hib. 6. et Scot. 42.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Byng. &amp; Byng.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="trial_proceedings">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:54229:42"/>
            <head>Trinity 7. <hi>Jacobi</hi> 1609. In the Common Bench.</head>
            <head type="sub">Colledge of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> Caſe.</head>
            <head type="sub">Brownlow's Reports: <hi>Second Part.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THomas Bonham</hi> brought an Action of falſe<note place="margin">Action of falſe impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment.</note> Impriſonment againſt Doctor <hi>Alkins</hi> and divers other Doctors of Phyſick: The Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants juſtified, that King <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>Anno Decimo</hi> of his Reign, founded a Colledge of Phyſicians, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>Letters Patents</hi> of their Corporation: And that they have Authority by that to chooſe a Preſident, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as by the <hi>Letters Patents, &amp;c.</hi> and then pleads the <hi>Statute</hi> of 32. <hi>H.</hi> 8. chapt. 40. and that the ſaid Doctor <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kins</hi> was choſen Preſident, according to the ſaid Act and <hi>Letters Patents,</hi> and where by the ſaid Act and <hi>Letters Patents</hi> it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided that none ſhall practiſe in the City of <hi>London</hi> or the Suburbs of that; or within ſeven miles of the ſaid City, or exerciſe the faculty of Phyſick, if he be not to that admitted by the Letters of the Preſident and Colledge, ſealed with their common Seal, under the Penalty of a hundred ſhillings, for every Moneth (that he not
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:54229:43"/>
being admitted) ſhall exerciſe the ſaid faculty; further we will and grant for us and Our Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, that by the Preſident and Colledge of the Society for the time being, and for their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors for ever, that they may chooſe four every year, that ſhall have the overſeeing, and ſearching, correcting, and governing, of all in the ſaid City being Phyſicians, uſing the faculty of Medicines in the ſaid City, and other Phyſicians abroad whatſoever uſing the faculty of Phyſicking by any means frequenting and uſing, within the City or Suburbs thereof, or within ſeven miles in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of the ſaid City, and of puniſhing them for the ſaid offences, in not well executing, making and uſing that: And that the puniſhment of thoſe Phyſicians uſing the ſaid faculty, ſo in the premiſes offending, by Fines, Amercements, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments of their Bodies, and by other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable and fitting waies ſhall be executed: Note the preamble of theſe <hi>Letters Patents</hi> is, <hi>Quod cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>regii officii noſtri munus arbitremur, ditionis noſtrae, Hominum felicitati omniratione Conſulere: Id autem vel inprimis fore, ſi improborum conaminibus tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtive occurramus, apprime neceſſarium fore deximus, improborum quoque hominum, qui medicinam magis avaritiae ſuae cauſa, quam ullius bonae conſcientiae fidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia profitebuntur unde Rudi &amp; credulae plebi plurima incommoda oriuntur, audaciam compeſcere.</hi> And that the Plaintiff practiſed in <hi>London,</hi> without admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Colledge, and being Summoned to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the Colledge, and examined if he would give ſatisfaction to the Colledge according to the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:54229:43"/>
ſaid <hi>Letters Patents and Statute,</hi> he anſwered that he had received his decree to be Doctor of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick by the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by the Univerſity to practiſe, and confeſt that he had practiſed within the ſaid City, and as he conceived, it was lawful for him to practiſe there, that upon that the ſaid Preſident and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty fined him to a hundred ſhillings, and for not paying that and his other contempt, commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him to priſon, to which the Plaintiff replied as aforeſaid, and upon this demurrer was joyned: And <hi>Harris</hi> for the Defendant, ſaith, that this hath<note place="margin">Serjeant <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> been at another time adjudged in the Kings Bench, where the ſaid Colledge impoſed a Fine of five pound upon a Doctor of Phyſick which practiſed in <hi>London</hi> without their admiſſion, and for the non payment of that, brought an Action of Debt, and adjudged that it lay well, and that the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 32. H.</hi> 8. extends as well to Graduats, as to others, for it is general, and Graduats are not excepted in the <hi>Statute,</hi> nor in the <hi>Letters Patents,</hi> and all the miſchiefs intended to be redreſſed by this, are not expreſſed in that, and the <hi>Statute</hi> ſhall not be intended to puniſh Impoſtors only, but all other which practiſe without examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and admittance; for two things are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Phyſicians, that is, learning and experience, and upon that there is the proverb, <hi>Experto crede Roberto:</hi> And the <hi>Statute intends</hi> that none ſhall practiſe here but thoſe which are moſt learned and expert, more then ordinary: And for that the <hi>Statute</hi> provides, that none ſhall practiſe here
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:54229:44"/>
without allowance and examination by the Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> and the Dean of <hi>Pauls,</hi> and four learned Doctors: But in other places the examination is referred only to the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, and the reaſon of the difference is, for that, that <hi>London</hi> is the heart of the Kingdome: And here the King and his Court, the Magiſtrates and Judges of the Law, and other Magiſtrates are reſident, and with this agreed the government of other well go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned Cities in <hi>Italy</hi> and other Nations, as it appears by the preamble of the ſaid <hi>Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents:</hi> and it appears by the <hi>Statute,</hi> that this was not intended to extend to Impoſtors only, for that the word Impoſtor is not mentioned in the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute:</hi> And the <hi>Statute</hi> provides that they ſhall be puniſhed, as well for doing and uſing, as for ill uſing: And alſo it is provided that the <hi>Statute</hi> of 1. <hi>Marie</hi> 1. Parliament, chap. 9. That the Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, Goalers, or Keepers of the Wards, Goals, and Priſons within the City and Precinct of that, ſhall receive unto his Priſon all ſuch perſon and perſons ſo offending which are ſent or committed to them, and thoſe ſafely ſhall keep without Bayl, till the party ſo committed, ſhall be diſcharged by the ſaid Preſident, or other perſon by the ſaid Colledge to that authoriſed, by which it appears, that the Goalers, Keepers of Priſons, have power to retain ſuch which are committed: That then the Preſident ſhall have power to commit, for things Implyed are as ſtrong as things Expreſſed; as it appears by the <hi>Com. Stradling and Morgans</hi> Caſe: and alſo in the Earl of <hi>Leiceſters</hi> Caſe,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:54229:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>
where it is agreed, that Joynture before Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture cannot be waved, and this is implyed within the <hi>Statute of 27. H.</hi> 8. And ſo the <hi>Statute of 2. Ed.</hi> 6. Provides that after ſeven years Tythes ſhall be paid, by which it is Collected by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, that during ſeven years, Tythes ſhall not be paid; and ſo he prayed Judgement for the Defendants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dodridge</hi> Serjeant of the King, for the Plaintiff ſaid, that the Statute of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4 <hi>H.</hi> 8. chap. 5. and the <hi>Letters Patents</hi> give power to four Cenſors to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh for ill executing, doing, and uſing the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of a Phyſician, and the Plantiff was not charged for ill executing of it, doing or uſing: But it is averred, where <hi>Revera</hi> the Plaintiff was nothing ſufficient to exerciſe the ſaid Art, and being examined, leſs apt to anſwer, and thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they forbade him, and being ſent for and not appearing, was amerced five pound, and order that he ſhould be Arreſted, and being Arreſted, upon his appearance, being examined if he would ſubmit himſelf to the ſaid Colledge; he anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and confeſſed, that he had practiſed within the ſaid City, being a Doctor of Phyſick as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, as well to him it was lawful, and that he would practiſe here again, for which he was committed to Priſon: So that he was amerced for his contempt in the uſing of the ſaid Art, and committed to Priſon for his anſwer upon his examination: And he conceived that there are two queſtions conſiderable.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:54229:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>Firſt, if the Colledge may reſtrain a Doctor of Phyſick of his practiſe in <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, admitting that they may, then if theſe are the cauſes for which they may commit by their <hi>Letters Patents;</hi> the firſt reaſon is drawn from the <hi>Letters Patents,</hi> and the ſaid <hi>Statutes,</hi> in which he ſaid that the intent of the King was the<note place="margin">Walter.</note> end of his work: And this intent ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for three reaſons apparent in the words contained in the Grant.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Intempeſtive conatibus occurrere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Improborum Hominum, qui medicinam magis avaritiae ſuae cauſa, quam ullius bonae Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiae fiducia profitebantur, audaciam Compeſcere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, which would invite learned men to practiſe here, and for that would, <hi>quod collegium <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Doctorum &amp; graviorum virorum qui me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinament in urbe noſtra Londino &amp; ſuburbibus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fra ſeptem millia paſsuum in urbe quaquaverſus, publice Exerceant inſtitui volumus &amp; imperanus:</hi> And further he ſaid, that there are three ſorts of men, which meddle with the Body of a man.</p>
            <p>Firſt, is the learned man which reads all Books extant, and his knowledge is ſpeculative, and by that he knew the nature of all ſimples.</p>
            <p>And the ſecond is practive, the knowledge of which is only his experience, he may give <hi>Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt:</hi> But the ignorance of the cauſe of the diſeaſe, and the nature of the things which he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies for the cure of that.</p>
            <p>And the third is an Impoſtor, which takes upon him the knowledge which he hath not, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them the Colledge may puniſh, for <hi>Male
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:54229:45"/>
utendo, faciendo vel exequendo,</hi> by what they will: And this was not the firſt care which was had, for in the 9. <hi>H.</hi> 5. was a private Act made for Phyſicians, by which there is great regard to them which are learned and educated in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity: And for that the Act provides that they ſhall not be prejudicial to any of the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and with this agrees 3. <hi>H.</hi> 8. 11. and the priviledges of them, and the <hi>Docti &amp; graves homines,</hi> mentioned in the <hi>Letters Patents,</hi> are the learned men mentioned in the Act, for the <hi>Statute</hi> provides that they ſhall puniſh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe <hi>Statutes,</hi> and late edicts: And by the former Lawes the Univerſities, that their priviledges were excepted, and by their former <hi>Statutes,</hi> the <hi>Letters Patents</hi> ought to be directed, for it is referred them: Alſo the <hi>Statutes</hi> of this Realm have alwaies had great reſpect to the Graduats of the Univerſities, and it is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe, for <hi>Sudavit &amp; Alſit,</hi> and hath no other reward but this degree which is Doctor, and for that the <hi>Statute of 21. H.</hi> 8. prefers Graduates, and provides that Doctors of Divinity or Bache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors ſhall be capable of two Benefices with Cure without diſpenſation: And ſo 13. <hi>Eliz.</hi> provides that none ſhall be preſented to a Benefice above the value of thirty pound <hi>per annum,</hi> if he be not a Doctor or Bachelor of Divinity: And to the objection, that none ſhall practiſe in <hi>London</hi> or ſeven miles circuit of it without licenſe, that this clauſe ſhall be expounded according to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to that he agreed, for the other branches
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:54229:46"/>
of the <hi>Statute</hi> are made to cheriſh grave and learned men, and for that it ſhall not be intended, that this branch was made for the puniſhment of thoſe, but of others which the <hi>Statute</hi> intended to puniſh.</p>
            <p>And to the ſecond objection, that every Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor is not the learned and grave man intended within the <hi>Statute,</hi> for the knowledge of many of them is only ſpeculative without practiſe, to that he anſwered, that all their Study is practiſe, and that if they have no practiſe of themſelves, then they attend upon others which practiſe, and apply themſelves to know the nature of Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            <p>And to the third objection, that in <hi>London</hi> ought to be choice men, for the <hi>Statute</hi> appoints that they ſhall be examined by the Biſhop, and Dean, and four others at leaſt, and for that there is a more ſtrict courſe for them, then in other places, to that it is agreed: But he ſaid that in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity there is a more ſtrict courſe then this, for here he ought to be publickly approved by many after he hath been examined and anſwered in the Schooles to divers queſtions, and allowed by the Congregation-houſe: And 35. <hi>H.</hi> 6. 55. Doctor is no addition, but a degree, (<hi>quia grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim &amp; progreſsione Doctrinae provenit,</hi> to that, and that Doctor is teacher, and that he was firſt taught by others as Scholars, afterwards he is Maſter, and <hi>Doctor dicitur à docendo, quia docere permittitur,</hi> and they are called Maſters of their faculty, and that the Original of Doctor came
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:54229:46"/>
of the Synagogue of <hi>Jewes,</hi> where there were Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of Law; and it appears that they had their ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in time of <hi>H.</hi> 1. And when a man brings with him the Enſign of Doctrine, there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he ſhould be examined again, for then if they will not allow of him, he ſhall not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, though he be a learned and grave man, and it was not the intent of the King to make a <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly</hi> of this practiſe.</p>
            <p>And to the ſecond point that he propounded, it ſeems that the Juſtification is not good, which is, <hi>Quia non comparuit</hi> upon Summons, he was amerced, and ordered that he ſhall be arreſted, and being arreſted, being examined if he would ſubmit himſelf to the Colledge, he anſwered that he was a Doctor, and had practiſed and would practiſe within the ſaid City, as he conceived he might lawfully do, and for that ſhewing of this caſe he was committed to priſon; and he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved two things upon the Charter.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That it doth not inhibit a Doctor to practiſe, but puniſheth him for ill uſing, exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and making, and may impriſon the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick and Impoſtor, and ſo prayed Judgement for the Plaintiff; and after in <hi>Hillary</hi> Term, in the ſame year, this caſe was argued by all the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, of the Common Bench, and at two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral daies, and the firſt day it was argued by <hi>Foſter, Daniell,</hi> and <hi>Warburton,</hi> Juſtices, at whoſe Arguments I was not preſent, but <hi>Foſter</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued againſt the Plaintiff, and <hi>Daniell</hi> and <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burton</hi> with him, and that the Action of falſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:54229:47"/>
was well maintainable. And the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond day the ſame caſe was argued again by <hi>Walmeſley</hi> Juſtice, and <hi>Coke</hi> chief Juſtice, and <hi>Walmeſley</hi> argued as followeth, that is, that the<note place="margin">Walmeſley.</note> Statute of 3. <hi>H.</hi> 8. was in the negative, that no perſon within the City of <hi>London</hi> or ſeven miles of that, take upon him to exerciſe or occupy, as Phyſician or Chirurgeon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And he doth not know in any caſe where the words of the Statute are negative, that they admit any Interpretation againſt that but one only, and that is the Statute of <hi>Marlebridge chapter</hi> 4. Which provides that no Lord ſhall diſtrain in one County, and the beaſts diſtrained drive into another County, in which caſe though that the words are negative, yet if the Lord diſtrain in one Country, he may drive his beaſts to his Mannor in another County, of which the Lands, in which the diſtreſs was taken, were held, but it is equity and reaſon in this caſe, that the Statute ſhould admit ſuch exception, for it is not of malice, but for that, that the Beaſts may remain within his Fee, but in the principal caſe there is not the like reaſon nor Equity. And alſo the King <hi>H.</hi> 8. in his Letters Patents recites as followeth, that is, <hi>Cum Regii officii noſtri munus arbitremur, ditionis noſtrae hominum ſelicitati omni ratione conſulere, id autem vel imprimis fore, ſi Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proborum conatibus tempeſtive occurremus, apprime ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium duximus improborum quoque hominum, qui medicinam magis avaritiae ſuae cauſa quam ullius bonae conſcientiae fiducia profitebantur,</hi> &amp;c. By which it appears, that it is the office of a King to ſurvey
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:54229:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his Subjects, and he is as a Phyſician to cure their Maladies, and to remove Leproſies amongſt them, and alſo to remove all fumes and ſmels, which may offend or be prejudicial to their health, as it appears by the ſeveral Writs in theſe ſeveral caſes provided, and ſo if a man be not right in his Wits, the King is to have the Protection and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him, leſt he being infirm, waſte, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume his Lands or Goods, and it is not ſufficient for him that his Subjects live, but that they ſhould live happily, and diſcharges not his Office, if his Subjects live a life, but if they live and flouriſh, and he hath care as well of their Bodies as of their Lands and Goods, for Health for the Body is as neceſſary as vertue to the minde, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King <hi>H.</hi> 8. to expreſs his extraordinary care of his Subjects made the ſaid Act, in the third year of his Reign, which was the beginning of his Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, to that purpoſe, and by the Common Law, any Phyſician which was allowed by the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity might practiſe and exerciſe the ſaid faculty within any place within <hi>England,</hi> without any diſpenſation, examination or approbation of any, but after the making of the ſaid Act made in the third year of King <hi>H.</hi> 8. none may practiſe, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, or occupy as Phyſician or Chirurgeon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the City of <hi>London</hi> and ſeven miles of that, if he be not firſt examined, approved, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> and the Dean of <hi>Pauls</hi> for the time being, calling to them, four Doctors of Phyſick or Chirurgeons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>&amp;c,</hi> And that no practiſer may occupy or exerciſe the ſaid fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:54229:48"/>
out of the ſaid Precincts, if he be not firſt examined, approved, and admitted by the Biſhop of the Dioceſs, or in his abſence, by his Vicar ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, every of them calling unto him ſuch expert perſons in the ſaid faculty, as their diſcretions think covenient, and the reaſon of this difference as he conceived, was for that, that in this City, and the ſaid Precincts, the King and all his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel, and all the Judges and Sages of the Law, and divers other men of quality and condition, live and continue, and alſo the place is more ſubject unto Infection, and the aire more peſtiferous, and for that there is more neceſſity, that greater care, diligence, and examination be made of thoſe which practiſed here in <hi>London</hi> and the Precincts aforeſaid, then of thoſe which practiſe in other places of the Realm, for in other places the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have better air, and uſe more exerciſe, and are not ſo ſubject to Infection, and for that there is no cauſe that ſuch care ſhould be uſed for them, for they are not in ſuch danger, and in the Statute there is not any exception of the Univerſities nor of thoſe which are Graduats there, and for that they ſhall be tryed by the ſaid Act, and the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 14. <hi>H. 8. chapter</hi> 5. only excepts thoſe which are Graduats of <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge</hi> which have accompliſhed all things for the form with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Grace; and if this Exception ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to extend to others, then all the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall be excepted by that, and ſuch exception was too general; and over he ſaid, that the Plaintiff gave abſurd and contemptous anſwer,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:54229:48"/>
when he being cited before them, ſaid that he would not be ruled nor directed by them (being ſuch grave and learned men,) and for that, that he hath practiſed againſt the Statute he was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily puniſhed and commited, for it ſhould be a vain Law if it did not provide puniſhment for them that offend againſt that; and <hi>Bracton</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nihil eſt habere Leges, ſi non ſit unus qui poteſt Leges tueri,</hi> and for this here are four grave and diſcreet men to deſend and maintain the Law, and to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh all Offenders againſt that, according to the Statute, by Impriſonment of their Bodies and other reaſonable waies, and the ſaid four men have the ſearch as well of thoſe men, as of other Mediciners, and the Statute of 1. <hi>Marie</hi> provides that the Keepers of Priſons, ſhall receive all which are committed by the ſaid four grave and learned men, and though there be great care com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to them by the ſaid Statute, and the ſaid Letters Patents, yet there is a greater truſt repo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in them then this, for we commit to them our lives, when we receive phyſick of them, and that not without cauſe, for they are men of Gravity, Learning, and Diſcretion; and for that they have power to make Lawes, which is the Office of the Parliament, for thoſe which are ſo learned may be truſted with any thing; and for the better making of theſe, they have power to aſſemble all the Commons of their Corporation, and the King al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes of that by his Letters Patents, for it is made by a Congregation of wiſe, learned, and diſcreet men, and the Statute of 1. <hi>Marie</hi> inflicts puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:54229:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
upon Contempts, and not for any other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, and they held a Court, and ſo may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit as every other Court may for a contempt of common right, without Act of Parliament, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, or other legal form of proceeding upon that, as it appears by 7. <hi>H.</hi> 6. for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt committed in a Leet, the Steward commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Offender to Priſon; and it was abſurd to conceive that the Statute will allow of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment without cauſe, and it is a marvelous thing that when good Lawes ſhall be made for our health and wealth alſo, yet we will ſo pinch upon them, that we will not be tried by men of experience, practiſe, and Learning, but by the Univerſity, where a man may have his Degree by grace without merit, and ſo for theſe reaſons he concluded that this Action is not maintaina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Coke</hi> chief ſaid, that the Cauſe which was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded<note place="margin">Coke.</note> for, that the Plaintiff was committed, was for that, that he had exerciſed Phyſick within the City of <hi>London</hi> by the ſpace of a Moneth, and did not very fitly anſwer, for which it was ordained by the Cenſors that he ſhould pay a hundred ſhillings, and that he ſhould forbear his practiſe, and that he did not forbear, and then being warned of that, and upon that being ſummoned to appear, did not appear, and for that it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that he ſhould be arreſted, and that after he was ſummoned again; and then he appeared, and denied to pay the hundred ſhillings, and he ſaid that he would practiſe, for he was a Doctor
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:54229:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and upon that it was ordained that he should be committed, till he ſhould be delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the Doctors of the Colledge, and upon this was the Demurrer joyned, and in pleading the Plaintiff ſaid, that he was a Doctor of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy and Phyſick, upon which the Lord took oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to remember a ſaying of <hi>Galen,</hi> that is, <hi>ubi Philoſophia deſinit, ibi medicina incipit,</hi> and he ſaid the only queſtion of this caſe depends not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the payment of the ſaid hundred ſhillings, but upon the words of the Letters Patents of the King, and the ſaid two Statutes, the words of which are <hi>Conceſsimus eidem praeſidenti,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Quod nemo in dicta Civitate, aut per ſeptem milliaria in circuitu ejuſdem exerceat dictam facultatem, niſi ad hoc per dictum praeſidentem &amp; communitatem ſeu ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſores, eorum qui pro tempore fuerint, admiſſus ſit, per ejuſdem praeſidentis &amp; Collegii literas ſigillo ſuo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni ſigillatas ſub paena centum ſolidorum pro quolibet menſe quo non admiſſus eandem facultatem exercuit, dimidium inde nobis, &amp; haeredibus noſtris, &amp; dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium dicto praeſidenti &amp; Collegio applicandum, &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terea volumus &amp; concedimus pro nobis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Quod per praeſidentem &amp; Collegium communitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> pro tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore exiſtent. &amp; eorum ſucceſſores in perpetuum, quatuor ſingulis annis per ipſos eligantur, qui habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ſuperviſum, ſcrutinium, &amp; correctionem &amp; gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernationem omnium &amp; ſingulorum dictae Civitatis medicorum utentium facultate, medicinae in eadem Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitate, ac aliorum medicorum, forinſecorum quorum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque facultatem illam medicinae, aliquo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> modo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentantium &amp; utenſium infra eandem civitatem &amp;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:54229:50"/>
ſuburbia ejuſdem vel ſeptem milliaria in circuitu ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Civitatis ac punitionem eorundem pro delectis ſuis, in non bene exequendo, faciendo &amp; utendo illa, nec non ſuperviſum &amp; ſcrutinium hujuſmodi medicorum &amp; eorum receptionum, per praedictos medicos ſive ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem eorum hujuſmodi legeis noſtris pro eorum Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatibus curandis &amp; ſanandis, dandis imponendis &amp; utendis quoties &amp; quando opus fuerit, procommodo &amp; utilitate eorundem legiorum noſtrorum; Ita quod punitio hujuſmodi medicorum utentium dicta facultate medicinae ſic in praemiſsis delinquentium, per Fines, Amerciamenta, Impriſonamenta corporum ſuorum &amp; per alias vias rationabiles &amp; Congruas exequantur,</hi> as it appears in <hi>Raſtal Phyſicians</hi> 8018, 392. So that there are two diſtinct Clauſes.</p>
            <p>The firſt, if any exerciſe the ſaid Faculty by the ſpace of a Moneth without admiſſion by the Preſident, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall forfeit a hundred ſhillings for every Moneth be that good or ill, it is not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial, the time is here only material, for if he exerciſe that for ſuch a time, he ſhall forfeit as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>The ſecond clauſe is, that the Preſident, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhall have <hi>Scrutinium Medicorum,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>&amp; punitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eorum pro delictis ſuis in non bene faciendo, utendo &amp; exequendo,</hi> &amp;c. And for that the Preſident and the Colledge may commit any delinquent to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: And this he concluded upon the words of the Statute, and he agreed with <hi>Walmeſley,</hi> that the King hath had extraordinary care of the health of the Subjects. <hi>Et Rex cenſetur habere omnes Artes inſcrinio pectoris,</hi> and he hath here purſued the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:54229:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Courſe of the beſt Phyſicians, that is, <hi>Removens &amp; promovens, removens Improbos illos, qui nulli bonae conſcientiae fiducia profitebantur &amp; audaces, &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movens ad ſanitatem:</hi> And for that the Phyſician ought to be profound, grave, diſcreet, grounded in learning, and ſoundly ſtudied, and from him cometh the medicine, which is <hi>removens &amp; promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is an old rule, that a man ought to take care, that he do not commit his Soul to a young Divine, his Body to a young Phyſician, and his Goods or other Eſtate to a young Lawyer, for <hi>in Juvene Theologo eſt Conſcientiae detrimentum; in Juvene Legiſlatore burſi detrimentum, &amp; in Juvene Medico Coemeterii incrementum,</hi> for in theſe cannot be the privity, diſcretion, and profound learning which is in the aged: And he denied that the Colledge of Phyſicians is to be compared to the Univerſity, for it is ſubordinate to that, <hi>Cantabrigia eſt Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia noſtra nobiliſsima totius Regni oculus, &amp; ſol ubi humanitas &amp; doctrina ſimul fluunt:</hi> But he ſaid, when he names <hi>Cambridge</hi> he doth not exclude <hi>Oxford,</hi> but placeth them in equal Rank: But he would alwaies name <hi>Cambridge</hi> firſt, for that was his Mother: And he ſaith that there is not any time, <hi>Pro non bene faciendo, utendo &amp; exequendo,</hi> for this <hi>non ſuſcipit Majus &amp; Minus,</hi> for ſo a man may grievouſly offend in one day, and for that in ſuch a caſe, his puniſhment ſhall be by Fines, Amerce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Impriſonments of their Bodies, and other waies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if practiſe well, though it be not an offence againſt the <hi>Letters Patents</hi> and the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:54229:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Statutes</hi> yet the puniſhment ſhall be but pecuniary, and ſhall not be Impriſoned, for if he offend the Body of a man, it is reaſon that his Body ſhall be puniſhed, for <hi>Eodem modo quo quis delinquit, eodem punietur,</hi> but if a grave and learned Doctor or other, come and practiſe well in <hi>London</hi> by the ſpace of three weeks and then departs, he is not puniſhable by the ſaid Colledge, though that be without admiſſion, for peradventure ſuch a one is better acquainted with the nature and diſpoſition of my Body, and for that more fit to cure any Malady in that then another which is admitted by the Colledge, and he ſaid that it was abſurd to puniſh ſuch a one, for he may practiſe in ſuch manner in deſpite of the Colledge, for all the Lords and Nobles of the Realm, which have their private Phyſicians, which have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with their Bodies, repair to this City, and to exclude thoſe of uſing their advice, were a hard and abſurd expoſition, for the old verſe is,</p>
            <q>Corporis auxilium medico committe ſodali:</q>
            <p>And alſo he ſaid that the ſaid Preſident and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge cannot commit any Phyſician, which exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſeth the ſaid faculty without admiſſion, for the ſpace of a Moneth, nor bring their Action before themſelves, nor levy that by any other way or means: but ought to have their Action or exhibit an Information upon the Statute, as it appears by the Book of Entries, for they ought to purſue their power which is given to them by the Statute, for otherwiſe the penalty being given, the one Moity to them, and the other to the King, they
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:54229:51"/>
ſhall be Judges <hi>in Propria cauſa,</hi> and ſhall be Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moners, Sheriffs, Judges, and Parties alſo, which is abſurd; for if the King grant to one by his <hi>Letters Patents</hi> under the Great Seal, that he may hold Plea, although he be party and if the King doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point another Judge, then the Grantee which is party, the Grant is void, though that it be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by Parliament, as it appears by 8. <hi>H.</hi> 6. 44. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. The Abbot of <hi>Readings</hi> Caſe, for it is ſaid by <hi>Herle</hi> in 8. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. 30. <hi>Tregores</hi> Caſe, that if any Statutes, are made againſt Law and Right, and ſo are theſe, which makes any man Judge in his own cauſe, and ſo in 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>Fitz. Annuity</hi> 41. that the Statute of <hi>Carlile</hi> will that the order of <hi>Ciſtertians</hi> and <hi>Auguſtines,</hi> which have Covent and Common Seal, that the Common Seal ſhall be in keeping of the <hi>Prior,</hi> which is under the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot, and four others which are the moſt Sages of the houſe, and that any Deed ſealed with the Common Seal which is not ſo in keeping ſhall be void, and the opinion of the Court that this is a void <hi>Statute,</hi> for it is imperttinent to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, being the Seal in their keeping, the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot cannot Seal any thing with it, and when that it is in the hands of the Abbot, it is out of their keeping, <hi>ipſofacto:</hi> And if the Statute ſhall be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, every common Seal ſhall be defeated by one ſimple ſurmiſe, which cannot be tried, and for that the Statute was adjudged void, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant: And ſo the Statute of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> which gives <hi>Ceſſavit</hi> after Ceſſer by two years to be brought by the Leſſor himſelf, was a good and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:54229:52"/>
equitable Statute: But the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 2. chap. 3. which gives <hi>Ceſſavit</hi> to the Heir for Ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer in time of his Anceſter, and that, that was judged an unreaſonable Statute in 33. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. for that, that the Heir cannot have the arrearages due in the time of his Father, according to the Statute of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> and for that it ſhall be void: And alſo the Phyſicians of the Colledge, could not puniſh any by Fine and alſo by Impriſonment, for no man ought to be twice puniſhed for one offence, and the Statute of 1. <hi>Mariae</hi> doth not give any power to them to commit for any offence w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was no offence within the firſt Statutes, &amp; for that he ought not to be committed by the ſaid Statute of 1. <hi>Mariae:</hi> But admitting that they may commit, yet they have miſtaken it, for they demand the whole hundred ſhillings, and one half of that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the King: And alſo they ought to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him forthwith, as well as Auditors which have Authority by Parliament, to commit him which is found in arrearages: But if he do not commit him forthwith, they cannot commit him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, as it appears by 27. <hi>H.</hi> 6. 9. So two Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the Peace may view a force and make a Record of that, and commit the offenders to Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but this ought to be in <hi>Flagranti Oriente:</hi> and if he do not commit thoſe immediately upon the view, he cannot commit them afterwards, and the Phyſicians have no Court, but if they have, yet they ought to make a Record of their commitment, for ſo was every Court of Juſtice: But they have not made any Record of that: And
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:54229:52"/>
Auditors and Juſtices of Peace, ought to make Records, as it appears by the Book of Entries: So that admitting that they may commit, yet they ought to do it forthwith, but in this caſe they cannot commit till the party ſhall be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, for this is againſt Law and Juſtice; and no Subject may do it, but till he be delivered by due courſe of Law, for the commitment is not abſolute, but the cauſe of that is traverſable, and for that ought to juſtifie for ſpecial cauſe; for if the Biſhop returns that he refuſes a Clerk, for that he is <hi>Schiſmaticus Inveteratus,</hi> this is not good, but they ought to return the particular matter: So that the Court may adjudge of that: Though it be a matter of Divinity and out of their Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, yet they by conference may be informed of it, and ſo of Phyſick: And they cannot make any new Lawes, but ſuch only which are for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter government of the old; and alſo he ſaid plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it appears by the Statute of 1. <hi>Mariae:</hi> That the former Statutes ſhall not be taken by equity, for by theſe the Preſident and Commons have power to commit a Delinquent to Priſon, and this ſhall be intended, if they ſhall be taken by equity, that every Goaler ought to receive him which is ſo committed: But when it is provided by 1. <hi>Mariae,</hi> ſpecially that every Goa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler ſhall receive ſuch offenders: That by this ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the former Statute ſhall not be taken by equity: And ſo he concluded, that Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall be entred for the Plaintiff, which was done accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:54229:53"/>
               <hi>Coke</hi> in the concluſion of his argument ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved theſe 7. things for the better direction of the Preſident and Comminalty of the ſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for the time to come. 1. That none may be puniſhed for practiſe of Phyſick in <hi>London</hi> but by the forfeiture of 5 <hi>l.</hi> a Month, which is to be recovered by Law. 2. If any one pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe Phyſick there leſs then a Moneth, that he ſhall forfeit nothing. 3. If any perſon prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited by the <hi>Statute offend in non bene exequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, &amp;c.</hi> they may puniſh him according to the Statute within the Month. 4. Thoſe whom they may commit to priſon by the Statute ought to be committed preſently. 5. The fines which they impoſe according to the Statute belong to the King. 6. They may not impoſe a fine or impriſonment without Record thereof. 7. The cauſe for which they impoſe fine or impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment muſt be certain.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="trial_proceedings">
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:54229:53"/>
            <head>The Proceedings of the Colledge againſt <hi>Chriſtopher Barton</hi> Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</head>
            <p>UPon the complaint of divers perſons againſt the ſaid <hi>Barton</hi> for practiſing of Phyſick, the ſaid <hi>Barton</hi> was ſent for by a Meſſenger of his Majeſties Chamber, who appearing before the Preſident and Cenſors the 6. of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1639. and many things being laid to his charge, yet for ſome reaſons he was bound with ſureties to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear again before them the 4. of <hi>October</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; And he then alſo appearing was for the Cauſes in the Cenſors Warrant expreſſed, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bartons</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment.</note> to the Priſon of <hi>Woodſtreet-Compter London,</hi> where he remained till the 19. of <hi>October</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, never having by all that time petitioned the Colledge for his liberty; and then by vertue of a Writ of <hi>hab. Corpus,</hi> which he had ſued forth of the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> he was carried with his Cauſe to the <hi>Kings-Bench</hi> Bar at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi> The Copy of which Warrant and the return thereof here immediately enſueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nos Johannes Warner &amp; Thomas<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Adams vic. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>London ſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Sheriffs. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</note> 
               <hi>London, Sereniſsimo Dno Regi in brevi huis ſchedul. annex. noiat ad diem &amp; locum in eodem bri. content.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:54229:54"/>
certificamus, quod ante adventum nob. predct. bris ſcilt. duodecimo die Sept. Anno Regni dci. Dni Regis nunc Angl. &amp;c. decimo quinto Chriſtophorus Barton in dco. bri noiat. comiſſus fuit priſone Dni Regis ſcilt. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putator. ſituat. in Woodſtreet London predct. &amp; in eadem priſona ſub Cuſtodia Iſaaci Pennington &amp; Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannis Wollaſton tunc vic. Civit. predct. &amp; in eorum exit ab officio ſuo, ſub cuſtodia nr. detent. virtute cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſdam Warranti Otwelli Meverell, Laurentii Wright, Edmundi Smith, &amp; Willmi Goddard in Medicinis Dctor. et Cenſor. Collegii Medicor. in London. ſub ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gillo Coi. Collegii Medicor. London pred. Cuſtod. predct. computorii London predct. vel ejus deputat. direct. cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus quidem Warranti tenor ſequitur in haec verba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ſſ.</hi> We <hi>Otwell Meverell, Lawrence Wright, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi>
               <note place="margin">Colledge Warrant.</note> 
               <hi>Smith,</hi> and <hi>William Goddard,</hi> Doctors in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick and Cenſors of the Colledge of Phyſicians in <hi>London</hi> being choſen by the Preſident and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Phyſicians aforeſaid to govern and puniſh for this preſent year all Offendors in the Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Phyſick within the City of <hi>London</hi> and the Suburbs thereof, and ſeven miles compaſs of the ſaid City, according to the authority in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half to us duly given by certain Letters Patents under the Great Seal of <hi>England</hi> made and granted to the ſaid Colledge and Comminalty by the late King of famous memory King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> bearing date the 23. day of <hi>September</hi> in the tenth year of his reign; and one Act of Parliament made in the 14. year of the reign of the ſaid late King <hi>Henry</hi> the 8<hi rend="sup">th</hi> concerning Phyſicians, where by the Letters Patents aforeſaid and every thing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:54229:54"/>
therein are granted and confirmed. And by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the ſaid Act of Parliament and Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents aforeſaid, and one other Act of Parliament made in the firſt year of the reign of our late So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lady Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> intituled, <hi>An Act touching the Corporation of Phyſicians in London,</hi> Did cauſe to be brought before us the ſixth day of this inſtant <hi>September,</hi> at our Colledge-houſe in <hi>Pater noſter-Row</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> one <hi>Chriſtopher Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and we have examined the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher Barton,</hi> and upon his examination and other due proofs, we have found that the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher Barton</hi> hath unskilfully practiſed the Art of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick within the City of <hi>London</hi> and Precinct afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, upon the bodies of <hi>Richard Ballady</hi> of <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary</hi> Pariſh <hi>London, Michael Knight</hi> of <hi>S. Botolphs</hi> Pariſh <hi>Aldgate London,</hi> and the Childe of one <hi>Jane Bigge,</hi> and ſome others, in the moneth of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary</hi> in the year 1638. contrary to the Lawes in that behalf made and provided; whereupon we have impoſed upon the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> a Fine of 20 <hi>l.</hi> for his evil practiſe in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick aforeſaid; And we have alſo for the ſame cauſe ſent you the Body of the ſaid <hi>Chriſtopher Barton,</hi> willing and requiring you in the Kings Majeſties name to receive and keep him in ſafe cuſtody as priſoner, there to remain at his own coſts and charges without bay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or mainprize un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he ſhall be diſcharged of his ſaid impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Preſident of the ſaid Colledge, and by ſuch perſons as by the ſaid Colledge ſhall be there unto authoriſed according to the Statute in
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:54229:55"/>
that behalf made, and this our Warrant ſhall be your diſcharge. Given at the ſaid Colledge the eleventh day of <hi>September</hi> in the fifteenth year of the Reign of our Sovereign Lord King <hi>Charles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Otwell Meverell, Edm. Smith, Lawr. Wright, William Goddard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Keeper of <hi>Woodſtreet Compter London,</hi> or his Deputy.</p>
            <p>To Mr. <hi>John Penyall</hi> one of the Meſſengers of his Majeſties Chamber in Ordinary to execute this Warrant:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Et haec eſt cauſa accepcois &amp; detenconis prefati Chriſtophori Barton in priſona predct. ſub cuſtodia nra corpus Cujus quidem Chriſtophori coram prefat. Dno Rege apud Weſtm. parat. habemus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being at the Bar the ſaid 19. of <hi>October,</hi> for that the Lord chief Juſtice Sir <hi>John Bramſton</hi> was not preſent, the other Judges preſent would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of Bayl, which the ſaid <hi>Barton</hi> tendred, but ſuſpended the matter untill Tueſday the 22. of <hi>October</hi> following, <hi>Barton</hi> for that time was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned back; and coming to the Bar again on the ſaid Tueſday with his Councel and Bayl, the Lord <hi>Bramſton</hi> being then preſent, my Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the return of the warrant, which was neglected by the Clerks of the Court, and left in the Crown Office in the Temple, ſo my Lord would not proceed, but reſpited the cauſe untill Thurſday the 24. of <hi>October</hi> following, when all parties appearing with Councel on both ſides, the Warrant and Return was read, and the Cauſe debated, and there the Court plainly declared,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:54229:55"/>
that he ſhould not be bayled, it being againſt the Law, and the Letter of the Warrant grounded upon the Statutes. Then it was deſired by <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> Councel, that he might go over to the <hi>Kings-Bench,</hi> which alſo was denied, becauſe he was committed originally to the <hi>Compter</hi> in <hi>Woodſtreet,</hi> as appeared by the Warrant, and ſo <hi>Barton</hi> was remanded by the Court to the ſaid Compter, and willed if he would have Liberty to ſubmit to the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Barton</hi> remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> Colledge and make his peace there: <hi>Barton</hi> being in Cuſtody of the Serjeant that carried him up to the Bar e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ibited his humble Petition to the Preſident and Cenſors the 25. of <hi>October</hi> ſigned with his own hand for abatement of part of his Fine and for his enlargement, ſubmitting in all things unto them; whereupon the Preſident and Dr. <hi>Meverell</hi> one of the Cenſors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were contented to abate the half of his Fine of 20 <hi>l.</hi> and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of 10 <hi>l.</hi> the one half to be paid in hand (which was paid) and the other half at our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy day next. And ſo upon the 29. of <hi>October</hi> ſigned his diſcharge and ſet him at liberty, he being put again before his enlargement into the ſaid priſon.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="trial_proceedings">
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:54229:56"/>
            <head>Termino <hi>Trinitatis,</hi> anno octavo <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roli</hi> Regis, in Banco Regis.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Crokes Reports,</hi> the Firſt Part.</head>
            <head type="sub">Butler <hi>verſus</hi> the Preſident of the Colledge of Phyſicians, <hi>Paſc. 7. Car. rot. 519.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>ERror of a Judgment upon a Demurrer in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Bench.</hi> The firſt Error aſſigned was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Record was, <hi>Ad reſpondendum Domino Regi &amp; Praeſidenti Collegii &amp;c. Qui tam pro Domino Rege, quam pro ſeipſo ſequitur quod reddat eis ſexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta libras, unde idem Praeſidens qui tam &amp;c. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit, &amp;c.</hi> Whereas the Action ought to have been brought by the Preſident only, <hi>qui tam, &amp;c.</hi> and not by the King and Preſident, <hi>&amp;c. ſed non allocatur:</hi> For being an Original Writ, the Writ is moſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſo, and ſometimes the other way: And they conceived it good both waies. But Informations are alwaies, that the party <hi>qui tam</hi> for the King, <hi>quam pro ſeipſo ſequitur, &amp;c. Vide Plowd. 77. new Book of Entries, 160. old Book of Entries,</hi> 143. 373. The ſecond Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror was, that the Replication was a departure from the Count; For the Count ſets forth, That King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, <hi>anno decimo Regni ſui incorporavit</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:54229:56"/>
(&amp; per le Statut <hi>of decimo quarto Henrici octavi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmavit) the Colledge of Phyſicians by the name of the Preſident, &amp;c. that no man ſhould practiſe Phyſick in</hi> London, <hi>or within ſeven miles, without Licence under the Seal of the Colledge, upon penalty of 5 l. for every moneth that he ſo practiſed, the one moity unto the King, and the other unto the Preſident of the Colledge, to the uſe of the ſaid Colledge,</hi> And for that the Deſendant not being allowed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> had pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed Phyſick for twelve months in <hi>London,</hi> The ſaid Action was brought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Defendant pleads the Statute of <hi>triceſimo quarto Henrici octavi cap. 8. That every one who hath Science and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the nature of Herbs, Roots and Waters, or of the operation of the ſame by ſpeculation or practiſe, may miniſter or apply in and to any outward Sore, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, Wound, Apoſthumations, outward Swelling or Diſeaſe; any Herb, Oyntments, Baths, Pultes, or Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſters, according to their cunning experience and knowledge,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>or Drink for the Stone and Strangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in any part of the Realm, without ſuit, vexation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>any Act or Statute to the contrary notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi> And that he having skill in the nature of Herbs, Roots, and Waters, by ſpeculation and practiſe, applied to perſons requiring his skill, Herbs, Ointments, Baths, Drinks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to their Sores, Uncomes, Wounds, and for the Stone and Strangury, or Agues, and to all other Diſeaſes in the ſaid Statute mentioned, <hi>prout ei benelicuit. Et quoad aliquam aliam practiſationem ſeu facultatem medicinae aliter vel alio modo quod non eſt culpabilis. Et de hoc ponit,</hi> &amp;c. And makes his averment, <hi>Et
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:54229:57"/>
hoc paratus eſt verificare,</hi> The Plaintiff replies, and ſhews the Statute of <hi>primo Mariae capite nono,</hi> which confirms the Charter of <hi>decino Henrici octavi,</hi> and the Statute of <hi>decimo quarto Henrici octavi,</hi> and appoints that it ſhall be in force, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any Statute or Ordinance to the contrary. And upon this it was demurred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a departure; for it intitles him by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Act, <hi>viz.</hi> the Statute of <hi>primo Mariae,</hi> which is not mentioned in the Count: and therefore 'twas aſſigned for Error. But all the Court here conceived, That it is no departure; Becauſe it fortifies the Count, and is as to revive the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>decimo quarto Henrici octavi,</hi> if it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed in this particular by the Statute of <hi>triceſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo quarto Henrici octavi:</hi> And for that the Caſe of <hi>Woodhead</hi> was ſhewn to the Court, <hi>Mich. 42. &amp; 43. Eliz. rot.</hi> 397. where the Preſident of the Colledge of <hi>All-Souls,</hi> bringing an Action upon the Caſe for taking Toll in, and ſhews a Charter of <hi>viceſimo ſexto Henrici ſexti</hi> to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged of Toll, the Defendant pleaded the Act of Reſumption of Liberties granted by <hi>Henry the ſixth,</hi> made, and ſo the Liberty gone. The Plaintiff pleaded a Reviver of them by the Statute of <hi>quarto Henrici ſeptimi:</hi> And it was held to be no departure, but as it were a confeſſion and avoiding. The third and principal Error aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned was, if the Statute of <hi>triceſimo quarto Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rici octavi,</hi> be not repealed by the Statute of <hi>primo Mariae,</hi> and if not, Whether the Defendant hath made a ſufficient Juſification? And <hi>quoad</hi> that,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:54229:57"/>
Whether the ſaid Statute be repealed, the Court was not reſolved. But <hi>Richardſon,</hi> Chief Juſtice, conceived it was repealed by <hi>primo Mariae,</hi> by the general words, <hi>any Act or Statute to the contrary, of the Act of decimo quarto Henrici octavi notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi> But I conceived, that the Act of <hi>triceſimo quarto Henrici octavi,</hi> not mentioning the Statute of <hi>decimo quarto Henrici octavi,</hi> was for Phyſicians: but the part of the Act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of <hi>triceſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quar. Henrici octavi,</hi> was concerning Chirurgeons, and their applying outward Medicines to outward Sores and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes: And Drinks only for the Stone, Strangul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and Ague; That Statute was never intended to be taken away by the Act of <hi>primo Mariae.</hi> But to this point <hi>Jones</hi> and <hi>Woitlock,</hi> would not deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Opinions, But admitting the Statute of <hi>triceſimo quarto Henrici octavi,</hi> be in force, yet they all reſolved, the Defendants Plea was naught, and not warranted by the Statute; for he pleads, That he applied and miniſtred Medicines, Plaiſters, Drinks, <hi>ulceribus, Morbis &amp; Maladiis, Calculo, Strangurio, Febribus, &amp; aliis in Statuto mentionatis;</hi> ſo he leaves out the principal word in the Statute (<hi>Externis.</hi>) And doth not refer and ſhew, That he miniſtred potions for the Stone, Strangullion or Ague, as the Statute appoints to theſe three Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes only, and to no other. And by his Plea his Potions may be miniſtred to any other ſickneſs; wherefore they all held his Plea was nought for this cauſe, and that Judgment was well given againſt him; Whereupon Judgment was affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="trial_proceedings">
            <pb n="110" facs="tcp:54229:58"/>
            <head>Termino Trinitatis anno quarto <hi>Jacobi</hi> Regis in Banco Regis.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Crokes Reports</hi> the Second Part.</head>
            <head type="sub">Doctor Langhton <hi>verſus</hi> Gardener.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>DEbt</hi> upon the Statute 14. <hi>H. 8. cap.</hi> 5. by the<note place="margin">(4)</note> Plaintiff, as Preſident of the Colledge of Phyſicians in <hi>London,</hi> and of the Corporation of Phyſicians there: For that the Defendant uſed the Art of Phyſick in <hi>London,</hi> without Licence from the Colledge there, againſt the Statute, and their Charter: For which he demanded 5 <hi>l.</hi> for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moneth, being the penalty given by the Statute: The Defendant pleaded the Statute of 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. which enables every one to practiſe Phyſick or Chirurgery, being skilful therein, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any Act to the contrary. The Plaintiff replies, and ſhewes the Statute <hi>primo Mar. cap.</hi> 9. which confirms their Charter, and every Article thereof to ſtand in force; <hi>Any Act, Statute, Law, or Cuſtome to the contrary notwithſtanding.</hi> Hereupon the Defendant demurred; Firſt, becauſe this general clauſe in this Law doth not reſtrain the Statute of 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. Secondly, that this pleading is a departure: For it ought to have been ſhewn before. <hi>Stephens</hi> argued for the Plaintiff. Firſt,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:54229:58"/>
That the Act of 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. is repealed by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of of <hi>Prim. Mar. Quoad</hi> the Colledge of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians in <hi>London,</hi> as fully as if it had been by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs words recited and repealed: For when it confirms the Charter of 14. <hi>H.</hi> 8. and appoints, that it, and every part thereof ſhall ſtand, and be available: The Statute of 34. <hi>H.</hi> 8. cannot ſtand with it, <hi>Quia leges poſteriores leges priores con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarias abrogant, 4. Ed. 4. Porters</hi> Caſe <hi>Co. 1. fol,</hi> 25. Secondly, That it is not any departure: Becauſe there is not any new matter; but matter pleaded in reviving of the former, or fortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof: And a Record was ſhewn, <hi>Mich. 10. &amp; 11. Eliz.</hi> betwixt <hi>Bomelins &amp;</hi> ..... where the Record was in the ſame manner as this Record is; and there the Plaintiff had Judgement: Wherefore, &amp;c. And there being none on the Defendants part to argue, The Court upon hearing of the Record, gave rule, that Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be entred for the Plaintiff, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="trial_proceedings">
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:54229:59"/>
            <head>Termino Paſchae anno quinto <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi</hi> Regis in Banco Regis.</head>
            <head type="sub">Doctor Atkins <hi>verſus</hi> Gardener.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Scir. fac.</hi> Upon a Judgment in Debt upon the<note place="margin">(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>)</note> Statute 14. <hi>H.</hi> 8. by Doctor <hi>Langhton</hi> Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the Colledge of Phyſicians in <hi>London,</hi> who died before execution had; and thereupon the ſucceſſor brought a <hi>Scir. fac.</hi> to have execution; It was thereupon demurred, becauſe the <hi>Scir. fac.</hi> ought to be brought by the Executor or Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrator of him who recovered, and not by the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor. But upon hearing of the Record, without argument, the Court held, that the ſucceſſor might well maintain the Action; For the Suit is given to the Colledge by a private Statute: And the Suite is to be brought by the Preſident for the time being; And he having recovered in right of the Corporation, the Law ſhall transfer that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the ſucceſſor of him who recovered, and not to his Executors: The Action being brought, for that he practiſed Phyſick in <hi>London</hi> without Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the Colledge of Phyſicians, againſt the Statute of 14. <hi>H.</hi> 8. Wherefore it was adjudged for the Plaintiff.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:54229:59"/>
            <head>Coram Judice D. Jo. Popham.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>APrilis die 8. Anno Dom. 1602. Compauerunt Rogerus Jinkins &amp; Simon Read in Aedibus Primarii Angliae Juſtitiarii D. Johannis Popham E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitis Aurati: coram ipſo Judice quiritantes, de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juria illis illata per Praeſidentem &amp; Cenſores Collegii Medicorum, quorum authoritate, ob illegitimam Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinae praxin, in Carcerem conjecti ſunt, ibidemque jam per aliquot ſeptimanas detenti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adfuerunt ex parte Collegii per Praeſidentem miſsi Cenſores tres, D. Johannes Nowell. Edwardus Lyſter &amp; Johannes Argent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Incarceratorum cauſam agebat quidem Magiſter Harris Juriſperitus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judex prius ſedulò perlectis iis Regni ſtatutis, quae ad medicinam faciunt: Jinkins urgebat, ut rationem redderet cur auſus ſit Medicinam exercere, licenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non priùs impetratâ à Collegio Medicorum? Is Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mùm Praxin denegavit, Poſtea, urgente magis Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, haeſitanter, &amp; ambigue reſpondit. Tandem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuens ne Jurejurando premeretur; faſſus eſt ſe ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quando Practicaſſe, idque, ut putabat, non illicitè, Quid, inquit Judex: Obtinuiſtine unquam Collegii Commune Sigillum? Non, inquit ille; Sed quia Chirurgus ſum: &amp; in opere Chirurgico ſaepe neceſſarius eſt internorum Medicamentorum uſus. Reſpondit Judex; re ita ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente, advocandum eſſe Medicum, atque nullo modo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chirurgo medicum agere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:54229:60"/>
               <hi>Objecit Juriſperitus Praeſidentis, &amp; Cenſorum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem non eam eſſe, quâ poſsint quenquam in Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerem conjicere, ideoque à Collegio, ad alios Judices cauſam omnem eſſe promovendam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hunc reprehendit Judex, aſſerebatque validam eſſe, maximéque legitimam, hac ex parte Collegii authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Multùm tandem conqueſtus eſt Jinkins, quòd ob ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram praxin, eamque ex aliorum Praeſcripto, tam gravis ei Mulcta ſit inflicta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tum Libro Annalium oſtenſo; Compertum eſt eum jam antea ſexties Publicè accuſatum eſſe, &amp; aliquoties etiam leves mulctas ſubiiſſe. Unde Judici aequiſsimum viſum eſt, ut, cum clementer tractatus, incorrigibilem tamen ſe praebuiſſet, graviori tandem mulcta premere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Et eo quòd aliorum Medicorum Praeſcriptis ad ſuam Praxin ſaepius ſit abuſus, Conſultiſsimum putavit</hi>
               <note place="margin">Medicor. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptis Dies Menſis, cum patientis No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine adſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendus.</note> 
               <hi>Judex, ut omnes Medici, Praeſcriptis ſuis omnibus, &amp; diem menſis, &amp; Patientis nomen inſcribant unde fraus iis abutentium, faciliùs deprehendi poſsit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judex, Re auditâ; Collegiique Cenſurâ optimè ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probatâ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jinkins red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur Carceri.</note> 
               <hi>Jinkins denuò Carceri reddendum cenſuit, donec Praeſidenti &amp; Cenſoribus ſatisfactum ſit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cumque quorundam Amicorum inſtantiâ rogatus eſt Judex, ut fide-juſſoribus admiſsis, immunitatem illi concederet à Carcere: Non eſt, inquit Judex, penes me, ut hoc faciam; Legibus enim Regni, illis ſolum da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut iſtud concedant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quidam qui aſtabat, objecit; Statuto quodam regni cautum eſſe, ne quis liber, Civis Londinenſis, per fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinſecum aliquem incarceretur. Perlectis ſtatuti verbis, nulloque modo ſenſum hunc ferentibus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:54229:60"/>
               <hi>Hujuſmodi, inquit Judex, interpretationibus, meam etiam poſsitis infringere authoritatem.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Theſe words the Lord Chief Juſtice ſaid in hearing this Cauſe.</head>
               <item>1. There is no ſufficient Licence without the Colledge Seal.</item>
               <item>2. No Chirurgeon, as a Chirurgeon, may practiſe Phyſick, no, not for any diſeaſe, though it be the great Pox.</item>
               <item>3. That the authority of the Colledge is ſtrong and ſufficient to commit to priſon.</item>
               <item>4. That the Cenſure of the Colledge, riſing from leſſer mulcts to greater, was equal and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable.</item>
               <item>5. That no man though never ſo learned a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician or Doctor may practiſe in <hi>London,</hi> or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſeven miles, without the Colledge Licence.</item>
            </list>
            <div type="excerpt">
               <head>Annal. l. 1. pag. 155, 156.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Read</hi> conqueſtus eſt Collegium contra regni ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ultra 20 l. paenam erogaſſe, verbis ſtatuti per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſis pronuntiavit Judex Collegio licere quam velint mulctam infligere, cuſtodem tamen carceris non eſſe aſtrictum ut eum detineat ſi ſit ultra 20 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Read</hi> praxin ſuam aſſeruit quod ſtatuto regni cuivis conceſſum eſt per herbas &amp;c. aliquos ſaltem morbos cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare: at reſpondit Judex nonlicere, quoniam non ad. miſſus erat per Collegium.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="resolutions">
            <pb n="116" facs="tcp:54229:61"/>
            <head>Reſolutions of Queſtions concerning the Colledge, by the Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor and Judges.</head>
            <p>THe King having directed his Letters to the Right Honourable <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Elleſmere</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> Sir <hi>John Popham</hi> Lord chief Juſtice and one of his privy Councel, They the ſaid Lord Chancellor and Lord chief Juſtice, by vertue of the ſame Letters called unto them Sir <hi>Thomas Fleminge</hi> then Lord chief Baron, Sir <hi>Thomas Walmeſley</hi> &amp; Sir <hi>Peter Warburton</hi> Knights, Juſtices of the Court of Common-Pleas, and Sir <hi>David Williams,</hi> and Sir <hi>Lawrence Tanfield,</hi> Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the <hi>Kings-Bench;</hi> and after due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had, both of the Charter of King <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and ſeveral Acts of Parliament thereof made in the 14. year of the ſame King, and the other in the firſt year of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> did on the firſt of <hi>May</hi> 1607. at the houſe of the ſaid Lord Chancellor, called <hi>York-houſe,</hi> reſolve the ſeveral Queſtions hereafter mentioned.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> Whether Graduates of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge</hi> may practiſe in <hi>London</hi> or ſeven miles compaſs of the ſame without Licence under the ſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Seal; by vertue of the clauſe in the end of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:54229:61"/>
the Statute of 14. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and whether that clauſe hath not relation to the Statute of 3. <hi>H.</hi> 8. only, or how far it doth extend?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>1</label> All reſolved that no Graduate that is not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and licenſed by the Preſident and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Phyſicians under their common Seal, could practiſe in <hi>London</hi> or within ſeven miles compaſs of the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> Whether by Graduates, Graduates in Phyſick only are to be underſtood?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>2</label> They reſolved, that the Exception in the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of 14. <hi>H.</hi> 8. ca. 11. of Graduates in the two Univerſities is to be underſtood only of Graduates of Phyſick, and of no others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And all reſolved, that by that Exception thoſe Graduates may pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe in all other places of <hi>England</hi> out of <hi>London,</hi> and ſeven miles of the ſame, without examination, but not in <hi>London,</hi> nor within the ſaid circuit of ſeven miles.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> If Graduates not admitted to practiſe in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> practiſe there, whether for evil practiſe or miſdemeanor therein, they be not ſubject to the correction and government of the Colledge?</p>
            <p>They all agreed that they are ſubject to the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>3</label> government and correction of the Colledge by an expreſs clauſe of the ſaid Charter enacted, which giveth to the Cenſors <hi>Superviſionem, ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinium, correctionem, &amp; Gubernationem</hi> of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons uſing the practiſe of Medicine within the City.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>4</label> If they may not practiſe without admiſſion of the Colledge (as their Letters patents plainly import)
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:54229:62"/>
Then whether ſuch Graduates are not ſubject to the Examination, without which there were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any admitted, and without which the admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on cannot be approved, becauſe every Graduate is not abſolutely good <hi>ipſo facto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>4</label> It was reſolved by all, that all that practiſed or ſhould practiſe Phyſick, either in <hi>London,</hi> or within the compaſs of ſeven miles of the ſame, muſt ſubmit themſelves to the Examination of the Preſident and Colledge if they be required thereunto by their authority, notwithſtanding any Licence, allowance, or priviledge given them in <hi>Oxford</hi> or <hi>Cambridge,</hi> either by their degree or otherwiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="resolutions">
            <head>Concerning puniſhment and correction againſt Offenders.</head>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>1</label> WHether the Cenſors alone may not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to priſon without Bayl or Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe all Offenders in the practiſe of Phyſick, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute of <hi>primo Mariae,</hi> and how long? Whether till he have paid ſuch Fine as ſhall be aſſeſſed upon him, or have ſubmitted himſelf to their order, and in what manner?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>1</label> They all reſolved, that for not well doing uſing or practiſing the Faculty or Art of Phyſick, or for diſobedience or contempts done and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt any Ordinance made by the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:54229:62"/>
by vertue and according to the power and authority to them granted, they may commit the offenders without Bayl or Mainpriſe, as the words of the Statute are, which they all reſolved could not be altered or interpreted, otherwiſe then the expreſs words of the Statute are.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> Whether they may not commit to priſon for diſobedience and contempt of the private Statutes and Ordinances of the Colledge made for the better government thereof, and for not payment of ſuch reaſonable Fines as ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the Preſident and Cenſors for mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the ſaid Colledge among the Members of the ſame Colledge.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>2</label> They all reſolved, that the Preſident and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge might commit to priſon for offences or diſobedience done or committed againſt any law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Ordinance made by the ſaid Colledge, and might impoſe reaſonable Fines for the breach thereof, and detain the parties committed till theſe Fines were ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>3</label> Whether they may not juſtly take upon every admiſſion a reaſonable ſum of mony for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter maintenance and defraying of neceſſary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences as in other Corporations?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>3</label> They all held that they might take ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſums.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>4</label> Whether thoſe only are to be committed that are offenders in <hi>non bene exequendo faciendo &amp; utendo facultate Medicinae,</hi> as in the Letters patents, and ſuch as are ſufficient and not admitted, are to be ſued for 5 <hi>l.</hi> a month, and not be committed?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="120" facs="tcp:54229:63"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>4</label> They all held, that by the Charter and Acts of Parliament, they might commit offenders and practiſers that offend in <hi>Non bene exequendo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendo &amp; utendo facultate,</hi> but for the committing to priſon of ſuch as practiſe (not being admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Colledge) they held it doubtful, for that the Charter and Statute do in that caſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict a puniſhment of 5 <hi>l.</hi> a moneth againſt ſuch practiſer, without admittance by the Colledge. But they all reſolved, that if the Preſident and Colledge made an Ordinance to prohibit the practiſing of all without admittance under the common Seal of the ſaid Colledge; That for breach and contempt of this Ordinance, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Colledge might both impoſe a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Fine upon the offender, and commit him without Bayl or Mainprize.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>5</label> Whether refuſal to come to be examined upon warning given be not a ſufficient cauſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitment?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>5</label> They all reſolved, that if the Colledge do make an Ordinance, That if any practiſer of Phyſick in <hi>London</hi> or within ſeven miles of the ſame ſhall obſtinately or wilfully refuſe to be examined by the Cenſors of the Colledge in <hi>non bene exequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do faciendo &amp; utendo</hi> the Art of Phyſick or his medicines or receipts, That the ſaid Preſident and Cenſors may commit him to priſon there to remain without Bayl or Mainprize untill he be delivered by the Preſident and Cenſors, and to forfeit and pay to the ſaid Colledge ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſum of money, that the ſame Ordinance
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:54229:63"/>
will be good and lawful. And if any after ſhall offend contrary to the ſame Ordinance, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Cenſors may lawfully commit ſuch of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender to priſon, there to remain without bayl or mainprize untill he ſhall be delivered by the ſaid Preſident and Cenſors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It pleaſed the Lord Chancellor to move theſe Queſtions To the Judges, as material for the execution of the Statutes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Whether the party committed for unskilfull or temerarious practiſe may have an Action of falſe impriſonment againſt them, and thereby draw in queſtion or iſſue, the goodneſs or badneſs of the Phyſick?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
               </label> All reſolved, that the party ſo committed was concluded by the ſentence and Judgement of the four Cenſors of the Colledge of Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Whether if any not admitted to practiſe phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick ſick within <hi>London</hi> or ſeven miles of the ſame, but once, twice, or thrice in one month, be an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt the Charter and Statutes of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reſp. </seg>
               </label> All reſolved he was, if he be a profeſſed Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="trial_proceedings">
            <pb n="122" facs="tcp:54229:64"/>
            <p>AT a Trial had at <hi>Guild hall</hi> before Juſtice <hi>Nicholas, Nov.</hi> 27. 1656. upon an Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, it was found for <hi>Barker</hi> upon theſe words in the Information miſlaid (<hi>by Letters of the ſaid Preſident and Comminalty Sealed</hi>) whereas the words of the Charter are, <hi>Sealed by the Seal of the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Colledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Barkers</hi> Councel at the Bar preſſed it upon the witneſſes whether they gave <hi>Barker</hi> money for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice only, or for Phyſick only, or both; They ſaid that he only ſold his Medicines as Apothecaries and any Free-man of <hi>London</hi> might do. Our Witneſſes ſwore that <hi>Barber</hi> took their money for both.</p>
            <p>Serjeant <hi>Maynard</hi> then urged that the King never gave his aſſent to this Charter as appeareth (ſaid he) by the Rolls of that Seſſion of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a Copy whereof he brought into the Court. And the reaſon then aſſigned was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the uſual words <hi>le Ray le veult</hi> were not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to this Act. But Mr. <hi>Finch</hi> deſired that point might be put upon demur in Law after trial, Serjeant <hi>Maynard</hi> then waved the point.</p>
            <p>After this trial, ſearch was made for the Act upon the Phyſicians Charter at the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> but found that there were no Acts kept there, made ſince the reign of <hi>H.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Then ſearch was made at the Clerk of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Office at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> but not one Act of that Seſſions of Parliament nor any other from
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:54229:64"/>
the 7. to the 22. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. found there, for moſt of the Acts kept there concern only particular actions or perſons.</p>
            <p>But at the Rolls this Charter was found, and that none of that part of the Act which is in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh in the Book of Statutes was there ſet down in writing, but the bare words of the Charter only, at the end whereof theſe words, but plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in another hand (<hi>huc uſque</hi>) were written, and after all this a good large ſpace in the parchment wholly blank left as it ſeems to inſcribe the reſt of the Act.</p>
            <p>After this Charter theſe words ſubſcribed <hi>per ipſum regem,</hi> &amp;c. which words as it appears by all other Acts paſſed in the ſame Roll, and as Mr. <hi>Clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> one of the keepers of the Parliament Rolls told me, in all other Acts made it manifeſt were paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the King himſelf being perſonally preſent in Parliament.</p>
            <p>Upon farther ſearch at the Rolls, I found the Act of Parliament its ſelf, and had it exemplified under the Seal <hi>Dec.</hi> 18. 1658. So that the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter its ſelf is in one Roll, and the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in another diſtinct Roll.</p>
            <p>Now as to that objection, that theſe words <hi>le Roy le veult</hi> are not ſubſcribed to this Act concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Phyſicians, I anſwer, that neither were theſe words ſubſcribed to ſome Acts preceding this, nor to any that followed it. And at the end of all this Roll 'tis ſaid, the King having heard all the Acts recited and read, did confirm them, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Parliament to ſee them all obſerved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:54229:65"/>
               <hi>Raſtals</hi> and <hi>Poultons</hi> Statute Books, our Charter and Exemplification have all of them <hi>per Nomina Praeſidentis Collegii ſeu Communitatis, &amp;c.</hi> But in <hi>Bonhams Caſe</hi> in <hi>Cooks Reports</hi> 'tis <hi>per Nomina Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidentis &amp; Collegii.</hi> 'Twas the opinion of two of our Councel that <hi>Et</hi> would make a variation and nonſuit conſequently. They both ſaid that for the Tithes of <hi>London,</hi> and <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extant but preſcription.</p>
            <p>If a Statute be ſpecial, particular, or private (as this of the Colledge is) then if any man will have benefit by or make uſe of it, or will charge another upon it, he muſt plead and ſhew the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute at large, <hi>vide Shepard</hi> in folio pag. 917. <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton, fol.</hi> 15. 1617.</p>
            <p>Lord chief Baron <hi>Steele</hi> at a Plea holden at <hi>Kingſton</hi> upon <hi>Trent</hi> 1655. the Action being laid in <hi>Nomine Praeſidentis Collegii ſeu Communitatis,</hi> &amp;c. and the Defendants pleading it ought to run ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Cooks Reports,</hi> in <hi>Nomine Praeſidentis &amp; Collegii,</hi> ſalved it thus, by ſaying there was to be put a <hi>Comma</hi> after. <hi>Praeſidentis,</hi> betwixt it and <hi>Collegii,</hi> and ſo did tantamount to <hi>Praeſidis &amp; Collegii.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At a Trial at <hi>Guild-hall</hi> againſt <hi>Trigge</hi> for ill practiſe, Judgment for <hi>Trigge,</hi> becauſe the Colledge could not prove what Medicines he gave, for he made his Medicines privately himſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Blank</hi> for ill practiſe fined by the Cenſors 20 <hi>l.</hi> and upon a <hi>habeas corpus</hi> was remitted to priſon, and paid the Fine. <hi>Ann. l. 2. pag.</hi> 186.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Trigge</hi> fined by the Cenſors for a <hi>Paracenteſis 20 l.</hi> ſent to <hi>Newgate,</hi> and paies the 20 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <pb n="125" facs="tcp:54229:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>14 15. H.8.</head>
            <head type="sub">By Eaſter Record 1656. firſt draught.</head>
            <p>BE it remembred that the Preſident of the Colledge or Comminalty of the faculty of Phyſicians in <hi>London,</hi> who followeth as well for <hi>Charles by the grace of God King of England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith,</hi> &amp;c. as for himſelf, did come before the Barons of this Exchequer the 6. day of <hi>June</hi> this Term in his own perſon, and as well for the ſaid King as for himſelf, did give the Court here to underſtand and to be informed, That one <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Barker</hi> of the Pariſh of St. <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> in the Ward of <hi>Dowgate London,</hi> Gent. between the firſt day of <hi>July</hi> laſt paſt, and the day of the exhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of this Information, that is to ſay, by the ſpace of 11. months at the Pariſh of St. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> aforeſaid, did exerciſe the faculty of Phyſick, the ſaid <hi>Richard Barker</hi> not being admitted to exerciſe the ſaid faculty of Phyſick by the ſaid Preſident and Comminalty by Letter of the ſaid Preſident and Comminalty ſealed with their common Seal, contrary to the form of the Statute in ſuch caſe made and provided: whereupon the ſaid Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as well for the ſaid King as for himſelf pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the advice of the Court in the premiſes. And the ſaid <hi>Richard Barker</hi> for the offence aforeſaid
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:54229:66"/>
may forfeit 55 <hi>l.</hi> of lawful money of <hi>England,</hi> that is to ſay, for every month of the ſaid 11. months in which he did exerciſe the ſaid faculty of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick not being admitted in form aforeſaid 5 <hi>l.</hi> of like lawful money of <hi>England.</hi> And that he the ſaid Preſident may have the moiety of the forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aforeſaid according to the form of the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute aforeſaid, and that the ſaid <hi>Richard Barker</hi> may come here to anſwer the premiſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="document">
            <p>SEcretary <hi>Walſingham</hi> writes a Letter in 88. to the Major and Aldermen of <hi>London,</hi> who had then charged the Colledge with Armes, that they ſhould no more trouble them hereafter, but ſhould permit them to live quietly and free from that charge. <hi>L. Annal. 1. cap. 67. Anno 1614. October</hi> 4. the Colledge being charged with Arms, Sir <hi>William Paddy</hi> pleaded the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the Colledge before Sir <hi>Thomas Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleton</hi> Lord Major and a full Court of Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Sir <hi>Henry Montacue</hi> Recorder, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that in former times by vertue of their Charter and Acts of Parliament, they have been exempted from this ſervice, and that 1. The Statute 14. <hi>H.</hi> 8. confirms not only all Grants, Articles and other things contained in the ſaid Letters Patents; but alſo for enlargement of farther Articles for the ſaid Colledge are to be
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:54229:66"/>
interpreted available to the ſaid Colledge in as large and ample manner as may be taken, thought and conſtrued by the ſame. 2. In <hi>Anno 32. H.</hi> 8. they and every of them of the ſaid body corporate or fellowſhip and their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, ſhall at all time and times be diſcharged to keep any watch or ward in <hi>London</hi> or the Suburbs of the ſame. Here obſerve the word (<hi>any</hi>) which in true right of conſtruction was to be extended as if that clauſe had been in more words expreſſed. 3. In the Act for the Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeons in the firſt entrance there are theſe words: <hi>It was thought expedient by the wiſdome of the land to provide for men expert in the ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Phyſick and Chirurgery.</hi> And therefore when it followeth in their Act of Parliament, that the Chirurgeons by expreſs words are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the bearing of armour, it may truly be inferred that Phyſicians are exempted (as before) from any watch or wards; as alſo Phyſicians here recited in the preamble ſhould receive a greater, or at leaſt the ſame immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, eſpecially ſince Phyſicians are by their Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Act of Parliament Chirurgeons with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out farther examination, and approbation to be had from the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> whereunto mere Chirurgeons are ſubject. An Alderman objects, that by the words of this Act of Parliament, <hi>viz.</hi> bearing of Armour, were to free their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but not to exempt them from the charge of the ſervice.</p>
            <p>Anſwer, That the difference <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:54229:67"/>
and wearing of arms was ſuch, that the very Etymon of the word bearing, as in many other caſes comprehended both, and therefore ſhould give immunity for both. 4. In all foreign or domeſtick wars, Phyſicians do attend the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in perſon, and for this produceth the regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter. The Recorder then peruſing every branch of the Statutes recited, and the reaſons urged, and opening every part thereof at large, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that the Acts of Parliament did extend to give to the Colledge as much immunity as in any ſort to the Chirurgeons. Whereupon the Court deſired a Catalogue of the Members of the Colledge, in number then 41. (which was immediately done) that others not of the Colledge might not delude them, and ſo claim priviledge. Hereupon ordered a diſpenſation of the Colledge from bearing of Arms, and alſo a precept then awarded by the Major and Court to commit all other Phyſicians or Chirurgeons refuſing to bear or find arms, who were not by the Colledge allowed, or Chirurgeons licenced according to form. <hi>L. 2. Annal. pag.</hi> 17, 18.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="act">
            <pb n="129" facs="tcp:54229:67"/>
            <head>Rot Parl. 32 H. 6. M. 17.</head>
            <p>REx adverſa valetudine laborans de aſſenſu Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lii ſui aſsignavit Joannem Arundel. Joannem Saceby, &amp; W. Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cliffe medicos Robertum Warren &amp; Joan Marſhal Chirurgos ad libere miniſtrandum &amp; exequendum in &amp; circa perſonam ſuam Inprimis viz. quod licitè valeant moderare ſibi dietam ſuam &amp; quod poſsint miniſtrare potiones ſyrupos Confectiones laxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivas medicinas clyſteria ſupoſitoria caput purgia gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gariſmata lealnen epithemata fomentationes embro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationes capitis raſuram unctiones emplaſtra, cerata ventoſa cum ſcarificatione vel ſine, Emorodorum Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rificationes &amp;c. Dantes ſingulis in mandatis quod in executione praemiſſorum ſint intendentes, &amp;c. <hi>Upon this four things are to be obſerved. 1. That no Phyſick ought to be given to the King with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good warrant. 2. This Warrant ought to be made by advice of his Councel. 3. They ought to miniſter no other Phyſick then that is ſet down in writing. 4. That they may uſe the aid of thoſe Chirurgeons named in the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but of no Apothecary, but to prepare and do all things themſelves,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And the reaſon of all this is, the precious regard had of the health and ſafety of the King which is the head of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</hi> Cokes inſtitutes pars 4. pag. 251.</p>
            <p>Phyſicians &amp; Chirurgeons ſoient ſages en lour facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties eyent ſans les conſciences cy que rien ne ent failli a
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:54229:68"/>
faire cure ſilz ne ſcavoyent a bone chiefe mitter ou ſilz a bon chiefe ſcav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yent &amp; entre-mettent nequidant folle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ou negligentment iſſent que ilz mittont froid pur chaude ou le revers, ou trop peu de cure, ou nemi mitter un due diligence &amp; noſmement en arſons &amp; ad abſciſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons que ſont defend a faire forſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> al peril des meſters ſi lour patients morerent ou perdent memorie en tiels caſes ſont ilz homicides ou Mayhemers. <hi>Mirror cap. 4. § de Homicide verb (daut' part.)</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>To Our truſty and welbeloved the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident and Cenſors of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Phyſicians within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <signed>JAMES REX.</signed>
            </opener>
            <p>TRuſty and welbeloved We greet you well; Whereas the Art of Phyſick by many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned men (making gain by the profeſſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to the great hurt and prejudice of many of Our loving ſubjects) is much abuſed in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Our Realm, but eſpecially in our City of <hi>London</hi> and the Suburbs thereof, the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof (as touching the practiſe of the ſaid
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:54229:68"/>
Art, and the practitioners thereof) being by the Lawes and Statutes of the Realm committed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the Preſident and Cenſors of our Colledge of Phyſicians, and you having alſo from us by our Letters Patents more ample authority for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion and correction of ſuch delinquents: We therefore minding ſo far as in us lieth the ſpeedy reformation of all ſuch abuſes and inconveniences, do by theſe preſents as heretofore yet more ſtrictly charge and command you the Preſident and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors aforeſaid to call before you all ſuch irregular and ignorant practitioners as contrary to our Lawes and authority do abuſe that Art, and to examine their ſufficiency, and ſuch as you ſhall find not ſufficient to puniſh for their bad practiſe according to our Lawes in that caſe provided. And Whereas we are credibly given to underſtand that many having been puniſhed and warned by you to deſiſt from any further practiſe do yet obſtinately notwithſtanding perſiſt in their former contempt of our Lawes and commandments, We will and command you that you proceed againſt ſuch delinquents with all ſeverity according to the tenor of our ſaid Letters Patents and the due courſe of our Lawes, by fine and impriſonment, or by cauſing them to enter into recognizance with condition reſtraining them to offend any more, or otherwiſe as the caſe ſhall require and ſhall be agreeable to juſtice. And our will and pleaſure is, that ſuch offenders as ſhall be ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, ſhall there remain without being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, unleſs it be upon their conformity and
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:54229:69"/>
ſubmiſſion to you the ſaid preſident and Cenſors, or other due courſe of Law wherein we require all our Judges and Juſtices that they be very careful and circumſpect not to do any thing that may give encouragement to ſuch offenders, by enlarging any ſuch too eaſily or without due exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the cauſes of their commitment, firſt calling thereto the ſaid Preſident and Cenſors or ſome of them to declare the true reaſons and cauſes thereof. And whereas we are given to underſtand that oftentimes upon the ſolicitation of ſome or other friend or perſon of quality ſutor to you for the ſaid delinquents after their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction you have been moved to wink at their faults, and neglect their puniſhment, to the great prejudice of the health of many our poor ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects: Our will and pleaſure is, and we do here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſtraightly charge and command you, that henceforth neither for favour, friendſhip, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of any you forbear the juſt cenſure and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment due by our Lawes unto ſuch delinquents as you ſhall anſwer to us on the contrary at your peril, and that you require the aid and aſſiſtance of the Lord Major and Aldermen of our City of <hi>London</hi> (whom by our Letters we have ſo required to do) for your better expedition in the execution of this our Royal Will and Commandment, not doubting but that you with more care will ſeek to ſuppreſs ſuch intolerable abuſes, and ſatisfie our truſts in this caſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to you.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given under our Signet at our Pallace of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> 
                  <date>the ſecond day of <hi>July</hi> in
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:54229:69"/>
the twentieth year of our Reign of <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of <hi>Scotland</hi> the five and fiftieth.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="events">
            <p>The Kings Councel about the ſame time ſend a Warrant for Attachment of Empericks, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to all Juſtices of Peace, Mayors, Sheriffs, Baileys, Conſtables, Headboroughs, and all other his Majeſties Officers and Miniſters within the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>London</hi> and ſeven miles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Butler</hi> made extraordinary Chirurgeon to the King, was permitted by the Lord Keeper to be ſued. <hi>Annal. pag.</hi> 97.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Blank</hi> had a <hi>Habeas Corpus</hi> 1637. but by the Judges was ſent back to priſon, having been fined by the Cenſors 20 <hi>l ob malam praxia,</hi> though he had Letters Patents from the Archbiſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="brief">
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:54229:70"/>
            <head>A Brief of what King <hi>James</hi> grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and defective in former Grants.</head>
            <p n="1">1. THat whereas they were by the former Act enabled to keep Courts and Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and thither to convent, and there to puniſh offenders, but had no certain place limited; now they have power to purchaſe a Hall peculiar for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Whereas they are by the former Act ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to purchaſe only 12 <hi>l.</hi> revenue to the ſaid Colledge; now they have power by the Letters Patents to purchaſe to the value of 100 Marks <hi>per annum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Whereas the Colledge is authoriſed of old by ſuite to recover from all practiſers in Phyſick without approbation from the Colledge 5 <hi>l.</hi> a moneth. By the laſt Letters Patents they are au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed to puniſh ſuch offenders contempt in not coming to the Colledge upon the Preſident and Cenſors Warrants: or in refuſing to anſwer being come by a Fine of 40 <hi>s.</hi> and impriſonment till they have paid the ſame. And for practiſing without Licenſe, upon conviction they may fine the offenders in 3 <hi>l.</hi> and impriſon them for ſeven daies, and untill they have paid ſuch fines.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whereas of old the Colledge might puniſh evil practitioners in Phyſick within their Limits by a Fine of 20 <hi>l.</hi> By their new Grant they may
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:54229:70"/>
examine for Witneſſes againſt them (upon oath) Chirurgeons, and Apothecaries, and Druggiſts; And the Servants and Attendants upon the Sick (and no others) and fine them 20 <hi>s.</hi> for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to come or anſwer before them; and upon conviction they may fine evill Practiſers in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick 10 <hi>l.</hi> and impriſon them for 14. daies, and until they pay the ſame Fine.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Whereas of old the Phyſicians had power to ſearch the Shops and Ware-houſes of all Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, Druggiſts, Diſtillers and Sellers of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines; and finding unwholſome Drugs and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, to burn them: By their new Grant they are authoriſed to fine ſuch offenders in 3 <hi>l.</hi> and to commit them untill they pay the ſame.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whereas of old the one half of all Fines to be impoſed by the Colledge were granted to the ſaid Incorporation, in their new Grant all the ſaid Fines are granted to them; paying to the King his Heirs and Succeſſors yearly 6 <hi>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. In the new Grant the Preſident and Cenſors are enabled to take Recognizances to the Kings Majeſty of Offenders convicted of unlawful or evil practiſe, with condition that they ſhall not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit like future offences, and to impriſon them if they refuſe to be ſo bound.</p>
            <p n="8">8. In the new Grant, the Collegiates are freed from bearing or finding of Arms, becauſe they are ſubject to ſerve in perſon, both in the Kings Armies, and in his Fleets upon occaſion.</p>
            <p n="9">9. His Majeſty promiſeth his Royal Aſſent for enacting this Patent the next Parliament.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
